<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Parliamentum pacificum, or, The happy union of King &amp; people in an healing Parliament heartily wish't for, and humbly recommended / by a true Protestant and no dissenter.</title>
            <author>Northleigh, John, 1657-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15979</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12951874</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12951874</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95944</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95944)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 723:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Parliamentum pacificum, or, The happy union of King &amp; people in an healing Parliament heartily wish't for, and humbly recommended / by a true Protestant and no dissenter.</title>
                  <author>Northleigh, John, 1657-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 75 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by M. Turner ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Northleigh. cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95944:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Parliamentum Pacificum:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, THE Happy Union OF KING &amp; People IN AN <hi>Healing Parliament:</hi> Heartily <hi>Wiſh't</hi> for, and <hi>Humbly Recommended,</hi> By a <hi>True Proteſtant,</hi> and no <hi>Diſſenter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>M. Turner</hi> At the <hi>Lamb</hi> in <hi>Holborn,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:95944:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>White-Hall, <date>
                     <hi>February</hi> 15. 1687/8.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Let this be Printed,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>SUNDERLAND</hi> P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95944:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:95944:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95944:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Parliamentum Pacificum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE deſign of this enſuing Diſcourſe, you will ſoon ſee, is not only directed to the <hi>Plainer</hi> Sort; for then it would ſuperſede all ſort of <hi>Explanation;</hi> but may ſerve to ſatisfy ſome Perſons of a <hi>finer</hi> Mould, and who to be ſure in the buſineſs of the State will make a better Figure: I am ſure the Good that it deſigns is ſo <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> that it onely Labours to make but <hi>One</hi> Intereſt of <hi>KING</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> to prove that diſagreeing Parliaments can never Procure the Kingdoms Peace; that the reaſonable Deſires of the Prince (though unreaſonably repreſented) are really conſiſtent with the Service of the Country, and that 'tis poſſible for a Courtier, or a Papiſt, to make a good Patriot; and, for this purpoſe, as we direct our Diſcourſe to thoſe that are to <hi>Chooſe</hi> our Senators, ſo we ſhall as humbly ſubmit it to the Conſideration of ſuch as are <hi>Choſen,</hi> that both <hi>tender</hi> Scruples, and <hi>learned</hi> Objections, may be ſo far ſatisfi'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd, as to conſent and conſpire in Unanimous Endeavours, for the ſetling of a Nation; an <hi>Healing Parliament,</hi> and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' I do not here prefix a fine Frontiſpiece, with as foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh an Explanation of it, yet I think fit to let the Reader know that the Title Page will be beſt explain'd by thoſe that follow it, when I ſhall ſhew Him:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That We once had a <hi>Parliament</hi> that was call'd the <hi>Healing One.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. When I ſhall <hi>ſhew</hi> the <hi>Manner</hi> How it was made to be ſo.</item>
               <item>3. The <hi>Maxims</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> that it <hi>Took.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. The <hi>wholeſome Effects</hi> that <hi>follow'd</hi> from it's ſober Conſultations.</item>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95944:4"/>
               <item>5. The <hi>Ways</hi> that are taken now to <hi>hinder</hi> the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch another.</item>
               <item>6. The <hi>Means</hi> that may be us'd to prevent the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Inſinuations of ſuch as would <hi>Obſtruct</hi> it.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT I. That We had a Parliament call'd the <hi>Healing One.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Parliament then, that was call'd this Healing One,</hi> and that by the beſt of Authorities, the <hi>KING's;</hi> by the moſt merciful Monarch, <hi>His Late Majeſty,</hi> that Prince of pious Memory, giving in expreſs terms of his own, this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter at their diſſolution, <hi>That to all Poſterity, it ſhould be Call'd the Bleſſed and the Healing Parliament:</hi> This <hi>Parliament</hi> I ſay, that had ſo <hi>good</hi> a Name, and that from ſo <hi>good</hi> a KING (tho' another is Fam'd for <hi>Working Wonders)</hi> brought about I think the Beſt of <hi>Miracles:</hi> the <hi>Reſtoration</hi> of their KING, and in that the Succeſſion of the <hi>Preſent,</hi> and was the ſame that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the <hi>Pack't Aſſembly,</hi> which upon the admiſſion of the <hi>Secluded Members</hi> diſſolv'd it ſelf, on the <hi>ſeventeenth</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1659. and with their expiring breath, ſummon'd <hi>that</hi> which is the ſubject we inſiſt on to ſucceed them, on the <hi>Twenty fifth</hi> of <hi>April</hi> next enſuing: <hi>That</hi> which had ſo <hi>glorious</hi> a Character of ſo <hi>great</hi> a KING, and whoſe <hi>wholeſome</hi> Conſtitutions, for the <hi>Healing</hi> our Breaches, and Curing our Diviſions, I would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly <hi>recommend,</hi> not only to the Nation for the next <hi>Great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</hi> but in the Words of this Royal Character, for a <hi>Pattern to all Poſterity;</hi> and ſuch an <hi>One</hi> will only be able to purſue the gracious <hi>Deſigns</hi> of our <hi>Preſent</hi> Soveraign, as well as merit the glorious Elogy of the <hi>Paſt,</hi> ſettle ſuch a Laſting Liberty, and Peace, as may not only ſecure it to his deſiring Subjects, for his <hi>own</hi> Life (but in his own Words too) to <hi>Poſterity,</hi> to make it a <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> that thoſe that come after may never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Alter it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95944:4"/>
               <head>SECT. II. The Manner <hi>How</hi> it was made to be ſo.</head>
               <p>I Wiſh I had no ſuch pertinent Proof for Application, to tell the Church of <hi>England</hi> that has hitherto been fam'd, not only for a Loyalty <hi>boaſted</hi> of, but <hi>approv'd,</hi> that this <hi>Healing Parliament</hi> of thoſe times, was brought about not only againſt their Expectation, but alſo againſt the very Proviſions of two direct <hi>Teſts</hi> to prevent it, which ſeems to intimate that <hi>divine</hi> Providence in its deſigns for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Peace,</hi> can never be baffl'd by <hi>Mens</hi> Politicks, and that the Meaſures of <hi>humane</hi> Wiſdom, for their own preſervation, may be much the ſame with <hi>Ill</hi> Men, as well as with thoſe that are really <hi>Good;</hi> and that the ſame ſort of Oaths &amp; Abjurations which the Preſent Eſtabliſh't Church has fram'd for it's <hi>ſupport</hi> (or as ſome ſay <hi>Inſupportable Dominion)</hi> were alſo contriv'd againſt the Meeting of this <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> by thoſe very Villains that had rais'd the <hi>Warr: Ab Hoſte doceri,</hi> is a <hi>good</hi> Maxim in a <hi>Camp Martial;</hi> but an <hi>ill</hi> Leſſon to be Learnt by a <hi>Church,</hi> even tho' She were <hi>Militant</hi> too.</p>
               <p>I do not ſay but that <hi>good</hi> Men may take the ſame meaſures for maintaining their <hi>legal</hi> Power, that have been us'd by the <hi>Bad</hi> for a <hi>bare</hi> ſupport of Uſurpation, but then they ought to take great heed too (eſpecially in Caſes of Conſcience) leſt any <hi>force</hi> of Compulſion betray the <hi>Weakneſs</hi> of their <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis known then upon Record, and may be Read in the Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the Commons, that the Seditious Aſſembly of <hi>Forty One,</hi> whom the Laws of the Land have declar'd to be ſo, and that Treaſonable too (and ſure then the Church ſo Signaliz'd for Loyalty, will never look on their <hi>Proceedings</hi> as good Preſidents:) 'tis certain I ſay, that <hi>thoſe</hi> fram'd all the <hi>Teſts</hi> and <hi>Oaths</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, for the <hi>Excluding</hi> all the reſt of the Nation, from all <hi>Offices</hi> in the <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> in the <hi>Church;</hi> and well they might; for <hi>well</hi> they knew, had their <hi>Cauſe</hi> been <hi>better,</hi> it would have born it ſelf out againſt the <hi>Worſt</hi> of Men; but it being ſo <hi>bad,</hi> they might fear to truſt the <hi>Beſt</hi> of Subjects; for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95944:5"/>
this, then, they fram'd their <hi>Negative Oaths, Engagements, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Solemn Oath, Oath of Abjuration;</hi> and in their dying Votes, and expiring breath, contriv'd theſe <hi>Tests</hi> againſt the Concord and Peace of the Parliament that was expected. <hi>Firſt,</hi> J. A. B. <hi>do acknowledge, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> are; that the War un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken by both houſes of Parliament, againſt the forces rais'd by the King, was juſt and lawful; 2d That Magiſtracy and Miniſtry are the Ordinances of God.</hi> So here they had found out a <hi>Teſt</hi> too, and that for Church and State, and <hi>ordered</hi> that thoſe who would not acknowledge <hi>this,</hi> were never to be admitted into any Office of <hi>Truſt,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> the words of 25 <hi>Car.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Military;</hi> and made uncapable to be Elected to ſerve as members in the next Parliament that was ſuddenly to ſit.</p>
               <p>The Church-Royaliſts, and Clergy then, as the Narratives <hi>of thoſe times</hi> tell us, who had ſuffer'd ſo much in the ſervice of their Sovereign (when it was their turn to ſuffer by ſuch a <hi>Teſt)</hi> look't upon it as too ſevere a Tryal, nay, Preacht, and Pray'd it down too as a piece of Tyranny, and Perſecution, tho it affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them <hi>only</hi> in their politick capacity, and no perſon was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by it, with any Pecuniary mulct, or Corporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: This their own Authors ſay they thought <hi>hard,</hi> to ſuffer <hi>only</hi> for their Fidelity to their <hi>Sovereign;</hi> and will theſe moſt unreaſonable men, moſt injuriouſly ſuppoſe it Juſtice and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that others are expos'd to be incapacitated for <hi>Truſt,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from <hi>Office,</hi> debar'd of birth-right; to be baniſht, fin'd, impriſon'd, and fairly hang'd, and that <hi>only</hi> for their Faith to their <hi>God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gentlemen, Theſe are great <hi>Truths,</hi> unleſs our Annals <hi>Ly.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of florid inſinuations, but a ſober and modeſt repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of matter of fact, which we ſhall further apply to the Circumſtances of our preſent time.</p>
               <p>And pray, what benefit and ty, after all, had thoſe Spiritual Bonds, and Coercives of the Conſcience and Soul, ſave only to enſnare people into <hi>Perjury,</hi> or puniſh them for <hi>not</hi> being <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd?</hi> (i. e.) ruining their <hi>eſtates</hi> in <hi>this</hi> world, becauſe they would not compound for their <hi>inheritance</hi> in the <hi>next.</hi> What ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect had that formidable Declaration, &amp; <hi>Teſt</hi> of the Two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, againſt the Members of the enſuing Parliament that was to Sit? why, our Hiſtory tells us, theſe their hard Excluſions
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95944:5"/>
were as little heeded by their Electors; the recover'd Nation began to revive its drooping ſpirits; it ſaw diſmal oppreſſion, and fearful Tyranny, like a cloudy ſhade flying from the Land, when the refreſhing Sun breaks forth with his ray, and equally diſpenſes his benefits to <hi>all</hi> below, <hi>Liberty</hi> was <hi>then</hi> too the long'd for bleſſing, and the Univerſal cry, <hi>peace</hi> of conſcience, <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of fouls, and a <hi>free</hi> Parliament were <hi>heard</hi> in the <hi>Land,</hi> where nought had been but <hi>complaining in the ſtreets;</hi> the freemen and freeholders began to think themſelves truly free, &amp; that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in their Choice of Repreſentatives, their Nations birth-right, and native Inheritance, and that notwithſtanding thoſe <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Oaths,</hi> and <hi>Teſts</hi> of Excluſion, and their being baniſh't both Houſes with an <hi>I. A. B.</hi> Neither will the Common Notion of Oaths impos'd by an <hi>unlawful</hi> Authority, being utterly void, ſatisfy all People; we have ſeen it would not in the Caſe of the <hi>Covenant;</hi> &amp; in ſome ſeveral perſons, that have been good caſuiſts too, it being an invocation of the ſame juſt God, tho' admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter'd with injuſtice by men, and which perhaps in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> the moſt <hi>Legal</hi> Government, (as many think) cannot well impoſe.</p>
               <p>It was at <hi>That</hi> time, the people began to think of chuſing ſuch Repreſentatives, as ſhould reſcue them from unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Laws, and a bondage more than that of the <hi>body:</hi> no perſons then pretended Loyalty to a Party, all were Diſſenters but thoſe in <hi>Arms;</hi> all the Nation big with Expectation of this bleſſed and reconciling Parliament: nay, moſt of the very <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> it ſelf, ſigning an <hi>engagement,</hi> to ſubmit to all it's conſultations; none were diſturb'd with apprehenſions of its approach, none <hi>caſt down;</hi> but ſome in <hi>high places,</hi> and ſuch as were likely to <hi>fall</hi> from a power of doing miſchief; <hi>That</hi> let <hi>Lambert</hi> out of the Tower, and led him into the field; <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and a <hi>fear of Peace: That</hi> Publiſht <hi>Papers</hi> too, to create Jealouſies of <hi>that</hi> enſuing Parliament; and the boldeſt of them too, was a <hi>Letter,</hi> not to a <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> but as ſent <hi>from Bruſſels:</hi> the Church of England-Loyaliſts then, were <hi>full</hi> of <hi>Addreſſes, Declarations,</hi> ſubſcrib'd by <hi>Nobility, Gentry, Clergy,</hi> full of condeſcention to all <hi>tender Conſciences;</hi> with theſe very ſoft terms &amp; expreſſions of <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</note> 
                  <hi>Publique Liberty, Publique Peace, National Intereſt; laying aſide all mention of Parties, and Factions; and burying all Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours,</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:95944:6"/>
                  <hi>and Animoſities:</hi> and had before agreed in a <hi>reconciling Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation,</hi> of Epiſcopal, Presbyterian, and Independant, and <hi>all,</hi> but Papiſt Church-government: and certainly it will not recommend much the demeanor of this Eſtabliſht Church, when it ſhall be ſaid with <hi>Truth,</hi> that ſhe was then only <hi>meek,</hi> when <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled;</hi> and then alone <hi>merciful,</hi> when ſhe could not <hi>hurt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wiſh I could not put an end to this Section with another ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that ſeems to have ſome affinity to the juncture of affairs afoot: As it was the Plot of that Parliament that had created all our troubles, at their expiration, to put a <hi>teſt</hi> to the Loyalty of the next that was to ſucceed; or rather a <hi>tryal</hi> of their affection to their Treaſon and Uſurpation: So alſo there was a contrivance upon the Aſſembling of that <hi>Healing Parliament,</hi> to have Ejected moſt of the Members after they were met, by Vertue of thoſe very Votes, and <hi>Teſts</hi> of their opinion of the <hi>War,</hi> and of the Miniſtry and Magiſtracy being only from <hi>God.</hi> I mention this as appoſite too, becauſe 'tis more than probable, that the Contrivances of the late <hi>Teſts,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to debar people of their Birth-right, their Peerage, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Parliament, they may move again <hi>Now</hi> to have all Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers excluded for their Opinions, and that they cannot take the <hi>Oaths;</hi> as if the belief of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> would turn the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements</hi> of the <hi>man</hi> too, and unqualify a perſon, for the affairs of his Country; as if a Coventicle was impoſſible to afford a Burgher, that underſtood the Conſtitution of his own Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: But certainly there may be ſome means found out for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viating ſuch an inconvenience; and ſure the KING, who by the reſolution of the Laws, and the greateſt Judges of it, can <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with thoſe <hi>Oaths</hi> to be taken in any <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Judicature;</hi> can by an argument <hi>a Majori</hi> extend his diſpenſation to ſuch as cannot take it in an Houſe of Commons, which is <hi>none;</hi> unleſs it ſhould ſo fall out too, as an officer upon the paſſing thoſe former <hi>Teſts</hi> told General Monk, while he was talking of a <hi>new</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>and thoſe qualifications: they themſelves, being to be Judges of themſelves, it may ſo happen, that the Major part may be of ſuch, as are not themſelves Qualify'd.</hi> And I may add to the preſent caſe, <hi>of ſuch</hi> as may not be willing, or care, that others ſhould ſo <hi>Qualify</hi> themſelves for the ſervice of their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country;</hi> as in their opinions muſt make them renounce their <hi>Heaven,</hi> and deny their <hi>GOD.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95944:6"/>
But we muſt not leave this Subject yet, without anſwering two Objections, wherewith the partial, &amp; concern'd, will be ſure to attack us in the rear; and therefore 'tis fit to face about to confute them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> Then, that the power which oppreſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> was an abſolute uſurpation, and terminated in a <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> not to be indur'd; the product of a deviliſh Rebellion, and the remains of a raging War.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That thoſe which ſuffer'd under her Reign, have had this aſſurance, and benefit too, that it ſhall always be by the known Laws of the Land, and Statutes of the Realm: whereas all thoſe <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Engagements, Votes</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> we ſo inſignificantly mention, were juſt no Laws at all; ſo that they ſuffer'd <hi>by nothing,</hi> as well as <hi>for</hi> it.</p>
               <p>To this it may be as readily replyed, that <hi>all</hi> ſufferings (if againſt all ſenſe and reaſon, to the ruining men for crimes they cannot but commit) are certainly the <hi>ſame</hi> to the <hi>ſufferers</hi> in the Penalties and Pains, they are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, whatever be the Lawfulneſs of the Authority that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts them: 'Tis as ſmall advantage to a man that has all his goods confiſcated for the Twenty pounds a Month, to think he was ruin'd by an Act of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as if he had been plunder'd by an <hi>Army</hi> of <hi>Olivers;</hi> and as little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for the poor Prieſt that muſt be Hang'd for his Habit, to ſay, he dyes <hi>Legally,</hi> as if he had been Knockt on the Head for taking the Wall. Juſtice and Equity will be ſtill the ſame, whatever are the various Revolutions of a Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick State; and founded upon Eternal <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as ſome Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims in the Schools, upon the ſame <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They muſt be ſoon ſatisfy'd too, and with as much Reverence to thoſe Mighty Powers; that no Power on <hi>Earth,</hi> no <hi>Humane</hi> Conſtitution, can make Statutes againſt the Decrees of <hi>Heaven,</hi> or reſiſt an Omnipotency that is <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine;</hi> their Dictates, they ſay, are <hi>Spirit</hi> that influences the <hi>Will:</hi> And will any man ſay <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> ſhall oppoſe it? <hi>Souls</hi> may be ſaid to have a <hi>Property</hi> too that cannot be violated by the Sanctions of an Humane Aſſembly; nor Perſons made to ſuffer for obeying the <hi>Divine</hi> dictates of their Devouteſt thought; or following the <hi>Natural</hi> Principles of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95944:7"/>
Education: The <hi>one</hi> of which even a Moral <hi>Turk</hi> will tell you, muſt not, cannot be oppos'd; and any honeſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then in Philoſophy, teach us the difficulty to Proſelyte <note n="*" place="margin">Naturam expellas furca licet uſque recurret <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or pervert it; and that certainly in leſſer concerns than the Salvation of a <hi>Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Diſſenters repreſent their ſufferings in all their addreſſes and Complaints as <hi>Tyrannical</hi> too, they are ſure the beſt Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of their miſeries that groan under them, and there may be <hi>Tyranny</hi> too in the <hi>Laws,</hi> tho the Legiſlators had a <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Power to make them; but theſe very <hi>Laws</hi> too have been ſtrain'd by <note n="*" place="margin">Ryots made and Routs of Meetings.</note> Conſtruction, and ſo they Sympathiz'd with thoſe under Uſurpation, and ſuffer'd by <hi>none at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To cloſe this Section, with the ſimilitude of the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of affairs, to Crown all, the <hi>KING</hi> himſelf <hi>then,</hi> like his other ſelf <hi>now;</hi> his only, and Lawful Succeſſor; intimated his deſigns againſt the opening of the firſt Seſſion of that <hi>Free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament:</hi> That he intended a <hi>freedom</hi> from all Penalties, and ſuffering for Religion, promis'd it to General <hi>Monk,</hi> and in his Declarations repreſented his readineſs to Conſent to any Act of <hi>Parliament, for the full granting that Indulgence.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Motives was that Miraculous Reſtoration facilitated, upon theſe foundations was fixt that firm (and what perhaps might have been a more laſting Peace too) had not the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful importunities of a prevailing <hi>Church,</hi> interrupted the felicity to the diſturbance of the <hi>State.</hi> Gentlemen, the Caſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> was once in Common with ſome Diſſenters, and no leſs hard than theirs is now; they ſuffer'd (you ſee) together once from a prevailing Party; and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> was certainly <hi>then</hi> as <hi>dear</hi> to them, as this <hi>Religion Eſtabliſht</hi> by <hi>Law;</hi> and <hi>that</hi> from their own mouths (if his Majeſty may take their words for it) was alway <hi>dearer to them than their lives:</hi> It was as great a Crime to them <hi>then</hi> to have a Common Prayer, as to a Diſſenter now to make uſe of the Directory; Her book of Liturgy was lookt on <hi>then</hi> as bad as that of the Maſs, and all her Canon and Rubrick, no more to be receiv'd than a Calendar of Red Letters, or the Rituals of <hi>Rome.</hi> Alas! What a mighty Metamorphoſis the felicity of ſome peoples affairs can produce, to the forgetting of their misfortunes; all their fellow-ſufferers, and even the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95944:7"/>
of their own Souls. The Diſſenters deſire to come juſt to the Circumſtances they were in, at the late <hi>KING</hi>'s Reſtoration. And why for Godſake! muſt this <hi>Eſtabliſht Church</hi> turn truly <hi>Militant,</hi> not only againſt all others, but it ſelf? And like that of <hi>Epheſus, Leave her firſt Love;</hi> and as ſome ſay, <hi>her firſt Faith too;</hi> to forget that compaſſion ſhe had for ſuch Sufferers, and her own ſenſe and opinion that ſuch ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings were moſt ſevere. What judgment can ſeriouſly be made by Sober Perſons; to what will impartial people im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute this her <hi>hot</hi> Zeal againſt Diſſenters, that in the dawning of her Reſtitution was hardly <hi>Luke-warm?</hi> Will it not give occaſion to ſay, that ſhe muſt anſwer for her ſelf, like the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odicean</hi> too? <hi>Becauſe, ſays ſhe, I am rich now, and increaſed with goods, and have need of nothing.</hi> And if it be ſo, that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters were promis'd <hi>then</hi> an Exemption from Penalties for <hi>matters of meer Religion;</hi> and the KING, Parliament, and Church, thought it meet, as matter of fact will make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, then certainly all this cry will ſound very harſh, and <hi>unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> againſt this preſent Prince, that has greater <hi>reaſons</hi> for it; when he <hi>only</hi> performs the promiſes of his Pious Predeceſſor, gratifies the deſires of <hi>his</hi> Reſtoring Parliament; and anſwers the very <hi>firſt</hi> Petitions of his People.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. The <hi>Maxims,</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> that it took.</head>
               <p>ANd now by the Diviſion of this Diſcourſe, we are come to the <hi>Third Point; The Maxims and Methods that were taken by this Healing Parliament.</hi> It met upon the Twenty Fifth of <hi>April</hi> (and who knows but about <hi>that</hi> time our next may meet) and may that Epoche of their Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, prove as great an Omen of their good Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: it found the Kingdom moſt unhappily confus'd with Diverſities of Opinions in the ways of worſhipping their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95944:8"/>
God; it found the ſevere Laws, of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> KING <hi>James,</hi> and <hi>Car.</hi> 1. very ineffectual for the ſuppreſſing of what was call'd Schiſm and Diſſention: For this reaſon they took care in the firſt place in their <hi>Act for Confirming of Miniſters;</hi> That none ſhould be <hi>Ejected</hi> for their paſt Non-conformity from 42 to 60, unleſs ſuch as had in the time of Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Ejected</hi> others. <hi>This</hi> was agreeable to what the KING had firſt propos'd to them; both before <hi>privately,</hi> and afterward at the <hi>publick</hi> opening of the Parliament: for <hi>this</hi> the Lord Chancellor, in their firſt Adjournment, was order'd to tell them from the KING, in theſe Terms:</p>
               <p>That no ſort of Piety and Godlineſs, ſhould be turn'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Lord Chancellors Speech on that Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> terms of ſlander and reproach, or diſtinguiſh between the Court, the City, or the Country. <hi>He was order'd further to tell them,</hi> That (by that favourable <hi>Act</hi> for confirming of Miniſters) his Majeſty was ſenſible he had gratify'd many worthy, and Pious Men, and ſuch as ſhould alway receive freſh evidence of his Majeſties favor and Kindneſs. <hi>In that Parliament he had this Direction to tell them,</hi> Of the ſad conſideration, that the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in Religion ſhould be the ground of Animoſities, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Revenge, Paſſions which the Divine Nature exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly abhor'd: <hi>That the Bloody Wars proceeded from thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions:</hi> And <hi>that</hi> (however deſcanted on, by men that have a mind to be Seditious) <hi>is juſt the ſame, what His preſent Majeſty was pleas'd to ſignify to be His Senſe too, in his late Declaration for Indulgence.</hi> The Ld. Chancellor further declar'd, <hi>That</hi> the marks of a true Church, were Charity to one another. He tells them, That this Diſquiſition had Coſt his Majeſty many a <hi>Sigh,</hi> many a <hi>Sad Hour:</hi> That he had taken pains to Compoſe them with Learned and Pious men, of different Perſwaſions, which they ſhould ſhortly ſee by a Declaration he would Publiſh on that occaſion, by which they ſhould ſee his great Indulgence, to thoſe who can have a <hi>Protection</hi> from their <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to differ from their brethren: Exhorting them all, to be but pleas'd themſelves, and perſwade others to be ſo. <hi>Thus</hi> ended that Seſſion, and was Adjourn'd to the Sixth of <hi>November</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               <p>Hitherto, you ſee there was no <hi>Penal Statutes</hi> made, no <hi>Force</hi> to be put upon <hi>Peoples Conſcience;</hi> and the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95944:8"/>
                  <hi>ſtill</hi> to be ſafe, without making of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> ſuffer.</p>
               <p>Purſuant to theſe Gracious Sentiments of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and prudent Reſolutions of the <hi>Parliament;</hi> The KING, before their Meeting again, Publiſh't a Declaration, concerning Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Affairs, full of gracious Conceſſions, to Reconcile all different Opinions in Religion: And ſuch was the Peaceable Reſult of that <hi>Royal Indulgence,</hi> (for it was really no other) that <hi>all</hi> Subjects ſeem'd to be ſatisfy'd; <hi>all</hi> Differences recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd, and the <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelf afterward giving the KING publick Thanks, for his Pious Inclination to Peace and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. To purſue it further, The <hi>Lord Chancellor</hi> had Liberty to offer Biſhopricks and Deanaries to thoſe that Labour'd for this Reconciliation; ſome accepted, others refuſed: a Commiſſion was iſſued out for an Agreement upon ſome Alterations in the Liturgy, as were requiſite to ſatisfy ſome Tender Conſciences: And the Miniſters met upon it afterward at <hi>Sion Colledge,</hi> and wou'd have <hi>agreed</hi> on a Model of Epiſcopacy. Here was an <hi>Agreement</hi> between KING, <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> but it was too great an Happineſs to laſt long: thoſe that had more cruel Inclinations, and aſpir'd to be ſo far powerful, as to puniſh for Non-conformity, foreſaw that this Parliament would never put them in a Capacity to do it; and ſo prevail'd, that on the <hi>Twenty Ninth</hi> of <hi>December</hi> following, was Diſſolv'd this <hi>Reconciling Parliament,</hi> though with the foremention'd Elogys of that <hi>Famous</hi> PRINCE; who, as he was beyond all Character, beſt underſtood how to give One, which he did here to this Effect, That it ſhould be Call'd to all <hi>Poſterity, The Bleſſed, and the Healing Parliament:</hi> So alſo, he broke out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this more Exalted Encomium, and Emphatical Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; <hi>That it ſhould be a Rule to his Actions and Councils, to Conſider; what is</hi> ſuch <hi>a Parliament like to think of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of Mine, or this Action?</hi> And in this Opinion of his <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> (though nothing can add more to it's Fame, after ſuch a Panegyrick from it's PRINCE) was he ſeconded by all Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians that Deſcribe it, who tell us, <hi>Never did</hi> KING <hi>and Parliament better Agree, never was a Parliament</hi> begun <hi>with greater Expectation,</hi> and onely <hi>Ended</hi> with leſs ſatisfaction in laſting no longer. Others call it the <hi>Happy Parliament,</hi> that aſſur'd the Foundations, rais'd the Structure of our Antient En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95944:9"/>
Monarchy: And Mr. <hi>Cowley,</hi> the ſweeteſt of our Bards, ſufficiently ſings it's Praiſes in his <hi>Ode</hi> on the <hi>Reſtoration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it happen'd here, as it always does, where the Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and <hi>Power</hi> of the PRINCE, makes the <hi>Clergy Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotentiaries;</hi> when they began to <hi>find</hi> their Strength, they aſſoon began to <hi>uſe</hi> it; and the <hi>moderate</hi> Men being baffl'd in their Elections, and the more <hi>Inconſiderate</hi> ſacrificing their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to their <hi>Ambition;</hi> which upon <hi>Conſideration now,</hi> they call <hi>Revenge,</hi> ſettled their <hi>Liturgy:</hi> A <hi>Parliament</hi> was Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in 62. Confirm'd an Abſolute Act of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity;</hi> the KING's Promiſes, Declarations, Commiſſions, all <hi>Dy,</hi> or had no <hi>Life;</hi> and about 2000 of Conſcientious Miniſters moſt Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionably ſilenc'd for their Oppoſition. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter to Diſſent.</note> The Gentlemen Confeſs their Errour, and ſo we need not prove it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV. The <hi>wholeſome</hi> Effects that follow'd it's Sober Conſultations.</head>
               <p>IF any one ſhould Ask us now to the <hi>Fourth Point: What were the good Effects that follow from this Aſſemblies ſober De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, and Conſultations?</hi> Why! The Anſwer is eaſy and ſhort; <hi>Peace,</hi> a National and Univerſal <hi>Peace;</hi> a <hi>Peace</hi> in Church; a <hi>Peace</hi> in State, ſo Calm and Serene, even to the ſatisfying of a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and a Soul; as if the Spirit of <hi>GOD</hi> had moved again up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Face of the Waters, after a confus'd Deluge, and a Sea of Blood; as if the <hi>holy Dove</hi> it ſelf, had brought the <hi>Peaceful</hi> Branch to our Iſle, as from the Deluge to an Ark: The <hi>Good</hi> Effects of it cannot better be gueſt, than from the <hi>Bad</hi> Ones that <hi>followed</hi> it's being <hi>Diſſolv'd;</hi> and that they were no greater, can only be imputed to the ſuddenneſs of it's Diſſolution, which was only worthy to have been <hi>Endleſs,</hi> and what both it's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding and following one were; truly <hi>Perpetual,</hi> and <hi>Long.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to confirm with the moſt forcible Argument, from mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact, the good Effects that follow'd it; there was nothing of a <hi>Plot</hi> heard of, all the the Time of it's Sitting, and what could be the Reaſon of ſuch a General Calmneſs and Serenity:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95944:9"/>
certainly nothing elſe, but the <hi>Liberty</hi> every one enjoy'd to Worſhip his <hi>GOD</hi> in his own Way; and what was generally expected, ſhould have been ſettled by Law, and which had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly been done too, had they ſate longer; and 'tis ſhrewdly to be ſuſpected, that the Intereſt ſome People had, who affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed power, and fear'd to loſe the <hi>Liberty</hi> which they better lik't, to puniſh other Religions by the Laws of their <hi>Church;</hi> hinder'd <hi>Toleration</hi> from being made an Act of the <hi>State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what <hi>follow'd</hi> pray preſently upon it's <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> but the Inſurrection of <hi>Venner,</hi> and his Fifth Monarchy-men, fighting for JESVS CHRIST, for fear now of what follow'd; that their <hi>Reign</hi> was <hi>like</hi> to be but ſhort?</p>
               <p>When the Oaths of Supremacy began to be tender'd to all; and the <hi>Teſt</hi> of Abjuration (that ſome thought a Temptation to a ſeeming Perjury) was indiſcriminately put; a thing, that <hi>Pryn</hi> himſelf (that had writ <hi>For</hi> the KING's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>in)</hi> tho' <hi>againſt</hi> all things before, could oppoſe, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> when Encroachments in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticals began to creep on; were there not then too, Deſigns and Conſpiracies ſet afoot; and <hi>Barebone, Salmon, Wildman, Ireton,</hi> and Others ſeiz'd, and Committed to ſafe Cuſtody?</p>
               <p>When that <hi>dreadful</hi> St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> (as they call'd it) began to dawn upon the <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> by which day they were oblig'd to read Divine Service, according to the Act of Uniformity, wear the Veſtments of the <hi>Church,</hi> or forſake their <hi>Pulpits,</hi> after <hi>all</hi> their Endeavours to prevail with a <hi>Parliament</hi> were in vain, and their Application to KING and Council as Fruitleſs; when the Biſhops were ready, and had provided men for to fill the places of <hi>ſuch</hi> as would not take the <hi>Teſt;</hi> and near two Thouſand were turn'd out upon it: the Conformiſts <hi>reſerving too much the bitter Taſt of their rough <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage,</hi> notwithſtanding the General <hi>Amneſty</hi> ſo much preſt by the KING; &amp; one would think might have been moſt <hi>Religiouſly</hi> obſerv'd by <hi>Prelates;</hi> Did not <hi>then</hi> firſt, Fears and Jealouſies begin to Invade the State, and even make the Government it ſelf afraid? So Conſcious is Oppreſſion of Conſequences that are Fatal; that <hi>power</hi> it ſelf can diſtruſt it's own <hi>Weakneſs;</hi> and for this reaſon preſently upon it (being ſenſible of the provocations given in Matters of Religion) Walls were order'd to be pulled down; ſeveral Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95944:10"/>
and Towns to be diſmantl'd; at the ſame time that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities of the Laws were to be put in Execution: and what enſu'd? but the ſuſpected Plot of <hi>Danvers, Ludlow,</hi> &amp;c. for which <hi>Phillips, Toung, Gibbs</hi> and Others were Executed.</p>
               <p>Upon the Neck of that, broke out another in the <hi>North;</hi> and while they were Labouring by Rigor to ſuppreſs the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the <hi>Church,</hi> what did they Raiſe but open Rebellions in the <hi>State?</hi> Several of the Conſpirators were Taken; and a Commiſſion ſent to <hi>York</hi> to Try them; fifteen were found Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Chief of them, one Capt. <hi>Oates:</hi> ſome were Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted at <hi>York,</hi> ſome at <hi>Leeds,</hi> ſome in Adjacent Places; and ſo univerſal was the Diſcontent upon this encroachment of the <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> that the ſame Conſpiracy had ſpread it ſelf to <hi>London,</hi> and was firſt to have broke forth in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>Sickneſs</hi> time, when the KING left <hi>London</hi> and went to <hi>Oxford;</hi> which, though not <hi>Viſited,</hi> the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> ſay, they found there their <hi>Plague</hi> too, the <hi>Five-Mile Act,</hi> to prevent (as they call'd it) <hi>the ſpreading their Infection;</hi> whereby indeed they were Baniſh't Corporations and Towns, as if they were <hi>Tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> with the <hi>Malignancy</hi> that Reign'd, and onely fit for a <hi>Peſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe;</hi> and that too with another <hi>Teſt</hi> to the purpoſe; why? What enſu'd preſently upon it? Before the <hi>Peſtilence</hi> was hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ceas'd, and the KING <hi>well</hi> return'd to <hi>London,</hi> but another Diſcovery for the Alteration of the Government; of which Conſpiracy, one <hi>Alexander</hi> was the Chief; the City to be Fir'd on the <hi>Third</hi> of <hi>September;</hi> the ſame time, that it was indeed: <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Gazet.</hi>
                  </note> and for which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> were ſo unreaſonably Reproach't; for which ſeveral were Try'd at the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> and Executed at <hi>Tyburn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt Commotion that began in <hi>Scotland,</hi> was alſo upon the ſame Account; when the Ryot that was made upon one of their Juſtices; as was Confeſt by both ſides, was only for too rigorouſly Executing the Laws againſt them in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; which Ryot, tho' rais'd by a ſmall Number of Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Sufferers, yet ſoon ran up ſo high as an Army, and which was Marching with all haſt to <hi>Edenburgh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the laſt Rebellion at <hi>Bothwell-Bridge,</hi> tho' begun by ſome deſperate Villains, to defend themſelves from the Juſtice they had deſervd, for the Murdering of the Archbiſhop, had
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95944:10"/>
never come to that height; had not the Covenanters thinking themſelves Oppreſt by the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> clos'd in with them, and increas'd their Army to ſuch a Number, as to make them formidable.</p>
               <p>And Laſtly, I much doubt, whether ever <hi>Monmouth</hi> himſelf would have made ſo much work in the Weſt, had not the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities of the Laws then Zealouſly ſet afoot, ſent him many a Souldier into the <hi>field,</hi> that did not dare to ſtay <hi>a home,</hi> for fear of fine and confiſcation; and had his Majeſty, aſſoon as he Aſcended his Throne, been Permitted by the Reaſons of State, or not oppos'd by the importunities of ſome peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to have declar'd his Reſolutions of Indulgence, perhaps it might have ſav'd a great deal of Proteſtant Blood; and Diſſenters never have fought for that <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> which it ſeems to them too, was <hi>Dearer then their Lives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God forbid!</hi> That ever Rebellion ſhould be really Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd by Religious <hi>Pretences;</hi> but ſince, Matter of Fact makes it Plain, that they are ſo of <hi>Pretended,</hi> as is manifeſt here from the Diſturbance that was given to the State, conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon every Uſurpation and Penalty, Tryal and <hi>Teſt</hi> that was put upon Peoples Souls (as is apparent from the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Particulars); can any man in his wits not cloſe with a Provident PRINCE, to remove the very <hi>Pretences</hi> too of it? To quarrel at ſuch a Prudential Act, is to tell His Majeſty, they are never <hi>Eaſy,</hi> but when <hi>Hee's Embroyl'd;</hi> never <hi>Secure,</hi> but when there's an <hi>Inſurrection</hi> againſt their KING. Theſe ſort of Men are more dangerous in their Sentiments, than ſome <hi>Country Ideots</hi> in their Suppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſome of them wont believe <hi>Monmouth</hi> to be <hi>Dead;</hi> and theſe by their own Maxims muſt wiſh him <hi>Alive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis as Certain as <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelf, if Fact can make a thing appear <hi>True;</hi> that Sufferers for Religion (and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps we may except no Perſwaſions) will endeavour to lay hold on any Alteration of State, to <hi>Reſcue</hi> themſelves from the ſeverity of ſuch Oppreſſions; 'tis as natural as to ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men to catch at a Plank: And I could prove <hi>this</hi> from Hiſtory, for above this <hi>Hundred</hi> and <hi>Fifty</hi> Years, from our <hi>Hen. th' Eighth,</hi> to thoſe inſtances I make uſe of in the laſt Reign. To <hi>this</hi> Provocation do the <hi>Hollanders</hi> owe their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95944:11"/>
Revolt, their Being, and their Common-wealth. To <hi>this,</hi> do the <hi>Hugonots</hi> of <hi>France</hi> Aſcribe their Entry into the <hi>League:</hi> and what that Coſt <hi>that</hi> Kingdom, let <hi>Ours</hi> Judge. To <hi>this,</hi> do diſcontented Courtiers, and deſperate Villains, owe all that which to a Government makes them Formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: for ſuch Creatures as could never Hope upon their own Intereſt, to Muſter an hundred Men (where a <hi>general In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi> is Eſtabliſh't) ſhall under a Preſſure of Conſcience, raiſe you a Million; and with this Advantage too, that the Cauſe (whatever are the Fellows that engage in it) will ſtill carry the better Face; and Quallify Villains of no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to Head thoſe that really Fight for it: and to tell you that they are <hi>The Armies of the Living GOD, the GOD of</hi> HOSTS; and <hi>that they Fight the Battles of the</hi> LORD. So certain it is, that thoſe who are not permitted to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble in their own <hi>Church,</hi> will alwayes be Reſtleſs and Uneaſy in the <hi>State: Paſſive Obedience</hi> in ſuch Caſes, we ſee ſooner Preach't than Practis'd; and ſuch as are deny'd in their own Way to Worſhip their <hi>GOD,</hi> will aſſoon be deficient in their <hi>Duty</hi> to their <hi>KING;</hi> and may the <hi>Fear of it,</hi> never make ſome ſort <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nautiful;</hi> that Profeſs, they'l never be Provok't, tho' by <hi>Suffering for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So much was it the ſenſe of His Late <hi>Majeſty,</hi> as partly appears before; that in purſuance of his Promiſes at <hi>Breda;</hi> and his Intimations to his Firſt <hi>Parliament,</hi> that was ſo <hi>Healing:</hi> To which he <hi>preſt</hi> a <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> that he alſo in his Declaration of <hi>December, Sixty Two,</hi> makes a Confirmation of it; and ſays, That he was <hi>Firm in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of Performing it to the Full:</hi> And this even againſt the Senſe of his New <hi>Parliament,</hi> that was more for Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty and Perſecution. Of this, he Expreſt his Senſe in his <hi>Parliament, July</hi> 16th. <hi>Sixty Nine:</hi> And then, in ſpite of them, <hi>March,</hi> 25th. <hi>Seventy Two,</hi> made good his Promiſes to <hi>All,</hi> by a <hi>General</hi> Indulgence, and a Protection of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:95944:11"/>
               <head>SECT. V. The <hi>Wayes</hi> that are Taken <hi>Now,</hi> to Hinder the Having ſuch <hi>Another.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving Diſcours't of the <hi>Paſt,</hi> we come home now to our Selves, and the <hi>Preſent</hi> Time, and to Conſider the <hi>Fifth Point; The Wayes that are Taken now, to Hinder the having ſuch Another Healing Parliament:</hi> And truly, they are not much Honeſter Attempts, than were us'd to prevent the Meeting of the <hi>Firſt;</hi> and that is the Old Antiquated pretence of <hi>Jealouſies</hi> and <hi>Fears;</hi> only there is another <hi>Knave</hi> turn'd Trumps now: (tho' 'tis the ſame thing to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, whether 'tis trick't upon, by that of <hi>Clubs,</hi> or <hi>Diamonds:)</hi> 'Tis ſtrange! That <hi>thoſe</hi> that made ſo lately the <hi>Folly</hi> of other Mens <hi>Fears</hi> ſo Ridiculous, ſhould make themſelves <hi>now,</hi> to thoſe <hi>very</hi> Men the moſt <hi>fearful Fools.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>thoſe,</hi> who ſtill aſſerted the Aſſurance and Security of their Religion, from the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of their KING; ſhould now, without the leaſt Breach of it, give him the Ly; and tell him to his Face, <hi>You are worſe than your</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Letter.</note> 
                  <hi>Word.</hi> That <hi>thoſe,</hi> who ran up the Prerogative, to the Height of it's <hi>Power;</hi> ſhould diſpute now, the <hi>Power</hi> of their KING's <hi>Diſpenſing.</hi> What is this, but a Confeſſing to their Foes, (whom they ſtill followed with Fine and Confiſcation) that their Divines were Dunces, their Books were Libels, and the Fam'd <hi>Filmer,</hi> the greateſt Fool? It is a ſaying ſo common, and ſo natural, that the moſt ignorant, both know it, and make uſe of it too; <hi>To Look before they Leap:</hi> and would any Conſiderate Men, make uſe of the ſame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and take the ſame Meaſures, for which they have ſo much Expoſed and Reproached others? But, it fares with them here in their <hi>Civil</hi> Matters, as the Late KING's Papers almoſt unanſwerably obſerve of their Concerns in <hi>Eccleſiaſticals; That</hi> part of the Nation, which looks moſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95944:12"/>
like a Church, cannot bring Her Arguments againſt the other Sects, for fear they ſhould be <hi>turn'd</hi> againſt Her ſelf. But only <hi>here</hi> they make the Inverſion much worſe: <hi>Here</hi> She takes the Old Arguments of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> on Her <hi>Side,</hi> only to make <hi>Her Own fly</hi> in Her <hi>Face;</hi> ſo that an Honeſt and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byaſt Aſſerter of the Government, has nothing elſe to do, to Anſwer the Clamors of the <hi>Preſent</hi> time, but to Declaim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Cavils of the <hi>Paſt;</hi> and <hi>both</hi> thoſe are Reducible to theſe Three Celebrated and Conteſted Points.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>I. <hi>Arbitrary Power.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Freedome</hi> of <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>For the Firſt, and for them all in their Order; though the preſent KING's Promiſes, are as <hi>Currant</hi> with them, as his Fathers <hi>Coin;</hi> and <hi>both</hi> bear the <hi>ſame</hi> Image and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription. Though the <hi>Leges Angl': libertas Parliament: Religio Proteſtant:</hi> have been the continual Subject of all this KING's gracious Declarations; and particularly, in that of His <hi>Indulgence:</hi> when (to put it in his <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. this <hi>King</hi>'s Two Proclamations to <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp; his Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence here.</note> Own Words) <hi>Property, Liberty,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> are <hi>all</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd to them, on the <hi>Word</hi> of a <hi>KING:</hi> Yet <hi>ſtill,</hi> the Matter by ſome or other muſt be <hi>still</hi> ſo manag'd, as to make the <hi>People</hi> to diſtruſt, and doubt of <hi>all:</hi> Such is the hard Fate of PRINCES (as if a Crown could not be contriv'd to ſit ſoft on a Royal Head; as if deſtin'd to be a Burthen by Decree;) both Extreams ſhall conſpire to make it uneaſy: Monarchs for the moſt part are Endanger'd, for their not <hi>believing</hi> any <hi>Danger</hi> to be <hi>near.</hi> 'Tis hard they ſhould ſuffer, by not <hi>being Believ'd</hi> too, when they tell their Subject there is <hi>None.</hi> Mark but the <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of your PRINCE, and then ſee, whether he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be treated ſo <hi>Ill.</hi> A numerous part of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being uneaſy (as certainly thoſe muſt be, that ſuffer for Conſcience ſake, and when the <hi>Iron Enter their very</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95944:12"/>
                  <hi>Souls)</hi> had made the Government a long time ſo too. To ſilence their Clamours and Complaints, the King would take away the occaſion of their Calamities, the ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Laws; and that raiſes now as mighty <hi>murmurings</hi> among <hi>thoſe,</hi> that were only for ſurpreſſing of <hi>Malecontents</hi> before; as if his <hi>Throne</hi> were more <hi>dreadful,</hi> when he makes it even the <hi>Mercy-ſeat.</hi> How ſhall the moſt gracious Prince pleaſe ſuch a divided People? where diſcontent only ſhifts Parties, and <hi>Loyalty</hi> ſeems no longer entail'd, (love at leaſt and affection) then as the King continues his favour, or it ſeems only now ſo long as he confines it to themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, ſure gratitude and friendſhip muſt not be limited like Marriage Vows, or thoſe of Devotion, to <hi>one</hi> Object: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a <hi>King</hi> to be conſiderd in his politick capacity like a natural body, <hi>Whoſe</hi> Love is <hi>then</hi> the moſt Generous, when 'tis moſt extenſive; and his power beſt <hi>abſolute,</hi> when he Reigns in the Hearts of <hi>all;</hi> to make himſelf this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarch</hi> ſeems <hi>only</hi> the deſign of his preſent Majeſty, and to make him more <hi>Fear'd</hi> than <hi>Lov'd</hi> are the devices of ſome Ureaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men.</p>
               <p>But the reſult of theſe Inconſiſtencies with themſelves, they will ſay does ariſe, and is occaſion'd by ſome deeper inſight of theirs into the deſigns of State, and our plauſible Varniſh may ſerve to ſet it off, but will never hinder them from ſeeing through it; 'tis ſtrang! that theſe politick Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles ſhould be ſo ſuddenly put on; this muſt make the Diſſenters value <hi>their</hi> opticks; proud of a better foreſight, and more acurate intuition; and tell the Church-men, we told you of this, and then where were your eyes? but could the Diſſenters have foreſeen too his Majeſties merciful Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> might never have been their <hi>Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Motto,</hi> or themſelves ſeduc'd to follow ſome more deſperate Malecontents to their death and deſtruction: was it Sedition in them to doubt? was it Treaſon almoſt to think? and is it a Loyal Act now, to declare in writing the danger of the Proteſtant Religion? and <hi>that</hi> at a time, when the free Exerciſe of it is permitted to <hi>All;</hi> certainly ſuch unwonted Surmiſes from Perſons that have declar'd their abhorrence of them as Seditious, are as <hi>ſurpriſing,</hi> as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95944:13"/>
the <hi>new Friendſhip's,</hi> and ſhew that the Tide is turn'd, the Wind tackt about againſt their Intereſts; and what can Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters <hi>ſay,</hi> but that they ſee through all this, and as they told the Diſſenters that the <hi>Liberty</hi> they labour'd for, was only a <hi>Licenſe</hi> to do what they <hi>Liſt;</hi> ſo their Popery that is now coming in, is nothing elſe but their Perſecuting Power that's going out.</p>
               <p>What will they <hi>not ſay?</hi> when they ſee thoſe that exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſeiſing of Franchiſes, as an undoubted Prerogative, Printed and Publiſht the forfeiture of all Charters, Prive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and Immunities; and that <hi>before</hi> they were granted with ſuch Reſtrictions and Reſervations as more impower his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, than when theſe People made them all thus depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant on the Crown: <hi>'Tis ſtrange!</hi> that even <hi>thoſe</hi> ſhould mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur at his Majeſties power of <hi>Diſpenſing,</hi> which the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Prerogative, and the Laws of the Land did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Allow; I do not deſign to enter here upon the old di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of <hi>Malum in ſe, &amp;. Prohibitum, For</hi> that <hi>Evil</hi> which was <hi>prohibited,</hi> when by reaſons of State it comes to be <hi>diſpens'd</hi> withall, is no longer ſo, but really <hi>good;</hi> ſo it would be oppreſſion in a Prince, to demoliſh the dwellings of his Subjects, but no one will ſay 'tis ſo in a Siege; when he burns down the Subburbs.</p>
               <p>But this being not only to be defended by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but the <hi>Laws;</hi> was repin'd at as * <hi>Arbitrary;</hi> the King upbraided with <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter: and Anſwer to the <hi>Teſt</hi> of Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty. <hi>Vid.</hi> All <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> Papers.</note> his Coronation Oath to keep all the Laws, the Judges Libell'd and Satyris'd for their ſenſe and opinions, and with a <hi>Non Obſtante</hi> poſted up in an houſe of Office: The rumour ran of nothing elſe, but <hi>all</hi> the Laws to be lay'd aſide, though on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſome</hi> Penal ones were ſuſpended; and when they might as well have made their Satyr and Animadverſion upon every Seſſion at the Old Baily, where the King was never deny'd the pardoning of a Felon, or remitting a Fine; tho' the one were for the higheſt miſdemeanour, and the other even for murder it ſelf: and ſure, to infer from an argument <hi>a fortio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> if the Law will juſtifie the Kings Mercy to a Malefactor for the ſhedding of blood, it will ſure extend to forgive the forfeiture of an Office or Place; and yet too, by the leave of the mighty Dr. and his moſt malitious <note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Burnet's</hi> Reflections on Declaration for <hi>Liberty,</hi> &amp;c.</note> conſtruction, this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95944:13"/>
ſhall not amount to the <hi>repeal</hi> of the Law, and be but a bare ſuſpenſion of the <hi>Penalty.</hi> For as it appear'd in the late Caſe of <hi>Hales,</hi> it was in the power of any man to <hi>Proſecute,</hi> tho it was at laſt left in the King to <hi>Pardon:</hi> And if the Dr. will make haſt before the Parliament may make ſome Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he ſhall bring what information he pleaſes againſt any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt for their forfeitures; where he may ſhew his malice, and do no miſchief: So that all his <hi>Scotch</hi> Droll, about <hi>Caſs</hi> and <hi>Null,</hi> and <hi>Abſolute Power</hi> apply'd to the Caſes in <hi>England,</hi> are nothing to the purpoſe. But it was not Dr. <hi>B.</hi> alone that was thus bold, we heard nothing about that time in <hi>private</hi> diſcourſe, but threatning of <hi>Publick</hi> impeachments; &amp; that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments had queſtioned <hi>Wolſey, Briſtol,</hi> and others, for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing ſuch diſpenſations; and that Judges had been with the old ſtory of <hi>Treſilian,</hi> hang'd for ſuch reſolutions. Gentlemen, it could not be the Diſſenters <hi>now</hi> that were guilty of theſe ſort of Obſervations, unleſs they were angry at the Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Mercy that reliev'd them.</p>
               <p>But that we have no reaſon to make this a piece of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Power,</hi> conſider but ſome Preſidents of Prerogative, and that in the former Reigns: King <hi>Edw. 3d.</hi> repeal'd an Act of Parliament (as impos'd by neceſſity) and <hi>that</hi> by his Royal Prerogative; the Parliament in <hi>Rich. 2d.</hi> time by ſeveral Judicial Acts, had proceeded againſt the Ld. Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, the Duke of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Arch Biſhop of <hi>York,</hi> to which the King had given his aſſent; but aſſoon as he <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd</hi> that <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> all was <hi>diſſolv'd</hi> too, that had been done againſt them.</p>
               <p>And that the Reſolution of our Judges may not be lookt on as ſo Extrajudicial and Extravagant, I'le refer them to what was reſolv'd by the Judges in the ſame Kings Reign.</p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>That the Statute of Commiſſion made in the laſt Parliament, was Void, becauſe againſt the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, and that the Adviſers to it deſerved Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>That the King could cauſe the Parliament to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed upon Articles by him limited, before they med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled with any other.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:95944:14"/>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>That the Judgment againſt</hi> Pool <hi>in Parliament was Revocable by the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that it is no new thing for the Judges in the higheſt manner to aſſert the Prerogative, and what ever <hi>Miracles</hi> were performed afterward by that Parliament of <hi>wonders,</hi> that does not make it leſs the duty of thoſe ſages to aſſert the right of the Crown; tho' ſome of them were afterward by the rebellious Barons, and the deſigning Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> brought to ſuffer for the ſervice to their <hi>King,</hi> and by the ſame <hi>People</hi> too, that afterward depos'd their Prince. I need no more then mention the Diſpenſation to the <hi>Juſtices</hi> againſt 37. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. and that common Caſe of the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifs, diſpenſed with by the <hi>2d.</hi> of <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. or the Caſe of Coinage in his 11. when <hi>Hen.</hi> 8 rejected the Popes Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micy in Eccleſiaſticals; 'tis as well known he reſerv'd it as <hi>Entirely</hi> to himſelf, ſettl'd upon him ſo by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: ſo that if the Pope ever had a <hi>Diſpenſing</hi> power with a <hi>non Obſtante; both Hen.</hi> 8 and <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. had it too, and I think <hi>both</hi> of them made uſe of it <hi>with a witneſs:</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Heylin's</hi> Hiſt. Reform. as alſo Acts &amp; Monuments, &amp; you'l ſee what <hi>Waſte,</hi> what <hi>Work</hi> was made with <hi>Altars</hi> &amp; <hi>Images;</hi> tho' ſuch irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Violence was by the Council of <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberis</hi> forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to be ſhewn, even the Pagan Idols.</note> the Sanctuary it ſelf was not ſafe againſt their <hi>Diſpenſations,</hi> that were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended even to Sacriledge too, and the <hi>Altar</hi> it ſelf was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd up for a <hi>Burnt-Offering</hi> to ſome Orders of the <hi>Council-Board.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The management of Religious matters will ever depend on the Civil Magiſtrate; and is a ſaying never the leſs cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, or more falſe, for being the ſenſe too of Mr. <hi>Hobbs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The power that <hi>theſe</hi> aſſum'd in Eccleſiaſticals, as ſome think too <hi>much</hi> (as it was deriv'd to all their ſucceſſors ſince) ſo none of them have exercis'd it ſo <hi>little</hi> as to loſe it by <hi>diſuſe:</hi> but in all their <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> to <hi>Forreigners,</hi> that came to ſettle, to their Families when encreas'd, and to ſeveral of their native ſubjects at <hi>home,</hi> ſufficiently manifeſted, that this Power was in the Crown, that it was often made uſe of; and that it is very unlikely any Prince will be willing to part with it. Who ever run the Royal Authority in <hi>Sacreds</hi> higher than the Church that diſputes it now ſo much; So that the Kings power is with them what they pleaſe, when
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95944:14"/>
it only countenances <hi>their</hi> Eſtabliſhment, and juſt none at all, when it will Favour <hi>any Other.</hi> I muſt confeſs I cou'd never find but that <hi>Argument</hi> &amp; <hi>Law,</hi> was ever Relatively <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Ill,</hi> according to the diſpoſition of the Party that was to <hi>Gain</hi> or <hi>Loſe</hi> by it, and every man will ever be a Knave or a Fool, to thoſe that are not of his Opinion: but yet certainly, there muſt be ſomewhat of Intrinſick Equity, and Eternal Reaſon; however confounded, according to the diverſity of Partyes, and partiality of the People; and by ſuch an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudic'd</hi> Judgment, I dare venture to try, not only the Power of <hi>Diſpenſing,</hi> but of the very <hi>Repealing</hi> of the <hi>Laws.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would ask theſe men, whether Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did not take as great a Liberty in <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Heylin's</hi> Reformation, &amp; even <hi>Burnets</hi> too.</note> Eccleſiſticals for the found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>their</hi> Church; <hi>greater</hi> than they can allow his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, only for the Countenancing of <hi>his,</hi> when Her Injunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the <hi>Church,</hi> paſt as <hi>currant</hi> with them for an Act of <hi>State;</hi> as if't had only been her <hi>Coinage:</hi> and <hi>Shee</hi> at the ſame time, could <hi>diſpenſe</hi> to read the <hi>Latine Service,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">It was ſaid by <hi>Moor</hi> in her Reign, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify'd in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; that the Queens <hi>Non Obſtante</hi> was good even againſt <hi>the Non Obſtanle,</hi> of an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to her Power &amp; Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative.</note> againſt what Her Self, and <hi>Parliament</hi> had <hi>Enacted?</hi> And if the Proceedings of PRINCES, muſt be ſo much expos'd to the Cenſure of the <hi>People:</hi> we meet with in her Reign, perhaps the higheſt Inſtance of unheard of Power, that Hiſtory affords; or, ever was aſſum'd by any Monarch that Sate on our Throne. And that was her Proceeding againſt the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> the next Heir to her Crown (tho' ſome would give Her a better Title) whom, againſt the Laws of Nature and Nations, the word of a Queen, the promiſe of a Siſter, the faith of a Chriſtian, after ſhe had fled to her for Refuge; after ſhe had flatter'd her to reſtore her; after Eighteen Years Impriſonment, made her hold up her Hand to a <hi>Bar,</hi> and be Beheaded on a <hi>Block.</hi> It may be the firſt Example of ſuch a ſort of Suffering, that ever was offer'd to a Crown'd Head, whatever are the thoughts of our ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated <note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> &amp; the Author of the Tryal, &amp; Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the New Teſt of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England's</hi> Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty.</note> Wits, to the contrary in the Caſes they put. For <hi>Licinius</hi> you muſt firſt obſerve, was by their own Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but a <hi>Colleague</hi> with <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> and we may tell ſuch Men of <hi>Law,</hi> that underſtand <hi>Loyalty</hi> to be nothing <hi>elſe;</hi> that till they prove the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> a <hi>Coparcenary</hi> with <hi>Q Elizabeth,</hi> they are impertinent in their Proof: but as Bad Luck would have it, when Wiſe Men make Ill Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95944:15"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Sleid.</hi> de quatuor ſumm. Imper. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Eutro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius,</hi> lib. 10. <hi>Socrates,</hi> lib. 1. cap. 2. &amp; lib. 2. cap. 1.</note> This <hi>Licinius,</hi> was Colleague with <hi>Maximianus,</hi> conquer'd by <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and kill'd in a tumultuous Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by the Souldiers. He might ſo well have told us of <hi>Will, Conqueror</hi> kill'd <hi>Harold</hi> the <hi>Dane:</hi> And that Authors <hi>other</hi> Preſident, that he Cites, for a Judicial Proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Crown'd <hi>Head,</hi> fails him too, as much: tho' he might have told us, which Queen <hi>Joan</hi> [there being two that Reign'd,] and both <hi>Bad</hi> enough: for that of Q. <hi>Joan</hi>'s of <hi>Naples</hi> Caſe, was ſhortly this: <hi>She</hi> had Hang'd her <hi>firſt</hi> Husband for <hi>Inſufficiency;</hi> Kill'd the <hi>ſecond,</hi> in trying too much his <hi>Ability;</hi> Beheaded the <hi>third</hi> for <hi>Incontinency. Shee</hi> was Vanquiſh't by the K. of <hi>Hungary,</hi> Brother to her Firſt Husband, and Hang'd in Revenge of his Death. Here's the Act again of an enrag'd Enemy, made the ſame with a friend and <hi>Ally,</hi> and the Caſe of the Lewdeſt Creature, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <note place="margin">Vid. his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the New Teſt.</note> to the moſt Pious <hi>Lady.</hi> Dr. <hi>B.</hi> himſelf cannot excuſe the Barbarous Proceedings that were us'd againſt her: and tho'I do not blame <hi>all</hi> the Biſhops of <hi>thoſe</hi> Times, and <hi>This,</hi> as ſome <hi>ſevere</hi> Papers have done: yet to be Juſt to both; <hi>moſt,</hi> both of the <hi>Clergy</hi> and the <hi>Laity</hi> that liv'd then, were for ſacrificing of her, to what they call'd <hi>Preſervation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion:</hi> and few of thoſe that have followed ſince, have juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed the Proceedings. Whatever were the Cauſe, the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects I'm ſure were Fatal; and I fancy, follow'd by ſome of our own Nation ſince; and that to the ſpilling of more of the <hi>ſame</hi> Blood; and verifying the Prophetick fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, as well as the ſeaſonable Sarcaſm of that unfortunate Princeſs; that the Engliſh were ever wont to Murder their <hi>own KINGS:</hi> and no wonder then, they would Sacrifice now the Crown'd Head of <hi>another Kingdome.</hi> Thus, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, ſuffer'd that <hi>Pious Princeſs</hi> (and if any) a <hi>Bleſſed Saint;</hi> and that upon the Pretence too, of a ſort of <hi>Penal Law:</hi> a <hi>Teſt</hi> on purpoſe to deſtroy her, and that upon the account of <hi>Religion. Buckhurſt</hi> and <hi>Beal</hi> both that brought her the diſmal Tydings of her <hi>Death;</hi> intimated to her, that her <hi>Life</hi> would be the ruine of the <hi>Religion</hi> received: and indeed 'twas as agreeable to the pretended Intereſt of the State that Condemn'd her: for ſhe had no other <hi>Crime</hi> but their <hi>Fears:</hi> and if her Endeavours to eſcape from the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95944:15"/>
Confinement of a Faithleſs Ally were high Treaſon, She was then only in a <hi>Plott.</hi> So fell that Unfortunate Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, whoſe Misfortunes would have melted Marble; and that by the height of the moſt <hi>Arbitrary Power:</hi> in a Reign, where we dream of nothing elſe, but <hi>Liberty, Property;</hi> and no other <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> but of impartial Juſtice: And can any one think, that his Majeſty himſelf, the direct Iſſue of the <hi>ſame</hi> Princeſs, whoſe Religion is the <hi>ſame;</hi> is not <hi>Wounded</hi> too with the ſanguinary proceedings of her Times, and the ſeverity of thoſe Laws ſtill in force; by which (whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is pretended) many meerly for Religion ſuffer'd; and thoſe <hi>Catholicks</hi> that were Executed, for what was adjudg'd High-Treaſon, found as little <hi>Mercy,</hi> as the other <hi>Juſtice:</hi> being Cut down alive, and Embowelled before their Face; till the Queen was forc't to Forbid ſuch cruel Executions.</p>
               <p>That the Power of the Prerogative has been Arraign'd with ſuch Animadverſions, as are above Suggeſted; and that the KING's <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> have been remark't upon, as Illegal; and without Preſident: and <hi>that</hi> by <hi>thoſe</hi> very men, that made it their Buſineſs to advance any abſolute Proceeding. He muſt have kept himſelf very cloſe, or doubt his Hearing that disbelieves it: but more than that, they have given it under their Hand, and the moſt modeſt of their Papers, an <hi>Anſwerer to the Judgment and Doctrin of the Clergy,</hi> about the power of <hi>Diſpenſing;</hi> does handſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clear them from the Belief of the Right of the KING's Prerogative in this point; and is loath they ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for ſuch Betrayers of the Liberty of the People. Their Crime had not been ſo great, had their Opinions lain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Obloquy of ſuch an Imputation; and the Anſwerer as little obliges his Church, as the Pamphleteer: but as modeſt as he is, 'tis manifeſt from it; that the Judgement of their Church is <hi>now</hi> againſt it, or elſe, ſure it muſt be a needleſs labour, if not impertinent, to take ſo much pains to vindicate its Members from it: But this I muſt obſerve from my acquaintance with <hi>all</hi> thoſe Authors Quoted; that tho' they have not in expreſs Terms extended the KING's power to <hi>Diſpenſe</hi> with <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> they have advanc't his Soveraignty to as high a pitch: and when the ſhooe pinches,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95944:16"/>
we are apt to complain, tho' it be of our own putting on: And thoſe that find, from the Revolutions of Affairs, any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected Inconveniencies to flow from their own Arguments, have nothing elſe to do, but deny the Conſequence, and pleaſe themſelves with a <hi>Non Sequitur:</hi> but I'le aſſure you, as modeſt as this man is in Queſtioning it, there are as bold Aſſerters in Print, that affirm with Confidence, with dint of <hi>Satyr,</hi> that theſe Royal Diſpenſations, are ſo many Breaches of Oaths, <hi>Irregular</hi> and Extrajudicial Proceedings. The late Letter to a <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> that has rais'd ſuch a Duſt, very ſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Laughs it out of doors; as if it might be Extended to <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with their Belief of the Church of <hi>Rome's</hi> Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. A very pretty <hi>Jeſt,</hi> to ſpoil a Latiniſm, and <hi>Play</hi> with his Soveraign, that is <hi>Sacred,</hi> as well as the <hi>Religion:</hi> but he is in <hi>earneſt</hi> too, and tells them their acceptance of it, has <hi>Retain'd</hi> them as Counſel for the Prerogative againſt <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> and that <hi>Parliaments</hi> may <hi>Pay</hi> them for it. The <hi>Tryal</hi> of the <hi>New Teſt,</hi> with Dr. <hi>B</hi>'s <hi>Tune; another to the ſame;</hi> are ſuch ſevere <hi>Satyrs</hi> on the ſame Subject; ſuch as the Government never ſuffer'd, I am ſure in the moſt ſeditious Times: ſo that I do theſe Gentlemen no Wrong, if we may believe our Ears and our Eyes (and Senſe with ſuch, cannot be deny'd an infallible Judge) when we lay at ſome of their doors, the deſigns of animating the People with the <hi>Old Din</hi> of <hi>Arbitrary Power;</hi> as the <hi>Indians</hi> do their Elephants, with a red Cloath, and bloody Colours.</p>
               <p>The other old Out-cry that is ſet afoot, is the popular Clamour about <hi>Parliament;</hi> and muſt that too be taken <hi>up,</hi> by thoſe that made ſuch a Noiſe to Cry it <hi>down?</hi> But here, theſe Gentlemen are more Pettiſh and Peeviſh; and harder to be <hi>pleas'd,</hi> than ever were the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> they for their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable ſpirit Condemn'd: They would have a <hi>Parliament,</hi> &amp; they would have none: ſo 'tis impoſſible to gratify thoſe that <hi>contradict</hi> themſelves: but wee'l ſuppoſe them, only ſome claſhing <hi>contrarieties;</hi> and ſo may be ſeemingly Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd. They would have a <hi>Redreſſing Parliament,</hi> and not a <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Addreſſers:</hi> and truly for that they now la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with all Artifice and Zeal, as if they intended to make every County an <hi>Aſſociated</hi> One; but ſure this way of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95944:16"/>
                  <hi>working</hi> may put the Nation in a <hi>ferment;</hi> and we can ſay with ſad Experience, it never yet procur'd the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>Peace.</hi> Wiſe men will conſider, tho' they are ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd of the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of their Cauſe, never to uſe <hi>bad</hi> means to bring it about.</p>
               <p>And I wiſh we were all ſo wiſe, and would do ſo too; but ſuch is the Seditious induſtry of ſome, to <hi>Create</hi> thoſe dangers <hi>truly</hi> out of <hi>nothing,</hi> when there are none to Invade them that are really near: And for this the Country ſhall be frighten'd with a Parliament of Courtiers, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in General, that it may be made up of Roman-Catholicks, both thoſe the moſt Panick Fears, and next to impoſſibilities; the Court never yet afforded us Members enough to make up a full Committee; and there are not Catholicks enough of great Eſtates in <hi>England,</hi> to ſerve <hi>two</hi> in a County: if Improbabilities won't be ſwallow'd, danger it ſelf, like a black Pill muſt be <hi>Gilded, to go down</hi> the better, and <hi>work</hi> with the People; and they muſt be told of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties interpoſition, that a Burgeſs muſt be made like a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, with a <hi>Congee d'eſlire;</hi> that he is reſolv'd to have a <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter, and the Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of the <hi>Teſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>Burnets</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</note> Parliament for his purpoſe; (and ſure, in deſires that are <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable,</hi> why ſhould he not?) and ſuch an one certainly is the deſign of ſettling a quiet both of Body and Soul, to all his Subjects. We are told from all the late Libells, that like Plague-Bills, or thoſe of the Pox, are put into your hands: that <hi>Returns</hi> muſt ſerve inſtead of an <hi>Election,</hi> that the one will never be permitted to be <hi>Fair,</hi> and the other muſt ſure be <hi>Foul.</hi> But theſe fooliſh inſinuations any one may ſee are on purpoſe to create Faction and Fears; and tho' his Majeſties deſire are as Earneſt as they are Reaſonable, for relieving the diſtreſſes of his Subjects; and the giving eaſe, and equal priviledg to all, yet he aims at no other end than the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it about by <hi>Law:</hi> Intereſt ſure will never ly, and 'tis <hi>that</hi> obliges thoſe that would have <hi>Laws</hi> Repeal'd, that the Authority be <hi>Lawful</hi> that Repeals them; and it would only afford another Parliament an Argument, to Void and Diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nul what ever was <hi>Done,</hi> were the Conſtitution of the <hi>Body</hi> not qualify'd to <hi>do it.</hi> But perhaps they may find that by <hi>Law</hi> too, &amp; that of their <hi>own</hi> making, his <hi>Majeſty</hi> may meet with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95944:17"/>
good <hi>Returns</hi> from moſt Corporations, ſince they won't queſtion ſure the Power of <hi>Regulating,</hi> which themſelves have given &amp; by which many of them too, not long ſince were glad to be brought into the Houſe of Commons, eſpecially by better <hi>Law</hi> now, ſince in all thoſe new Charters, there are expreſs Proviſoes for his Majeſties changing any <hi>Part,</hi> or altering the <hi>Whole.</hi> But is this now ſuch a new thing, to have the mind of the <hi>Prince</hi> ſet upon compaſſing, by the intereſt he has with the <hi>People,</hi> any point of State, that he judges convenient for the Welfare of Himſelf and Subjects? Thoſe that think ſo, are but little acquainted with Books or Hiſtory, and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve <hi>Old</hi> things, have forgot tranſactions that are very <hi>New.</hi> I need not mind them, that there is hardly an account of any <hi>Reign</hi> that does not afford us an Inſtance. But tell them, that they gave us one themſelves, and that in the very <hi>laſt:</hi> With what Vigor the Succeſſion was Invaded, they can <hi>Boaſt,</hi> to their own <hi>Honour</hi> it ſeems, and others <hi>Shame:</hi> and had not his Late Majeſty Interpos'd with his utmoſt Power, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Forfeiture of Franchiſes, and Regulating Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; they can <hi>Glory</hi> to ſome peoples <hi>Reproach,</hi> that the <hi>Tide</hi> had never been <hi>Turn'd;</hi> and will theſe men Tugg now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame Stream they ſail'd down in ſo merrily? If their meaſures were ſo <hi>Fair</hi> then, how come the ſame Practiſes ſo <hi>Foul</hi> now? eſpecially when by preſident and reſtrictions, made more Warrantable too: for as they did <hi>Well</hi> to <hi>Defend</hi> the Right of <hi>Succeſſion;</hi> ſo the ſame <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> with as many of their fellow Subjects, think that <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> can be as <hi>well Defended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I can tell them of greater Liberties, that have been taken by the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> tho' nothing like it has been here attempted now; and that is, if I miſtake not, in this very Point of <hi>interpoſition</hi> to Returns and Elections.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard.</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> called all the <hi>Juſtices</hi> and <hi>Sherifs</hi> to <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> ſays our Hiſtory, intimating that he was to call a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and that they ſhould uſe the matter ſo, that no Knight or Burgeſs ſhould be choſen, but ſuch as the King and Council ſhould name; 'tis true, their anſwer was peremptory, they could not do it: but he that reads the Hiſtory, will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoon the Reaſon. The Lords were in Arms, and a Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95944:17"/>
in the Realm; and tho' this were not Juſtifyable by <hi>Law,</hi> it may ſerve to ſhew what great attempts have long ſince been made upon <hi>Liberty;</hi> when it was reſolv'd <hi>too</hi> in his Reign, <hi>That the King could cauſe the Parliament to proceed upon Articles by him Limited:</hi> I think this might have ſpoil'd the <hi>Letter-Makers</hi> Jeſt; upon the Elections of <hi>Congee d'eſlire,</hi> when it would have chang'd his <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Debate</hi> too, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>Merit</hi> of <hi>Obedience:</hi> and yet theſe were the reſolutions long ſince of Judges and Lawyers. But this I know they'l ſay, was only offer'd at by an <hi>Arbitrary King.</hi> I am ſure an <hi>unfortunate one,</hi> and whom his Subjects us'd as <hi>ungratefully.</hi> But then wee'l turn the Tables, and tell them of a <hi>Popular</hi> one, whom they Complimented into the Throne, and that is his immediate Succeſſor: in the 6 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. he call'd a Parliament at <hi>Coventry,</hi> and ſome ſay in his proceſs to the Sherifs, and Writ of Summons, my Ld. <hi>Coke</hi> will only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to be in his Letters, he Commands that no Lawyer ſhall be return'd a Knight or Burgeſs: And ſo by his Royall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority it ſucceeded too. Tis true, in the next Year, and the next Parliament they Petition'd for the Liberty of freer Elections, and had it granted them; however, this ſtill proves, that ſuch <hi>Royal Interpoſitions</hi> are not altogether new; and that in former Reigns, the Prerogative ran higher in this point.</p>
               <p>So much for the <hi>ſecond</hi> Section of the <hi>ſame</hi> old Clamors rais'd and reviv'd: and that the <hi>Third</hi> may be the <hi>ſame</hi> too, ſome Churchmen have taken too <hi>much</hi> Pains, and I wiſh I could ſay, to <hi>little</hi> purpoſe. No ſooner was the Prince by Providence placed in his <hi>Throne,</hi> and whom their Sermons of Nonreſiſtance they ſay ſolely ſet upon it; (tho' his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Arms in the <hi>Weſt</hi> did ſomewhat ſecure it too); but ſome of the very ſame men manag'd the matter ſo; as if <note place="margin">The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> provided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch reflections on the Emperors Religion at the <hi>Dyet</hi> at <hi>Ratisbone.</hi>
                  </note> they had a mind to Preach him <hi>out</hi> again, <hi>Arbitrary power, Popery, Proteſtant Religion,</hi> was more the Theam of the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, than before it had been of the Fanaticks Papers and Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets: and that at the ſame time that his Majeſty had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of his <hi>own</hi> perſwaſion to meddle with nothing that was controverſial, * and which was as <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly</hi> obſerv'd by them too. This was a <hi>Great</hi> indecency at
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95944:18"/>
                  <hi>leaſt,</hi> if not a <hi>little</hi> diſobedience, eſpecially when after the Kings injunctions had ſatisfy'd them; He lookt upon it as tending to Sedition. Controverſies never yet edify'd <hi>much</hi> out of a Pulpit, and it may be well wiſht there were <hi>leſs</hi> of it in the Preſs. What party was the <hi>firſt</hi> aggreſſor will not ſo ſoon be <hi>found,</hi> tho' that which <hi>firſt</hi> deſiſts may be <hi>found</hi> the Wiſeſt. Arguments may now be better worded, <note n="*" place="margin">Some ſay the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Side be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan firſt in their Sermons. <hi>Vid.</hi> Preface to the further Deſence of the Biſhop of <hi>Condom.</hi>
                  </note> as all Arts are by length of time improv'd; but the beſt of our <hi>Virtuoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> in Divinity, have with all their late <hi>Experiments</hi> hardly made any new <hi>Diſcoveries;</hi> and <hi>little</hi> has been ſaid after they have labour'd ſo <hi>much</hi> on both ſides, but what has been brought on the Stage before. People enter only the Liſt <hi>now</hi> to ſhew their Courage, and make a Spectacle, and like <hi>Gladiaters</hi> ſeem to draw by conſent, and <hi>aſſign</hi> the Places of their Combate; and ſure never was that ſacred Science ſo truly <hi>Polemical:</hi> whereas after all, the Myſteries of <hi>Religion</hi> muſt either be left to <hi>God</hi> that gave it<hi>:</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> that he has Eſtabliſht, or to every <hi>Individual Breaſt.</hi> If to the <hi>firſt,</hi> we muſt leave off all diſputes, and leave the Iſſue to <hi>God,</hi> and the Laſt day; if to a <hi>Church,</hi> then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt to a Univerſal and Catholick one: to which, if we ſubmit to be guided by, we muſt <hi>think</hi> it Infallible, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it <hi>be;</hi> for ſure 'tis beſt to truſt <hi>moſt</hi> our Salvation where there is the <hi>leaſt</hi> Error; and madneſs, to ſwear <hi>Abſolutely</hi> to the <hi>truth</hi> of a thing that may <hi>poſſibly</hi> be <hi>falſe:</hi> And if the Bible, and the Books of Scripture as <hi>well Interpreted,</hi> muſt be the guide, who ſhall be Judg of its being done ſo <hi>well?</hi> and I cannot ſee how a <hi>National</hi> Church, or <hi>Eſtabliſht</hi> one, that will not pretend to this infallibility, can command with Puniſhment, Pains, Death and Anathema, to believe as ſhe does <hi>interpret,</hi> (unleſs we acknowleg'd that Church to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in the <hi>right,</hi> that has the <hi>Power):</hi> for if ſhe puniſhes People for not believing her to <hi>Interpret well,</hi> it will be hard for her to <hi>avoid</hi> an impoſſibility of <hi>interpreting amiſs,</hi> &amp; that will amount almoſt to ſomewhat of a <hi>Judg</hi> that cannot <hi>Err:</hi> ſo that unavoidably we fall into the laſt part of the Dilem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, of letting <hi>every</hi> one adhere to the <hi>Expoſitions</hi> and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of that <hi>particular</hi> Church, which agree beſt with his Reaſon, and are moſt ſatisfactory to his Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:95944:18"/>
I confeſs, theſe Conſiderations weigh'd with me ſo much, as to think an <hi>Eſtabliſh't Toleration</hi> unavoidable, both from the Circumſtances of the <hi>State,</hi> and the Doctrine of the <hi>Church;</hi> for as <hi>Infallibility</hi> is hard to be <hi>believ'd,</hi> ſo ſure 'tis more <hi>hard</hi> to think, a Church can force you to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> Her, that does not pretend to it: and if an Alliance between <hi>that</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> be ſuch a Contradiction; what an Abſurdity muſt Perſecution be, from thoſe that will not preſume to be <hi>Infallible?</hi> and that an <hi>Abſolute</hi> or <hi>Implicit</hi> Subſcription to all her Articles, has been alway requir'd, I need not prove; ſince <hi>Diſſenters</hi> 'tis certain have often Offer'd <hi>Conditional</hi> Ones; and were not ſo much as ſuffer'd this modeſt Interpoſition, of ſubſcribing to her <hi>Laws,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">So Adjudg'd, 33, 34. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> &amp; were Rejected on the ſame Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in the 13, 14. <hi>Car.</hi> 2.</note> as far as they were agreeable with thoſe of <hi>GOD,</hi> and the <hi>Land;</hi> which I wiſh, may not lay too much of the Schiſm at <hi>their</hi> door; that think it only to be ſuppreſt, with Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities and Executions: but while we muſter up theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments about Religion, we raiſe but the Legion of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits we would lay; and is only ſo far, from an Impertinence and Digreſſion, as it terminates to prove the neceſſity of a Tolleration, and the deſign of the Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>I do no Injury to them or the Truth, when I tell them <hi>thus;</hi> That the Din of <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> has founded too much of late the alarum from the Pulpits; as if the Watch-man had been plac't upon the Top of the Tower, and ſeen the whole Hoſt of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> to come up and beſiege the <note n="*" place="margin">A <hi>City</hi> that was of Old, <hi>At unity with it ſelf.</hi>
                  </note> City of <hi>Jeruſalem; Martyrdom, Perſecution, Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings</hi> have been the Subject of ſome Sermons, not as Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Exhortations; but rather to create dreadful Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which can't be ſo well Juſtify'd by ſuch as are fond for the retaining the Power of <hi>Forcing;</hi> and were it not ſo intended, the Preachers up of ſuch Suggeſtions, would ſee themſelves impertinent; when they take their Texts from all the miſeries of the afflicted, as if they were already in Torment: when they make the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> another <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and tell us of <hi>her Tribulation of Ten Dayes.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this is not a ſeaſon of talking of <hi>Fire</hi> and Faggot; as if all <hi>Smithfield</hi> were in a Blaze; when the tenderneſs of the moſt Indulgent Monarch, makes it his care, that there may not be ſo much as a <hi>Fine</hi> Inflicted for Religion; when He proteſts and declares to the contrary; and by Practice,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95944:19"/>
and the very <hi>Powers</hi> of his Prerogative (they will hardly grant him) has endeavour'd to make it good. Not only ſome Sermons, but ſeveral Books aſſert theſe ſuggeſtions to be ſober <hi>Truth;</hi> and I hope I ſhall not become any peoples <hi>Enemy</hi> for telling it: who if he were known, no one would imagin it Malice meant. I cannot think a <hi>Particular</hi> Invec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, or Satyr of a Zealot, ought to be paum'd upon a <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> Aſſembly or the Church; or the whole Body ſuffer for any Members Fault, tho' they would do well too, to deal as fairly with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> and not reproach it for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the <hi>Depoſing Power,</hi> and the <hi>Deſtroying</hi> of <hi>KINGS,</hi> when by their own Confeſſion, they find it only among <hi>ſome</hi> of their Writers; which by the <hi>Sorbone</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> were ſufficiently Condemned. 'Tis hard to tell a Church, <hi>She</hi> is of that Opinion which She generally denies; and ſhould ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tell a Third what I think; were he in his Wits, he would ſooner take my word for it.</p>
               <p>'Tis to be wiſh't ſhe would put in practice, what I know ſhe has often requeſted from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> for it's Juſtification; to Diſcover and Cenſure ſuch as are Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours in theſe inflaming Diſcourſes, and by that beſt of Vindication, diſown them. I could recite ſome Paſſages to this purpoſe out of ſeveral Prints; but can in kindneſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear them too; ſince they are in pieces that have been <hi>leſs</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>notice</hi> of; and ſhall only touch upon thoſe that are <hi>more</hi> generally <hi>Known.</hi> The <hi>Notable Letter</hi> to a <hi>Diſſenter;</hi> The <hi>Tryal</hi> and <hi>Examination</hi> of the <hi>New Teſt of the Church of Englands Loyalty:</hi> which Latter, tho' a Piece diſcommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by both Parties, for it's Zeal and Abuſe, ought to have been Anſwer'd with leſs Reflexion on the Crown; and the moſt ſeditious Papers of <hi>Dr. B. All</hi> theſe own themſelves under their Hand, Members of that Communion; while they induſtriouſly diſperſe things dangerous to the <hi>State,</hi> and diſagreeing to the Doctrines of that <hi>Church</hi> they would offer to defend. The whole drift and deſign of theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, is only to perſwade the People, that <hi>Popery</hi> is ſolely Concern'd; even where the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> is ſo much promis'd to be Protected. I forbear to repeat Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on a Government, that are Libels almoſt in their very repetition, to ſhoot back their <hi>Arrows,</hi> even <hi>Bitter Words,</hi> ſhould be ſo done too, that the <hi>Plague</hi> might be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95944:19"/>
                  <hi>ſtay'd,</hi> without <hi>ſpreading</hi> the <hi>Infection:</hi> he is but a bad <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> that comes with a <hi>Doſe</hi> in his <hi>Pocket,</hi> and the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> in his <hi>Face:</hi> It would be but little ſervice at this time to the Crown, to reprint a <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> of <hi>Tolleration Diſcuſt,</hi> for the ſake of ſome <hi>Cold</hi> animadverſions upon it; and ſo moſt <hi>Officiouſly</hi> Confute with an <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> what is a <hi>Duty</hi> to ſilence, and ſuppreſs. <hi>Sedition</hi> that is ſet of with ſuch ſmooth Inſinuations, ſhould be dealt with like a Wench, that has us'd much dawbing; who is then beſt <hi>Expos'd,</hi> when you have pull'd off ſome Petticoats, and waſh't away her Paint; for the Preſs, and Printing, depends upon it's Management, and is onely an undecided and Indifferent Engine and Art; either of <hi>pretended Good</hi> to the Government, or <hi>real Ill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I come now in the next place to make ſome Remarks upon another Method that has been taken to hinder the meeting of another <hi>Healing Parliament;</hi> and that is not only in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging all <hi>Addreſſes</hi> to the KING that intimated their inclination towards it; but even the returning ſo much as Thanks to His MAJESTY, for Repeating of his Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to protect a Church, that has given him the greateſt Power in Eccleſiaſticals: and <hi>all</hi> this ungrateful obſtinacy for the ſake of <hi>Religion</hi> too; and as their beſt <hi>Reaſons</hi> are, <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Oxford.</hi> Reaſons. Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dr. <hi>B.</hi> &amp;c.</note> leſt it ſhould be thought to be <hi>Precarious:</hi> 'Tis to be La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, to ſee ſo Learned a Body that was lately ſo Signa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd, (as ſome ſaid) for a <hi>Criminal</hi> Obedience, a <hi>Paſſive</hi> one: and burnt thoſe Authors in Effigie, that could not come up to their moſt Meritorious Opinions. 'Tis hard to ſee <hi>ſuch,</hi> ſo ſuddenly chang'd, as to think it no <hi>Crime,</hi> the <note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>Caſe</hi> of their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testing College,</hi> tho' <hi>Conſcience</hi> muſt give it ſuch a <hi>modeſt</hi> Complection, was, in plain terms, the greateſt <hi>Contumacy</hi> to their <hi>King; Conſcience</hi> (if ever a pretence) was truly made ſo here, for not to mention his Majeſties <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> and their own <hi>Diſpenſing</hi> with ſome of their <hi>Coll. Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut.</hi> or their Societies having <hi>ſubmitted</hi> to the ſame Caſe, and ſo confeſt it in former Reigns, 'tis known to <hi>both</hi> the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitys,</hi> that where the <hi>Stat.</hi> of their <hi>Coll.</hi> obliges them to Elect their Fellows only from <hi>ſuch</hi> a County. that <hi>themſelves</hi> have put Perſons of <hi>another</hi> to move for a Mandamus, and brought them in too, with a <hi>Non Obstante</hi> to their <hi>Statutes</hi> and their <hi>Oaths.</hi> But beſides, neither of thoſe are Concern'd, for the Mandate of their King is an <hi>abſolute</hi> command to <hi>Admit;</hi> and their obligation to their <hi>Oaths,</hi> is only in thoſe Points, where they are left to <hi>Elect.</hi> In ſhort, their Combining to be ſtubborn, was but a Confederacy againſt the Power of their Prince, whoſe <hi>Proceedings</hi> will <hi>Abound</hi> with Juſtice, when their Puniſhment may <hi>Want</hi> Pity.</note> 
                  <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeying</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:95944:20"/>
of their <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>Oppoſing</hi> their <hi>KING.</hi> 'Tis ſtrange, that ſuch Men muſt be ſo ſparing of their <hi>Thanks</hi> now to their PRINCE, that <hi>once</hi> thought they could never return enough (when even for a common Kindneſs, we uſually ſay among our ſelves, <hi>Thank ye Twice);</hi> and to ſay that for the <hi>ſame</hi> aſſurance, they had Addreſt long ſince, when He came to the Throne; was but little better, than telling His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> He might have <hi>ſpar'd</hi> his Complement, and this Condeſcenſion to his Subjects, was a ſort of <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>errogation.</hi> I could never imagine what was the meaning of ſuch Irreverent <hi>Reſervedneſs</hi> in ſo many Members of a <hi>Church,</hi> that was once ſo <hi>Forward,</hi> as to fall under ſome Peoples Laſh for <hi>Officious:</hi> but ſome Perſons now, upon the pretence of their Integrity, are tickl'd with the Vanity of being Fam'd for <hi>ſtout,</hi> and <hi>ſtanding to their Principles;</hi> and Men of ſuch a temper, from the Fame that they affect, muſt endeavour to be ſurly and moroſe; but this is ſtill, but a deſperate ſort of <hi>Imprudence,</hi> if we conſider the Caſe that Occaſions this Diſcourſe, no <hi>Wiſe</hi> Man will be ſtiff and ſturdy to thoſe that can <hi>humble</hi> him; and when the <hi>Inſolency</hi> of the Provocation may procure more Miſchiefs, <hi>than</hi> any by all his <hi>Bravery</hi> he can defy.</p>
               <p>To tell us that a <note n="*" place="margin">Tryal of the New Teſt. Page 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Legal</hi> Eſtabliſhment will force a <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> Protection; and that the King has <hi>ſworn</hi> to defend the <hi>Church,</hi> as bold upbraidings as they be to the <hi>Crown,</hi> are but <hi>bad</hi> Encouragement to continue their KING's Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and as Lame excuſes for their Ingratitude; for ſure the Countenance of a Prince would be ſomwhat of a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative too, and not indanger their <hi>Security</hi> from the <hi>Law:</hi> whatever <hi>Oath</hi> he took to Protect their Religion, he did not <hi>Swear</hi> too to put out his Declaration of Aſſurance alſo; and tho' he be oblidg'd to Govern by <hi>Law,</hi> I don't know what <hi>Law</hi> oblidges him to tell them ſo often that He <hi>Will;</hi> In this ſure his Majeſty has <hi>done More</hi> than he was bound to do; and then, thoſe that are deficient in their dutiful Return, can never have done ſo <hi>much:</hi> no <hi>Silly</hi> Sophiſtry, no <hi>Fooliſh Fear</hi> will wipe away the Scandal of ſuch a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable reproach; and it will ſound a little harſh, (tho' the danger were ſuch indeed) when ſome of Her Enemies ſhall
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95944:20"/>
obſerve, that for keeping out ſome Popiſh <hi>Secluded Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> the Loyal Church of <hi>England,</hi> is now the <hi>Non-addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers.</hi> But to do Her Juſtice too, ſome of her Biſhops upon more ſerious Conſultations, did atone for a more General defect, and <hi>Oblidg'd</hi> their Communion by a <hi>Prudential</hi> Act, that fain would have been ſo improvidently <hi>Wiſe</hi> as to <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oblige</hi> her ſelf.</p>
               <p>I could ſuperadd here, that other ſilly Suggeſtion of the Reſtitution of <hi>Abby-Lands;</hi> were not the Panick Fear of it Superſeded by a Learned Treatiſe, and the Confirmation of them from the Pope, even in the time of Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> the common Intreſt of <hi>Papiſts</hi> to Oppoſe it, and that his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty might as well ſet up a Court of <hi>Wards</hi> and <hi>Liverys;</hi> and ſo make <hi>All Lands</hi> ly at his Mercy: and that <hi>He</hi> himſelf has <hi>Aſſur'd</hi> them Expreſly to the <hi>Scots</hi> in his Proclamation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI. The <hi>Means</hi> that may be us'd to Prevent the <hi>Malice</hi> and Inſinuation of Such as would <hi>Obſtruct</hi> It.</head>
               <p>AND now at length, we are arriv'd to put a Period to theſe Points; and having conſidered the <hi>Methods</hi> that have been us'd to <hi>Hinder</hi> this <hi>Healing Parliament,</hi> we are come to the <hi>Sixth</hi> and laſt <hi>Section,</hi> to Conſider the <hi>Sixth Point; The means how to Prevent the Deſigns and Inſinuations of ſuch as would Obſtruct It.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for that, reflect but a <hi>little</hi> on theſe following <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations:</hi> if they have but <hi>little</hi> Weight with them, you are not burdned <hi>much;</hi> if they have <hi>not</hi> a <hi>little,</hi> 'tis your Intereſt to bear with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſider,</hi> That notwithſtanding the ſpecious pretences, of ſome ſpiteful and malicious men, theſe dreadful apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that are put into your heads, may be none at all; at leaſt not ſuch as they are repreſented; that the Authors of them may be men that oppoſe his Majeſtys Gracious intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, more out of malice to him, than kindneſs to themſelves, and their <hi>Church:</hi> I ſpeak to <hi>Church-men</hi> (for Diſſenters can't
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95944:21"/>
be ſuppos'd diſſatisfy'd with that mercy that makes them happy beyond their expectation) but they are Members, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve of this <hi>Eſtabliſht Church</hi> (for all the many Letters to the other Congregations) that from the preſent Conſtitution of our Government, I fancy muſt for the <hi>moſt</hi> part be concern'd, that can <hi>best</hi> Second the Clemency of their KING, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm to them an <hi>eſtabliſht</hi> Toleration by a Law, and ſuch an one as will repeal <hi>All</hi> thoſe by which they have a long time ſo <hi>unreaſonably</hi> ſuffer'd.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>I. <hi>'Tis Reaſonable to be done.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>'Tis Fitteſt for them to do it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>'Tis Their Intereſt ſo to do.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>And firſt, let them tell me, their beſt pretenders to <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> whether the ſuffering for Conſcience ſake, can without the greateſt reluctance of Conſcience it ſelf, be defended; or whether it's advocates are not toucht with an inward aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, at the ſame time they write for it, eſpecially, ſhould they reflect, it may be their turn to ſuffer? whether a <hi>body</hi> ought to ſuffer for the ſentiments and ſuggeſtion of the <hi>Soul</hi> that informs it, when it conſiſts only in the Worſhiping of the ſame God, in which all Chriſtian Churches agree? ſure theſe men are not ſo fond of the Fire and Faggot they ſo much fear, as to Juſtifie for it the perſecution of the Primitive Chriſtians, and make their <hi>Martyrdoms</hi> but ſo many Judicial Proceſſes for their <hi>Nonconformity,</hi> when of the old <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> Emperors, few were of Opinion in this Point, to Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh people into Compliance: the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, I think, is <hi>now</hi> ſo well ſettl'd, and the <hi>Seed</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> ſo well ſown, that there is no great need of the <hi>Sanguis Martyrum</hi> to water it; neither is the repreſentation of it in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſo improper, or the compariſon ſo abſurd; for tho there may be a better Warranty to force people of the ſame Faith in Chriſt, to the worſhipping their God in an <hi>Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht</hi> Way, than the <hi>Pagans</hi> could pretend to, for the forc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to be <hi>Infidels;</hi> yet this would juſtify them <hi>ſtill,</hi> who thought their Irreligion and Idolatry the beſt of Devotion, and had the Decrees of their Emperors to Authoriſe it; which were with them the Statutes and Laws of the Land: and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95944:21"/>
I am ſorry that I can add, that ſuch ſeverities amongſt our ſelves, ſeem <hi>much</hi> worſe, when we agree in one <hi>common Faith,</hi> in one <hi>Creed,</hi> in one <hi>Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> neither is the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Puniſhment, and ſort of Suffering ſo abſurd; for tho we do not exerciſe, by our Laws, the <hi>Long Sheet</hi> in <hi>Foxes Martyrology,</hi> and are left, as we ſee the <hi>Heathens</hi> were there, to ſtudy Torment; tho' the <hi>Flames</hi> that he has made to rage ſo ſtrongly through his vaſt Volumms, are happily quencht, all Burnings forbidden, and Religion no more to ſuffer with a Writ <hi>de' Haeretico:</hi> it will be as little credit to <hi>it ſtill;</hi> that 'tis <hi>now,</hi> no <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggot</hi> that can force a Conſcience, but only an <hi>Hangman</hi> and an <hi>Halter.</hi> 'Tis <hi>true,</hi> that whatever has been the ſeverity of the Laws, ſuch cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties have ſeldom been put in Execution; but to ſay, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were, is as certainly <hi>falſe:</hi> Several in Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> Reign, ſuffer'd meerly for profeſſing of their Faith, and my ſelf remember <hi>three</hi> that dy'd for it, and that <hi>only</hi> for being Prieſts, in the late Perjurious time of Arbitrary Oaths, and pack't Evidence; beſides, <hi>another</hi> that was condemn'd and baniſht; whom I have met with ſince in his Exile. But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be the <hi>Mercy</hi> of the King, the <hi>Cruelty</hi> of the Laws can never be the more defended, and they are never the more <hi>Merciful</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Clemency</hi> of the Prince that remits them. In the mean time, ſuch bloody ſanctions are certainly blots to that Religion that keeps them upon Record; and if we <hi>commend</hi> thoſe that are for retaining them, we muſt at the ſame time <hi>blame</hi> thoſe that but ſo lately repeal'd the Writ <hi>de Comburendo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>much</hi> for the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of them, and but this <hi>little</hi> for <hi>Fact;</hi> they cannot tell us of any Country that is Proteſtant, nor of any Catholick, but where the Inquiſition is Eſtabliſht, where it is made Capital to profeſs a particular Faith, even in <hi>France</hi> (whoſe Cruelty is decry'd ſo much) tho' the <hi>fugitives</hi> are driven to the Galleys, they are not gon ſo far yet, as for <hi>profeſſing,</hi> to make it Death. How quietly do thoſe peaceable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries Flouriſh, where at this time for Conſcience there is no Oppreſſion at all? The celebrated Dr. ought to have Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd <hi>that</hi> too, as well as the Miſery of thoſe places where any Perſecution reigns. The Proteſtant and Popiſh Churches,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95944:22"/>
I've ſeen ſtand very Quietly together in moſt of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Maſtrich, Breda,</hi> &amp;c.</note> fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier Towns of <hi>Holland;</hi> and in the Dominions of ſeveral PRINCES of <hi>Germany;</hi> and the Magiſtracy by <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heidelberg, Ausburg</hi> nd <hi>Duſeldorp.</hi> By the Treaty at <hi>Munſter</hi> &amp; <hi>Oſnabrugh.</hi>
                  </note> turns Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted by the two different Perſwaſions, without any Laws for <hi>Hanging</hi> or <hi>Burning</hi> one another; and 'tis ſure, no <hi>Bad</hi> Preſident, if we only take Example by our <hi>Proteſtant Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as ſome of our Laws are <hi>ſanguinary</hi> for Matters of meer <hi>Religion:</hi> ſo there are others that are leſs ſevere, tho' as inconſiſtent with the Charity of a <hi>Church,</hi> or the Quiet of a <hi>State;</hi> ſuch as <hi>Fines, Confiſcations</hi> and <hi>Impriſonments;</hi> and what Inconveniences they have brought upon the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in <hi>general,</hi> as well as the poor Sufferers in <hi>particular,</hi> we have touch't upon before, and now as needleſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. The Diſcovery of thoſe vaſt Summs of which the KING is defrauded, may hereafter make appear what was Extorted from the <hi>Subject,</hi> to the Enriching of ſome <hi>Knaves,</hi> and the Ruine of more <hi>Honeſt</hi> Families.</p>
               <p>But the preſſing the <hi>Reaſonableneſs</hi> of it ſo much, ſeems almoſt unneceſſary, when the moſt inviſible Commiſſioner from the <hi>Church</hi> that is <hi>ſo Concern'd,</hi> comes up <hi>ſo far,</hi> as to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance with his Celebrated <hi>Reaſonings</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs</hi> of theſe ſevere Sanctions; by ſeeming ſo willing to <hi>Suſpend</hi> them for the ſake of <hi>ſome</hi> Diſſenters, &amp; not <hi>others:</hi> &amp; ſhall this be taken for <hi>Reaſon</hi> too? ſure the Univerſities will teach him better Logick. I know the Aphoriſms of their Schools in ſome Sence ſay; <hi>That of Contraries there is the ſame Reaſon;</hi> but ſure they won't make it out in <hi>Contradictories</hi> too. Is then <hi>Tolleration?</hi> is the <hi>Repealing</hi> of the <hi>Laws Reaſonable,</hi> for the ſake of <hi>ſome</hi> Diſſenters, and not <hi>others?</hi> I don't know what they fear of <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> I am ſure this is <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Reaſoning;</hi> and but little better than <hi>none</hi> at <hi>all.</hi> The <hi>Letter</hi> might have been a little <hi>more</hi> Contracted; to ſay <hi>much</hi> in a <hi>little,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> the ſolidity of his mighty Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made up into <hi>one</hi> ſyllogiſm (i. e.) <hi>It is but Iuſt that all the Penal Laws for Religion, ſhould be Repeal'd; but that all Penal Laws for Religion, ſhould be Repeal'd, is not Iuſt;</hi> Ergô, <hi>The Laws againſt the Roman Catholicks,</hi> &amp;c. If there be any Contradiction in the Terms and Premiſes;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95944:22"/>
who can help it? for certainly ſuffering for Religion, muſt be the ſame to <hi>All,</hi> whatever are the Profeſſors of it; and if we once grant it <hi>unreaſonable</hi> to <hi>ſome,</hi> then preſently to <hi>all</hi> unprejudic'd <hi>Reaſon,</hi> untainted with Intereſt and Art, it muſt conclude <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally,</hi> and extend to <hi>All;</hi> and I <hi>know</hi> theſe <hi>Barbarcus</hi> Logicians <hi>know</hi> ſo too, and include in it both <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Jew,</hi> and any thing that's <hi>Pagan,</hi> unleſs it be Mr. <hi>Johnſons</hi> the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Popery &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſm.</note> 
                  <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are then the Roman Catholicks <hi>no Diſſenters?</hi> or are they <hi>Diſſenters</hi> with you worſe than Infidels? for it ſeems, for the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Proteſtant. <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> the <hi>Circumcis'd Diſſenters,</hi> the <hi>Mahometan Diſſenters,</hi> and the <hi>Pagan Diſſenters;</hi> theſe <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Laws</hi> are <hi>too</hi> Cruel and Severe. May <note n="*" place="margin">By 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 25 <hi>Car. 2d.</hi> &amp; 30. They are deny'd Office. they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar'd from Sitting in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to which they are <hi>Born.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Birthright,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">By 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> They are forbid the Court &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, Towns &amp; City.</note> 
                  <hi>Humanity</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">By 31. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz.</hi> 13 <hi>Jac.</hi> 3. <hi>Car.</hi> 1. Their Aſſurances, Wills. Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Truſts Voided, Goods confiſcated, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> and <hi>Property,</hi> be concern'd in the Caſe, and made Motives to the removing of what is <note n="*" place="margin">By 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 25 <hi>Car. 2d.</hi> &amp; 30. They are deny'd Office. they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar'd from Sitting in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to which they are <hi>Born.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Injurious,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">By 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> They are forbid the Court &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, Towns &amp; City.</note> 
                  <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous,</hi> or <note n="*" place="margin">By 31. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz.</hi> 13 <hi>Jac.</hi> 3. <hi>Car.</hi> 1. Their Aſſurances, Wills. Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Truſts Voided, Goods confiſcated, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> 
                  <hi>Prejudicial</hi> to them; and cannot <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> come in for a ſhare by <note n="*" place="margin">By 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 25 <hi>Car. 2d.</hi> &amp; 30. They are deny'd Office. they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar'd from Sitting in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to which they are <hi>Born.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Birth,</hi> by <note n="*" place="margin">By 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> They are forbid the Court &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, Towns &amp; City.</note> 
                  <hi>Nature,</hi> or <note n="*" place="margin">By 31. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz.</hi> 13 <hi>Jac.</hi> 3. <hi>Car.</hi> 1. Their Aſſurances, Wills. Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Truſts Voided, Goods confiſcated, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> common <hi>Equity;</hi> or are Papiſts not <hi>Born</hi> to the <note n="*" place="margin">By 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 25 <hi>Car. 2d.</hi> &amp; 30. They are deny'd Office. they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar'd from Sitting in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to which they are <hi>Born.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges</hi> of <hi>Society;</hi> are they all <note n="*" place="margin">By 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> They are forbid the Court &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, Towns &amp; City.</note> 
                  <hi>Beaſts,</hi> or all <note n="*" place="margin">By 31. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz.</hi> 13 <hi>Jac.</hi> 3. <hi>Car.</hi> 1. Their Aſſurances, Wills. Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Truſts Voided, Goods confiſcated, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> 
                  <hi>Beggars?</hi> (and truly if we may truſt ſome deſcriptions, not long ſince applauded, they have ſet them out but little better. Sure this is not the way for continuing the Fame of that Church, for being alway on the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Tryal of the New <hi>Teſt.</hi> page 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Charitable ſide toward Papiſts;</hi> this will inſtead of <hi>having her Charity miſtaken,</hi> ſhew that ſhe <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes her Charity.</hi> It would be a more <hi>Charitable Act</hi> for this Church, by way of an expedient, to get <hi>one</hi> Statute to paſs for making the Papiſts <hi>Perfect Out-Laws (i. e.)</hi> as my Ld. <hi>Coke</hi> expounds it, to be <hi>hunted like Woolfes,</hi> then to keep <hi>Twenty-four</hi> in Force, for their Confuſion, Death and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. How can it be anſwer'd either to <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Man,</hi> when by ſo publick an <hi>Act</hi> as a <hi>National Repeal,</hi> you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that to make men ſuffer for Religion is <hi>Barbarous</hi> and <hi>Inhuman,</hi> and at the ſame time you leave upon Record the ſevereſt of thoſe ſufferings in their fulleſt force; this is filing up ſuch a laſting reproach to your ſelves, that you would ſeem to take care, leſt <hi>time</hi> ſhould take it off, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy fail to be tranſmitted to <hi>poſterity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as by <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> they muſt <hi>come in</hi> for a Common Share, ſo I ſee no reaſon of <hi>State,</hi> no <hi>Civil</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95944:23"/>
that Obliges you to keep them <hi>out;</hi> 'tis but a bad ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the <hi>Clergy</hi> (as often as 'tis us'd) when from the <hi>Popes</hi> Supremacy, they make all <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſuch mortal Enemies to <hi>all</hi> Monarchs; they might as well prove that by <hi>their</hi> own ſwearing to obey their <hi>Metropolitan,</hi> they part with their Allegiance to the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and ſo ſet <hi>Lambeth</hi> too againſt <hi>Whitehall:</hi> 'Tis profeſt by them <hi>All,</hi> they acknowledg no other Power of the Pope but in <hi>Spirituals;</hi> and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants will tell them that they <hi>do,</hi> whatever they <hi>do</hi> or <hi>ſay</hi> to the contrary; nay, tho' ſome have diſallow'd even <hi>that,</hi> and will no practiſe to the contrary pleaſe them? does not the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> the moſt Catholick King alive, live <hi>as free</hi> from Rebellions (I am aſham'd to ſay more) then the King of <hi>England?</hi> is not the King of <hi>France</hi> as abſolute as our own at <hi>Home,</hi> &amp; as ready to quarrel with <hi>Rome</hi> upon the leaſt diminution of his Right? and to come <hi>homer</hi> to our <hi>ſelves,</hi> have not our <hi>own</hi> Laws juſtl'd out this Jealouſy with the <hi>Popes</hi> Pretentions, in ſeveral <note n="†" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Stat.</hi> of <hi>Carlile</hi> of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſoes,</hi> &amp;c.</note> Statutes, under our <hi>Catholick</hi> Kings.</p>
               <p>But beſides their <hi>Principles</hi> (as to their particular <hi>Practiſe</hi> and Behaviour) have they not given <hi>England</hi> Proof enough, they can live in it like good Subjects; and if we put the <hi>Teſt</hi> of their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> againſt <hi>That</hi> made to <hi>prevent Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> I am afraid it will ſpoil all the <hi>Praeamble.</hi> Gentlemen, Matter of Fact confirms it; and 'tis in vain to diſpute: <hi>They</hi> Fought with You for CHARLES the FIRST, in the <hi>Field;</hi> and <hi>They alone</hi> Preſerv'd the SECOND in the <hi>Royal Oak;</hi> forſook their Fortune at <hi>Home,</hi> and follow'd Him in his Exile <hi>Abroad.</hi> The <hi>Beſt</hi> of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> could do no <hi>more;</hi> tho' ſome might fare <hi>better</hi> that did not ſo <hi>much:</hi> and <hi>their</hi> being among the <hi>Rebels,</hi> is but a Libel of <note n="*" place="margin">This their Celebrated Dr. has made K. <hi>James</hi> 1. to <hi>curſe</hi> his <hi>Poſterity:</hi> K. <hi>Charles</hi> 1. to <hi>betray his Friends, Char. 2d.</hi> to <hi>deceive his People, James 2d.</hi> to <hi>Oppreſs</hi> his <hi>Subjects:</hi> as if He had labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Infamy of Libelling <hi>four</hi> Kings in <hi>one</hi> piece of Paper; as if his Quarrel were too meanly commenc'd, if it did not ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in the laſting Reproach of our whole <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Line; and he had better Authority to do it, becauſe himſelf a <hi>Scot;</hi> and his <hi>Soveraign Lords</hi> were all at <hi>laſt</hi> to Suffer, becauſe his <hi>Maſter</hi> by him was at <hi>first</hi> Betray'd. <hi>Vid.</hi> Paper, <hi>page</hi> 12, 36, 23. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Burnet</hi>'s, both on the <note n="†" place="margin">How can this <hi>Establiſht Church,</hi> if it has any Veneration to the <hi>Duſt</hi> of their Late <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Prince Deceas'd?</hi> applaud, approve of the Writings of ſuch an Injurious Impoſtor, that would have his <hi>Name</hi> Buried too; and that tells them, <hi>The greatest Kindneſs that can he done to His Memory,</hi> is to <hi>Forget Him.</hi> page 23.</note> KING's Declaration, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:95944:23"/>
                  <hi>them:</hi> which is ſufficiently Baffl'd by the well-known Story of <hi>Coll. Aſhton;</hi> who, when refus'd by <hi>his KING,</hi> was Courted into Commiſſion by the <hi>Parliament;</hi> which, aſſoon as Receiv'd, he Laid himſelf and That at His Majeſties Feet. This is as certain, as that ſome <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects were in Rebellion; which, if ſuch a thing muſt Reflect on a <hi>Church,</hi> I am afraid <hi>that</hi> will very much ſuffer: and to ſay the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> and Eſtabliſh't <hi>Church</hi> did diſown all ſuch Proceedings, will not much mend the Matter, when ſo <hi>many</hi> of her Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers were ſo <hi>mainly</hi> concern'd; for tho' the Sectaries at laſt prevail'd, for the ſubverting of the <hi>State;</hi> the Commons of <hi>Forty-One</hi> that Commenc'd the Quarrel were generally <hi>Church-men;</hi> and 'tis not impoſſible for ſuch to be Zealous, and Diſcontented too; neither is the Communion bound to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for the faults of thoſe members ſhe Condemns; the Lord Lieutenants that this Parliament choſe, were for the moſt part <hi>Conforming</hi> men, and <hi>Eſſex</hi>'s Army had <hi>many</hi> ſuch Officers too; ſome can tell us this for a <hi>truth,</hi> that liv'd then, and their Catalogue for the Militia makes it no <hi>ly.</hi> 'Tis too much to <hi>remember,</hi> and too ſoon to <hi>forget,</hi> that moſt of the <hi>Excluding Members</hi> were of <hi>that</hi> Communion, as well as all the moſt Eminent Conſpirators in the laſt Plot and Rebellion; and even her <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> was Burleſque by one that publickly profeſt himſelf her ſon: I ſpeak it not for a diſparagement to the <hi>Church,</hi> that was then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond diſpute, both in <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Practiſe</hi> faithful to the <hi>Crown;</hi> but to ſatisfy ſuch men, that it is both imprudent and irrational for them to fling out ſuch arguments as will fly in their face; and as unjuſt to cenſure a whole Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, only for the fault of ſome of it's Profeſſors: for <hi>King-killing</hi> and <hi>depoſing,</hi> to condemn a Catholick Communion; and from the writings of a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> to upbraid the <hi>Church</hi> of Rome, and that in Terms too bitter for a <hi>Prayer;</hi> to make their <hi>Religion</hi> to be <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and their <hi>Faith Faction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo much for the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of a <hi>Legal Toleration,</hi> and <hi>General Comprehenſion.</hi> Now to ſhew too, that the <hi>Members of the Church Eſtabliſht,</hi> ought to be willing to get it <hi>Done:</hi> And that <hi>2d. It is fitteſt for Them to do it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>firſt,</hi> they muſt remember, that by <hi>themſelves</hi> theſe Laws
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95944:24"/>
were <hi>made;</hi> and as a learned Lawyer lets us know, that he is the <hi>beſt Judg of a Law that has the Power to make it;</hi> ſo we may ſay, thoſe that <hi>make</hi> it, when it happens to become unreaſonable, are the <hi>Fitteſt</hi> to get it <hi>Repeal'd:</hi> if the <hi>Prelates</hi> are become <hi>leſs riged,</hi> if the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Perſecution</hi> is turn'd into a <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> if they make no matter of <hi>Conſcience</hi> to give <hi>Indulgence,</hi> what greater proof can they give of <hi>all</hi> this, then by their <hi>own</hi> voluntary Cancelling thoſe ſevere Laws, which <hi>themſelves</hi> muſt own, for ſome conſiderations of State were <hi>only</hi> made? This would be a much better evidence of their more mercifull diſpoſition then <hi>all</hi> the Promiſes of <hi>T. W.</hi> It will be no ſuch <hi>ſcandal,</hi> tho' it be <hi>true,</hi> when <hi>all</hi> that can be ſaid, is, <hi>You were overſeen: Length</hi> of time, and revolution of affairs, tell People at <hi>laſt</hi> their <hi>long</hi> errors, tho commonly too <hi>late,</hi> and <hi>then</hi> for the moſt part make men <hi>wiſe,</hi> when they cannot make <hi>amends</hi> for their <hi>folly.</hi> But Fortune ſeems to favour you <hi>now,</hi> and puts it in your Power, to <hi>mend all</hi> that was <hi>amiſs;</hi> ſhe ſeems to Court your Inclinations, and tempt you, to <hi>Credit your ſelves, Gratify your</hi> KING, <hi>and Pleaſure all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next Place, I hope it will be as plain, That <hi>3d, It is their Intereſt ſo to do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> becauſe 'tis <hi>they themſelves</hi> that have aſſerted the Kings <hi>Power</hi> in Ecleſiaſticals to be <hi>ſuch;</hi> that it may be much to their detriment to Provoke <hi>ſuch</hi> a Prince, whom <hi>they</hi> by Law have made ſo <hi>Powerful;</hi> neither is it ſuch a <hi>Childiſh</hi> reaſon, that it muſt be <hi>dally'd</hi> with, or laught out of doors, as an <hi>Author</hi> does it, with <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Tryal of the New <hi>Teſt.</hi> page 6.</note> a <hi>Legal Eſtabliſhment (even whilſt it remains ſo) legally ſubverted.</hi> It may be done Sir, without ſuch a deal of <hi>Contradiction,</hi> when People make <hi>Laws</hi> that <hi>Contradict</hi> themſelves: if <hi>Popiſh Recuſants are ſo dangerous,</hi> that they muſt not be <hi>Tolerated</hi> in <hi>England</hi> by a <hi>Law,</hi> and we have ſuch <hi>Laws,</hi> that ſet the King as Supream, <hi>to do whatſoever the Pope could have done; Papiſts</hi> may well expect to be Protected from ſuch a <hi>Catholick</hi> King, and perhaps <hi>Proteſtants</hi> owe to <hi>His</hi> Promiſes <hi>moſt</hi> of their Security: the <hi>Review</hi> of <hi>their firſt-Fruits, to the full Value,</hi> as little as it terrify'd the <hi>bright Spirits</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> may Perchance be found the ſmalleſt part of the Prerogative; and tho ſuch a <hi>Canon</hi> could not <hi>Frighten</hi> them ſo far as to comply with their <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſan</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:95944:24"/>
(if matters are to be manag'd <hi>meerly</hi> by the Laws that are made) I fear there may be ſome found that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power the Prince to <hi>deprive</hi> them of a <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> they will do wonderous <hi>well,</hi> I will not ſay <hi>wiſer,</hi> if they do it <hi>themſelves,</hi> if only for fear leſt <hi>others</hi> ſhould do it <hi>for them:</hi> I much doubt, if Diſſenters ſhould once come to be the Prevailing part in a Parliament, whether they would make ſo good <hi>terms</hi> for this <hi>Eſtabliſht Church,</hi> as ſhe might do (if ſhe pleas'd) for <hi>her ſelf.</hi> The King has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven her very good words for it, and I wiſh ſhe may not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the Benefit of them; He has promis'd to Protect, and doubtleſs will not deny her any reaſonable means for her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation: if he has a mind to do her <hi>Good,</hi> how can ſhe be angry, if he'll only keep her from doing <hi>ill?</hi> the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of <hi>Daniel</hi> could find no <hi>Occaſion againſt him, but in the Caſe of his God;</hi> but yet we ſaw the King <hi>labour'd</hi> to <hi>deliver him.</hi> 'Tis not to be doubted, if ſhe comply with <hi>his Majeſties</hi> requeſt, he will refuſe <hi>Hers;</hi> and why may ſhe not be as ſafe with an Act of <hi>Jac. 2d.</hi> for <hi>Eſtabliſhing her the National Religion,</hi> tho ſhe part with the 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> for <hi>hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up all that differ from her?</hi> It will never be the <hi>worſe</hi> Church, becauſe it cannot do more <hi>ill.</hi> And the Notion that ſome ſort of people have got in their Noddles, of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of ſuch Laws in a <hi>Church,</hi> for the Support of what is the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> is falſe both in <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Fact;</hi> for certainly, <hi>that</hi> may be ſupported without ſurpreſſing <hi>all</hi> other Opinions; and there is no need that a Jeſuit muſt be <hi>Gibbeted,</hi> and other Diſſenters <hi>Baniſh't,</hi> and <hi>Hang'd</hi> too if they <hi>return,</hi> and that <hi>Sanoumary Laws</hi> muſt be ſubſervient to an <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity:</hi> Tis no more, then if a man ſhould tell you; Look you Sir, moſt People are of our mind, and we can get a Patent to make you think ſo too; and if you <hi>wont</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what you <hi>cant</hi> believe, or believe <hi>all</hi> that we <hi>can</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, you muſt even ſuffer what coms on't, be it Fine, Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, Baniſhment, or Death; why, a moral <hi>Heathen</hi> would be divided in his paſſions at the nonſenſe of ſuch ſeverity; and <hi>Democritus</hi> himſelf in a doubt, whether he ſhould <hi>laugh</hi> or <hi>cry;</hi> and ſuch partial <hi>Chriſtians</hi> muſt Bluſh too when they blame the Proceedings of the moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King; and whom
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:95944:25"/>
they make for it too in their fam'd Antiphraſis even <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt</hi> himſelf. But one would think that doubt ſhould be out of doors, of a <hi>Church Eſtabliſht</hi> by <hi>Law</hi> not to be able to ſubſiſt, without it reſerve a Power by <hi>Law,</hi> to puniſh all others: when the <hi>Preſent</hi> practiſe of ſo many <hi>Forreign States,</hi> proves the Conſiſtency, and we have the promiſe and experiment of two KINGS Reigns, that it <hi>ſhall,</hi> and <hi>can</hi> be ſo in ours at <hi>home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis to no purpoſe, to <hi>Tattle</hi> us out of the Integrity of a good Action, with the <hi>tale</hi> of a <hi>Tub,</hi> or <hi>fool</hi> away a pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Act, with an <hi>Aeſop's Fable,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Tryal of <hi>the New Test,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>To tell us</hi> of the <hi>Conditions of Peace, that were made upon the ſurrendring</hi> of the <hi>Dogs,</hi> and that the <hi>Sheep,</hi> afterward, were worried by the <hi>Wolves:</hi> Setting aſide the <hi>malice</hi> of the Application, it is moſt <hi>fooliſh,</hi> and impertinent, when the <hi>contrary</hi> is <hi>more</hi> true, and theſe <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary Laws</hi> are to be laid aſide, and that <hi>only</hi> for their <hi>ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of <hi>blood;</hi> and ſure 'tis not the firſt time too, we have known <hi>Dogs to worry Sheep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Common gratitude to ſo good a King ſhould Perſwade this Church to Comply with his reaſonable requeſts: has he diſcountenanc'd any of them, but ſuch as have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd it by this Obſtinacy, perhaps more <hi>imprudent,</hi> than <hi>ſafe?</hi> And had the <hi>Parliament diſſolv'd,</hi> but a little <hi>conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended,</hi> I fancy there would not have been ſo <hi>much</hi> work cut out for <hi>this:</hi> Has not the <hi>King,</hi> whoſe <hi>Royal</hi> diſpenſations qualify <hi>all,</hi> prefer'd them <hi>Equally,</hi> both in <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Camp,</hi> making every mans <hi>merit</hi> his promotion, without examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his <hi>Faith?</hi> Has there a <hi>ſingle</hi> man been prefer'd to any Benefice or Cure, but ſuch as have been qualify'd by Law, tho ſome perhaps have been <hi>diſpens'd</hi> with to keep them, that for altering their Religion, they might not <hi>ſtarve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In <hi>Edw.</hi> the Sixths Reign, even from the confeſſion of Doctor <hi>Burnet,</hi> moſt of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, only for being true to their old perſwaſions, were <hi>troubl'd,</hi> were turn'd out <hi>Illegally,</hi> were impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd ſeveral years; till Queen <hi>Marys</hi> Reign. <hi>Vid.</hi> the continuance of his Reflection on Mr. <hi>Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las.</hi> pag. 63. And ſure our preſent Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op of <hi>Londons</hi> Caſe was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet ſo hard, tho ſo highly reſented.</note> Where is this mighty progreſs for the introducing of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery? The KING now is going into his <hi>fourth</hi> year, and the Church ſtands ſtill it as was four years agon; and the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Din, of the meaſures and <hi>faggot</hi> of <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> is as much to the Purpoſe, as if they told us of the <hi>fire Ordeal</hi> of <hi>Queen Emm: She</hi> remov'd <hi>all</hi> the Biſhops in no more than <hi>one</hi> year; and I think <hi>Queen Eliz.</hi> did it <hi>all</hi> in <hi>one</hi> Month: and here, ſince <hi>Appropriating</hi> of Loyalty is ſo much in faſhion,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:95944:25"/>
we cannot but ſay this for the Papiſt too, (whoſe Fidelity to the Crown is too much queſtion'd:) this <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Queen was <hi>by their own Confeſſion,</hi> and as it plainly appears from our <hi>own</hi> Annals, advanc'd to the Throne, by a Popiſh Parliament, <hi>then</hi> ſitting; and no one can tell, had they been ſitting at KING <hi>Charles</hi> the Seconds Death, of what temper they would have been, the Legitimacy of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> was then in <hi>diſpute</hi> amongſt <hi>all</hi> Catholicks; the Succeſſion of his preſent Majeſty was <hi>indiſputable</hi> by his <hi>blood,</hi> and yet <hi>Heath</hi> the Popiſh Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan and <hi>then</hi> Lord Chancellor, without any <hi>diſcontent,</hi> ſays their <hi>own</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Heylins Reformation. Page 101.</note> Hiſtorian, declares her Title to the Crown, to <hi>both</hi> Houſes of Parliament, and ſo was ſhe receiv'd without the leaſt oppoſition, which certainly does ſavour ſomwhat of an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nqueſtionable Loyalty:</hi> And if that wont ſerve, the ſame Author ſays more, <hi>That many in the Houſe of Commons that had a great zeal for their Popiſh intereſt, yet Preferred their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">page 107.</note> 
                  <hi>to their Natural Prince, before their concernments for the Church of Rome.</hi> And this is ſure more Loyalty then was ſhewn by the Proteſtant Reformers to her Predeceſſor, againſt whom they ſet an Uſurper in the Throne, contriv'd a Will, and rais'd an Army; tho ſo much muſt be ſaid for the <hi>Suffolk-Goſpellers</hi> of the <hi>Country,</hi> that they were better Subjects, then the mighty <hi>Liturgy</hi> men at <hi>Court,</hi> and aſſiſted <hi>Queen Mary</hi> with <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Arms,</hi> when the other kept from her the <hi>Capital</hi> and the <hi>Crown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queen <hi>Eliz. held</hi> more Biſhopricks in her hand for <hi>many</hi> years, <hi>many more,</hi> then <hi>this</hi> KING ſince his coming to the Crown has <hi>diſpos'd</hi> of: their Churches, their Chappels are all at their own Devotion, and <hi>that</hi> within his Royal Pallaces, and his own Walls. Upon Application of theſe very Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, has he confirm'd to them ſeveral <hi>Freedoms</hi> and <hi>Immunities,</hi> where he might have interpos'd with his <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive:</hi> Theſe undiſtinguiſht favours to all alike, one would think ſhould oblige ſome perſons not to deny that <hi>Peace</hi> to their <hi>Soveraign,</hi> which he labours to give to all his <hi>Subjects;</hi> A <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Mind,</hi> A <hi>Peace</hi> in the midſt of <hi>Arms;</hi> but ſuch only as are employ'd for their <hi>defence,</hi> the <hi>credit</hi> of their Nation, and the <hi>Terror</hi> of their neighbours; tho even <hi>that</hi> muſt be made their <note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Burnets</hi> Papers.</note> 
                  <hi>Grievance</hi> too, which by the <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>Grandeur</hi> of their Prince, is their <hi>greateſt glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:95944:26"/>
But there are many things beſides to be conſider'd; <hi>conſider</hi> but the <hi>reaſon</hi> of Enacting theſe Laws, eſpecially againſt <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Recuſants,</hi> upon whom they are <hi>moſt</hi> ſevere, and that they are now become the <hi>moſt</hi> unreaſonable; becauſe the very occaſions that call'd for them, and to ſome people ſeem'd to make them neceſſary, are now juſt none at all: the <hi>Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> to <hi>thoſe</hi> very <hi>Statutes</hi> ſeem but ſo many Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the <hi>body</hi> of the <hi>Law.</hi> It would be hard for a <hi>Judge</hi> or <hi>Justice</hi> to tell the <hi>King</hi> of his <hi>dangers from Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> when he's ſure he can put his greateſt faith, and confidence in them, and has ſo often try'd them in <hi>dangers</hi> too: but it ſeems <hi>they</hi> and the <hi>Statutes</hi> being the better <hi>Judges</hi> of it, are not bound to believe the <hi>KING,</hi> but to Proſecute his friends for <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> whom truſting and trying, he finds to be guilty of no <hi>Treaſon</hi> at all. And had not our <hi>Proteſtant</hi> offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the <note n="*" place="margin">What can e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the <hi>Church</hi> ſuffer, from the <hi>Repeal,</hi> that it is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to from the Kings <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation?</hi> And the malice of their Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> makes them the <hi>ſame.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on Declaration.</note> 
                  <hi>Peace</hi> better <hi>repeal</hi> thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> that are become but a <hi>dead letter,</hi> thenly under a ſeeming ſort of Perjury, for not putting them in Execution?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſider,</hi> if in the time of the late KING, by ſome Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Q. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz.</hi> K. <hi>I.</hi> K. <hi>Ch.</hi> before Cited.</note> 
                  <hi>Law,</hi> all the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> had been <hi>baniſht</hi> the <hi>Court,</hi> or from <hi>Acceſs</hi> to the <hi>Kings Perſon,</hi> if they had been made <hi>Malefactors, Felons,</hi> and <hi>Traytors,</hi> of whoſe Loyalty he had ſo much proof in their adhering to the Crown, would not his Majeſty have been <hi>bound</hi> to get them <hi>repeat'd,</hi> and <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> have thought it the moſt <hi>reaſonable</hi> thing in the world, that the Roman Catholicks in <hi>England</hi> have for a long time lain under ſeverity not only of Opinion, and Cenſure, but Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and the Law? even Proteſtants may allow, without falling from their <hi>Faith,</hi> or favouring their <hi>Religion:</hi> for ſuch a modeſt confeſſion in their favour, is no Vindication of the Doctrine of their <hi>Church;</hi> and their Caſe to be conſider'd here, reſpects only their affairs in relation to the <hi>State;</hi> and the matters being <hi>meerly</hi> Political, muſt be determin'd by the Maxims of our <hi>States-men,</hi> and ſo no Subject to be decided by the School-men and <hi>Divines:</hi> And <hi>ſince</hi> thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſuffer from the Conſtitution of Paſt-times, partial to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>ſince</hi> Papiſts that were once <hi>deny'd</hi> acceſs to the <hi>perſon</hi> of their <hi>KING,</hi> are now the <hi>Support</hi> of his <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſince</hi> ſuch put in but for a freedom from <hi>Penalty,</hi> and an
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:95944:26"/>
Immunity only from their being <hi>puniſht</hi> as Malefactors, it would be as great a want of <hi>honeſty,</hi> to call them <hi>Knaves</hi> for it, as it is of <hi>Wit,</hi> to think them <hi>fools.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>Abſurdity</hi> of ſuch unreaſonable Laws is ſomwhat more Conſiderable, when they ſeem not a little to <hi>touch,</hi> what is expresſly forbidden, <hi>The Lords Anointed:</hi> Let them tell me, where there is another ſuch <hi>abſurd</hi> inconſiſtency of <hi>State,</hi> where the <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> ſerve only to pollute their very <hi>Fountain,</hi> the KING; and make a <hi>Criminal</hi> of the <hi>Prince</hi> to that very Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in which he <hi>Preſides,</hi> where the Worſhip of his <hi>GOD</hi> muſt be ſaid to be an Offering to <hi>Idols,</hi> and his Converſion to a <hi>Faith, High Treaſon againſt himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then again, <hi>ſince</hi> Papiſts, as 'tis now apparent, have prov'd themſelves <hi>No</hi> ſuch Criminals to the State, <hi>No</hi> ſuch Peſts of Society, as they have been repreſented; <hi>ſince</hi> they have <hi>Suffered</hi> the Severities of the Nations <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and ſeal'd their Innocency in their <hi>ſufferings</hi> and <hi>Blood; ſince</hi> they were ſacrific'd to the Perjury of <hi>Recorded Villains,</hi> and for a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy that can <hi>now</hi> only be Believ'd by <hi>Fools</hi> upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; 'tis time ſure, after this <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of the Nation has been ſatisfy'd ſo <hi>much,</hi> even to the <note n="*" place="margin">vid. <hi>Oat</hi>'s Tryal.</note> 
                  <hi>Arraigning</hi> of it ſelf, to let them find a <hi>little Mercy</hi> too; and the <hi>more</hi> (one would think) for their Misfortunes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſider</hi> who they are that Furniſh you with ſuch diſtruſtful Apprehenſions of the Promiſes of your PRINCE; and would frighten you into Dangers and Deſpair: <hi>One</hi> of them a diſcontented Malecontent, an Exile out of <hi>your</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; a Criminal by <hi>Proceſs</hi> in his <hi>Own;</hi> and whoſe <note n="*" place="margin">Tho'by the <hi>Dr's.</hi> leave, the Lawyers ſay, <hi>Abjura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> will not <hi>Transfer it;</hi> vid. <hi>Cok.</hi> 7. <hi>Rept. p.</hi> 9. <hi>Dyer,</hi> ſol. 300.</note> 
                  <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance,</hi> if we believe him, is tranferr'd to <hi>another</hi> abroad; and ſhall the ſevereſt Satyrs, that Sedition can afford, or Rage and Malice invent, paſs with us for pure Politicks and Impartial Truth? There are <note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Dr. B<hi>'s</hi> Papers, Letter &amp; Tryal of the Teſt.</note> Others we have touch't upon, that are no leſs <hi>Notorious</hi> and Applauded, whoſe beſt of <hi>Praiſe,</hi> is in not being <hi>Known,</hi> that affect us like <hi>Vipers</hi> with their <hi>ſting,</hi> while at the ſame time, they can <hi>hide</hi> their <hi>Heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Never <hi>Credit</hi> thoſe, that endeavour to <hi>Diſcredit</hi> their KING; for ſuch as will take that <hi>Liberty,</hi> forfeit their
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:95944:27"/>
                  <hi>Honeſty,</hi> and by the very <hi>Fact,</hi> are not to be <hi>believ'd:</hi> Pray, what Attempt has he made, to make the <hi>National</hi> Religion the <hi>Roman Catholick?</hi> Which perhaps, were it deſign'd, is as little feaſible: that will alway preſerve it ſelf the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> Religion which is moſt <hi>generally</hi> Receiv'd; and untill they can prove to us, That the <hi>Revealing</hi> the <hi>Laws,</hi> will make more Papiſts in <hi>England</hi> than Proteſtants; they may make <hi>many Words,</hi> but <hi>no Arguments.</hi> Has it not all the appearance in the world, that it is the <hi>Principle</hi> of His <hi>MAJESTY</hi>'s <hi>Soul,</hi> and not any <hi>Deſigns</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> that makes Him deſire to have all the <hi>Souls</hi> of His Subjects at eaſe too; to ſuccour, and relieve the <hi>Oppreſſed;</hi> and let the <hi>Priſoner go free:</hi> if not, pray, what then Oblig'd Him to that tender Compaſſion to the <hi>French-Protestants?</hi> They are as much <hi>Hereticks</hi> to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and cannot pretend to a greater ſhare of Friendſhip, from the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of their Doctrine or Faith: They could not Plead <hi>Priviledges, Immunities,</hi> and <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> and tell the KING He was bound by His <hi>Coronation Oath</hi> to Protect them; yet'tis well known what Encouragement He has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Them:</hi> He has made uſe of His Prerogative for <hi>Their</hi> Preſervation, and even <hi>Diſpens'd</hi> with <hi>Law,</hi> for the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their Livelihood, and exerciſing of their Trades; made uſe of His <hi>Proclamations</hi> to Command our Charity; and repeated them often to preſs the Performance. Theſe are <hi>Great Truths,</hi> and no <hi>little</hi> Arguments to ſilence ſome Mens ſeditious Inſinuations; and the Celebrated Dr. would have been a better <hi>Subject,</hi> and <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> too, had he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the <hi>Faith</hi> of the <hi>Prince</hi> Palatin! he ſo much Commends, to the <hi>conſtancy</hi> and <hi>goodneſs</hi> of his <hi>Own</hi> at home; and not ſet off his adhering to <hi>their Laws,</hi> only to repreſent the Breach of Ours <hi>here:</hi> beſides, he might have been ſo Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did to obſerve, that the Peaceable and Flouriſhing Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe <hi>German</hi> Countries, is chiefly owing to that free Exerciſe that is permitted of Religion: the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches being both <hi>ſumptuouſly</hi> Built in ſome Places, and as <hi>publickly</hi> frequented; nay, in <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> Church <hi>we</hi> have known them ſucceſſively celebrate the Maſs, and the Proteſtant Service, and the Magiſtracy took
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:95944:27"/>
it's <hi>Turn</hi> in <hi>Civil</hi> Adminiſtration, after the ſame manner as the others did in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical:</hi> The <hi>Dr.</hi> would have done well to obſerve, that in theſe Dominions, there was no <hi>Forcing</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> nor any <hi>Penal Laws</hi> for it in <hi>Force;</hi> even where the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops Preſide as Soveraign <hi>Princes;</hi> there is no ſuch Perſecution, as in the Electorates of <hi>Cologn</hi> and <hi>Mentz:</hi> but the <hi>painful</hi> Gentleman muſt be pardon'd for his <hi>Elaborate</hi> Obſervations to abuſe his <hi>Prince,</hi> when he has dealt as boldly with the <hi>Trinity;</hi> and from the moſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of the Manuſcripts, made room for the Doctrin of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid</hi> his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> 
                  <hi>Arians:</hi> If he can ſerve the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion no better <hi>abroad,</hi> than by Betraying the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> he had better <hi>Diſpens'd</hi> with his Travels, and ſtay'd at <hi>Home.</hi> His frequent Reflections on the late <hi>Chief</hi> Miniſter of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Juſtice, and now the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> in the State too; as they cannot detract from the mighty <hi>Merit</hi> of that <hi>Loyal Peer,</hi> ſo they ſerve only to make up the Meaſure of the <hi>Drs.</hi> Malice: his <hi>Zeal</hi> to the Service of the <hi>Crown</hi> can never be made <hi>Criminal</hi> by the Pen of a <hi>Zealot</hi> that invades it, and he cannot but Libel the KING's moſt <hi>Faithful</hi> Friends, that ſo willingly would <hi>Abjure</hi> his <hi>own Faith</hi> and <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All Injury is ſuperſeded by ſuch Calumny, even to the contradicting of the moſt common Aphoriſm, <hi>and nothing of it will ſtick,</hi> tho' laid on in <hi>abundance: Conſider,</hi> that ſuch Mens Suggeſtions are Malitious, and muſt not, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Believ'd: <hi>Conſider,</hi> that ſome may make a <hi>cry</hi> for their <hi>Diana;</hi> tho' no one be going to intercept their <hi>Trade,</hi> or take away her <hi>Shrines:</hi> In ſuch caſes, thoſe that have no concerns of Employment in the Church, are the beſt Judges, whither She be really injur'd; for partial People, and Perſons concern'd, are apt to Anticipate Dangers, tho' they are not ſo much as in the <hi>Clouds,</hi> or Hanging over their Heads; and thoſe that are but ſtanders by, are the beſt Judges of the Fair Play: The Jealouſies of <hi>ſuch</hi> Men is a debaſing of their Function that is <hi>Sacred;</hi> when like Mechanicks in a <hi>Trade,</hi> they are afraid of <hi>Interlopers,</hi> and will give occaſion to ſay, that this <hi>earneſt Contending</hi> ſeems more for their Temporal Poſſeſſions, than <hi>for the Faith that was once delivered to the Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:95944:28"/>
If our Laws were truly like the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> that they <hi>Alter'd not,</hi> and which was inſiſted on to a <hi>Perſian</hi> Prince up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the like occaſion, for <hi>Darius</hi> his condemning of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> for the <hi>Worſhip of his God;</hi> then I confeſs the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of <hi>Altering</hi> ſuch <hi>Laws,</hi> would make the very intention of it Criminal. But when our Law it ſelf tells us, That <hi>any Subſequent Parliament, can Null all the Acts of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding, When</hi> it has been done almoſt <hi>every</hi> Seſſion, and is <hi>abſolutely</hi> neceſſary for the Conſtitution of a State; it muſt not be put upon with <hi>Falſhoods</hi> and <hi>Paradoxes.</hi> And to ſay, that if the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> are Repeal'd, Popery will then be Eſtabliſht by <hi>Law,</hi> will be <hi>Falſe,</hi> both from Inference and Fact; for ſure that is not preſently an <hi>Eſtabliſht Church</hi> that is juſt let looſe from the <hi>Priſon</hi> and the <hi>Jayl;</hi> and there will ſeveral Statutes remain in Force, <hi>For</hi> maintaining of her Tyths, Dignities and Revenues, <hi>For</hi> making none <hi>capable,</hi> but ſuch as ſhall be exactly <hi>Conformable: For</hi> preſerving the <hi>Preſent,</hi> a <hi>National One,</hi> unleſs ſhe be <hi>No Church,</hi> when ſhe has <hi>No</hi> Power to Puniſh.</p>
               <p>Don't be deceiv'd with the <hi>ſhaddow;</hi> that all things ſhall be granted to your hearts eaſe under the <hi>Next Succeſſor;</hi> this (were it not a fooliſh ſort of argument) would help me to Cap their <hi>Fable</hi> of the <hi>Dogs,</hi> with <hi>another</hi> to <hi>the ſame;</hi> but this is certainly <hi>Folding your Arms,</hi> a penſive hoping in the <hi>Shade,</hi> when you can run out and play in the <hi>Sun;</hi> and will ever it's Beams be the leſs refreſhing, becauſe it will riſe again the next day; and you are not ſure but it may be in a <hi>Cloud:</hi> but then, theſe <hi>Men</hi> that draw ſuch a wiſe Scheam of future Politicks, can they foreſee the <hi>Breaſts</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> that they thus Promiſe for them, and when their <hi>Hearts</hi> are ſaid to be only in the hands of <hi>God?</hi> Who knows but the <hi>Royal Heir,</hi> out of a Senſe of Filial Duty, and Pious Gratitude to the memory of it's Parent, will protect <hi>All</hi> thoſe that have Faithfully ſerv'd him, of any Perſwaſion whatſoever, <hi>eſpecially</hi> when ſo <hi>nearly</hi> ally'd to the <hi>very Boſome</hi> of a <hi>Prince,</hi> whoſe way of Worſhip neither is the <hi>ſame</hi> with the <hi>National</hi> here, and in whoſe Countries <hi>All</hi> Religions have been <hi>ever</hi> alike <hi>Tolerated.</hi> But beſides, with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to their moſt Judiciary Calculations, I look upon it as a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:95944:28"/>
little ſort of undecent forecaſt, to be <hi>Always</hi> Erecting ſuch Scheams for the <hi>Next Heir,</hi> both in Diſcourſe, and Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as ſeem almoſt to calculate the Nativity of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> and as if they would comfort themſelves, that his Reign wont be long; Arguments are made, Concluſions are drawn, and even Projects fram'd, with the Premiſſes <hi>Still, If the King die.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Regno H.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Stanley</hi> loſt his Head by a leſs ſevere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Treaſon <hi>Ex hypotheſi;</hi> And ſuch inſinuations ſeem to ſavour of the <hi>Prayers</hi> made by ſome Zealots in the <hi>1ſt.</hi> of <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> alſo <hi>Collins</hi> Caſe in <hi>Rolls</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. of words ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken on ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, vid. 1 <hi>Mar.</hi>
                  </note> Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> that her <hi>Days</hi> might be <hi>Shortned,</hi> or her <hi>Heart Turn'd;</hi> but for all the <hi>Condition</hi> annext, it was made <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Treaſonable.</hi> I would not have ſome men play the <hi>Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> too much, and limit the Life of a Monarch, by the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culating of his Age; the Prayers of <hi>Good</hi> men may <hi>prolong</hi> it, and thoſe of the <hi>Bad</hi> will never cut it <hi>ſhort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Future</hi> Contingencies cannot be <hi>foreſeen,</hi> but by that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> alone that had its being from <hi>All Ages,</hi> that has a <hi>Continu'd</hi> view of <hi>Time,</hi> and all <hi>Eternity</hi> by <hi>Intuition,</hi> and in whoſe <hi>Hands</hi> alone are theſe Princes <hi>Hearts.</hi> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Judgment was always fallible, and very apt to make falſe conjectures; <hi>ſome</hi> People could not think His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty would prove a Prince ſo <hi>Gracious, Merciful,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent,</hi> &amp; for that were uneaſy; and who would have thought that ſome men that inſiſted ſo much on <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> ſhou'd be now <hi>Impatient,</hi> and almoſt <hi>Diſobedient</hi> under his Reign? To <hi>Diſtinguiſh</hi> themſelves out of their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> may ſhew their <hi>Logick</hi> or their <hi>Law,</hi> but never will their <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Allegiance;</hi> I am aſham'd to ſee men labour to make <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Tryal of the New Teſt. page 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> the ſame, as if People when they have got a <hi>Capricious Interpretation</hi> in their <hi>Head,</hi> have Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to ſpoil the <hi>Common acceptation</hi> of a <hi>Word.</hi> We all know forſooth, as well as the Criticks, that <hi>Loy</hi> ſignifies <hi>Law;</hi> but was ever <hi>Loyalty</hi> taken yet, in common diſcourſe, for <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> too? we are bound to do all that's <hi>Lawful</hi> &amp; <hi>Right</hi> to one another, by <hi>Law;</hi> &amp; are we therefore one anothers <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Liege</hi> Subjects? but to take it in their <hi>Perverted Senſe,</hi> or that of <hi>Coke Littleton;</hi> to Defend this Kings Power of <hi>Diſpenſing,</hi> is the moſt <hi>Loyal Act</hi> you can do, ſince by thoſe very <note n="*" place="margin">2d. Inſt. <hi>p.</hi> 496.</note> Lawyers, the <hi>Kings Prerogative is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:95944:29"/>
                  <hi>to be the Beſt and Chiefeſt Part of the Law.</hi> But I am ſorry to ſee <hi>Church-men</hi> now aſſume this very Notion for <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Liegeance</hi> is the Proper <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and that implys an obligation of obedience, from the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign by <hi>Birth,</hi> by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> who is call'd their <hi>Natural</hi> Lord, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to <hi>Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal</hi> Laws. <hi>Vid.</hi> to this purpoſe 2 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 128, 7 Report p. 4. and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> a reſerve to their Love and Allegiance, when to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, this very quibling on the <hi>Word,</hi> was us'd, not long ſince, by thoſe they call'd <hi>Wiggs</hi> and <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> and was by the Prerogative-Lawyers of thoſe times laught at, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; 'tis the Fate always, when men begin to grow Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to contradict themſelves; as if what was <hi>Loyalty</hi> under <hi>one Prince,</hi> was not ſo under <hi>another,</hi> and one <hi>King cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe</hi> with what the <hi>other Can.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Malicious</hi> Accuſation can never carry the cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Loyalty</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> conſider in the Common Caſe of <hi>Felons,</hi> and <hi>Malefactors,</hi> the credit of their <hi>Accuſers</hi> is in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>more</hi> Invalidated then by proving any manner of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice</hi> in their Proſecutors; and pray then let the <hi>King,</hi> when <hi>He</hi>'s <hi>arraign'd</hi> (for the ſake of his Prerogative) have but as much Priviledge as a Priſoner at the Bar, when his <hi>Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer</hi> too appears the moſt <hi>Malicious,</hi> and what is <hi>more,</hi> by Proceſs upon Record, the greateſt <hi>Malefactor:</hi> the Law in many Caſes <hi>Implys</hi> a <hi>Malice,</hi> but here it is moſt plain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Implication,</hi> if you <hi>Conſider</hi> the Libells the learned Doctor has lay'd at your doors are penn'd by a Perſon that wanted <hi>more</hi> preferment here, and who for his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deameanors was turn'd out of the <hi>little</hi> he had: By <hi>one</hi> that <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Firſt Letter to Ld. Midd.</note> left <hi>England</hi> (and I believe him) <hi>with his Maieſties Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation;</hi> and by his commands was forbid to return: By <hi>one</hi> that ly's <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Proceſs and Citation.</note> charg'd with no leſs than High Treaſon, and who confeſſes in the Second Addreſs that he ſent to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary; that ſuch proceedings ſhall <hi>provoke</hi> him.</p>
               <p>Whatever is the veracity of the moſt <hi>moderate</hi> Man, he muſt not be believ'd when he rages moſt <hi>Immoderately;</hi> no more than a Bear is to be truſted when you have baited him, only becauſe before he was quiet and tame: and <hi>mens</hi> Paſſions too, in ſpite of our boaſted <hi>Reaſoning,</hi> even by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too much <hi>exalted,</hi> can <hi>debaſe</hi> themſelves ſo far as to become <hi>brutal,</hi> and then the <hi>deliberate</hi> miſchiefs they do, are the more dangerous, from the ſagacity of that ſeduc'd rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that then truly, <hi>ſells it ſelf to do wickedly;</hi> and what more <hi>Ingenious</hi> Revenge, could an enrag'd, and <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Second Letter.</note> 
                  <hi>provok't</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:95944:29"/>
                  <hi>baſſal</hi> take againſt his <hi>Liege</hi> Lord, then ſuch a pretty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, for the renouncing his <hi>Allegiance:</hi> And that he means by it more than a <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Third</note> 
                  <hi>Temporary</hi> Revolt to a <hi>forraign</hi> Juriſdiction, will appear from ſome paſſages in his <hi>own</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, when he ſuggeſts to our <hi>Peaceful</hi> Subjects here, the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Six Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, pag. 22.</note> Principle of Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> his <hi>State of War,</hi> and the <hi>Scurvy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph of ſelf Preſervation;</hi> when he inſinuates alſo that his Faith to his Prince may be <hi>Temporary</hi> too at <hi>home,</hi> and to laſt no longer than the <hi>King</hi> will Countenance or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect.</p>
               <p>What more <hi>Malicious</hi> Conſtruction can be made from the <hi>plain</hi> meaning of <hi>Expreſs</hi> words? The <hi>King Declares,</hi> no one ſhall ſuffer for <hi>meer Religion.</hi> And what ſays the Dr? Why, <hi>then when Religion</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> are interwoven, they can claim <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Ibid page, 23.</note> no benefit by the <hi>Declaration.</hi> Would the Doctor oblige the <hi>King</hi> from his <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> to <hi>Tolerate</hi> Robbers and Murderers? for it is the <hi>Policy,</hi> and <hi>Publick ſafety</hi> of the State that puniſhes <hi>them ſtill:</hi> or is it poſſible that people, when they ſuffer for any <hi>other</hi> offence that by Law is truly <hi>Criminal;</hi> can be ſaid to ſuffer for <hi>meer Religion,</hi> when by Law too <hi>that</hi> is made no <hi>Crime</hi> at all? Or would the Doctor have had the KING's <hi>mercy</hi> to have Anticipated the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of <hi>future</hi> times, and extended to the <hi>Crimes,</hi> which <hi>hereafter</hi> on the <hi>Pretence</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> they may <hi>poſſibly</hi> Commit? and yet this with prejudic'd perſons muſt paſs for Reaſon that has nothing in it of Common Conſequence; and that the Doctor may not want contradiction too (for <hi>malice</hi> will make wiſe men commit abſurdities) tho I am ſorry to ſee ſo Celebrated a Reaſoner run himſelf into ſuch misfortune, only for the <hi>defaming</hi> of his <hi>own</hi> KING: at the ſame time he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute for it the <hi>French-man</hi> for too much <hi>Praiſing</hi> of <hi>His.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In one <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of Reflection on <hi>Mr.</hi> Varil. p. 5.</note> Page of his Reflections, he makes our Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to <hi>get the better of the</hi> Monarch of <hi>France,</hi> to be more <hi>fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> in her perſecution; and to have <hi>Animated the bloodieſt of her Biſhops, Bonner,</hi> he makes her as much a Monſter as his <hi>own malice,</hi> or that of the <hi>other</hi> Sex can make a <hi>Woman</hi> well to <hi>be,</hi> or be <hi>well imagin'd:</hi> and whats the meaning of all this? Why! Here 'tis very fit for his purpoſe ſo to do, and the Doctors <hi>Satyr,</hi> muſt come in <hi>here</hi> only in oppoſition to the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:95944:30"/>
Monſieur's <hi>Panegyrick;</hi> but then in another <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. pag. 150.</note> Page, this <hi>ſame Q. Mary</hi> was a <hi>Woman ſo far from delighting in ſeenes of blood, that her Clemency was much magnify'd, and the mildneſs of</hi> that Princeſſes Reign, <hi>gave</hi> no <hi>Cauſe to complain of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor</hi> of <hi>her Proceedings,</hi> and what's the matter now? Why, the KING, the Council, the then Chief Juſtice are all to be Libell'd; and the <hi>Clemency</hi> to <hi>Wiat</hi>'s Crew, ſet againſt the Doctors <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty</hi> in the Weſt; and I warrant you, we ſhould have heard no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s being <hi>mild,</hi> had it not been to make our moſt <hi>Merciful</hi> Monarch <hi>Cruel:</hi> there is not one ſuch a touch of kindneſs to that Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> in all his Book of Reformation. But after all this his forc't Compliment to her <hi>Pious Memory</hi> and <hi>mildneſs,</hi> his excepting it as to <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> will not much mend his <hi>matter</hi> here, for let the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to <hi>Cruelty</hi> be what they will, it can never make the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Perſon <hi>mild,</hi> much <hi>leſs</hi> in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>meer Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> for <hi>there</hi> it <hi>more</hi> aggravates, and for that the Doctor might have ſpar'd a little <hi>Panegyrick</hi> upon His Majeſty, that in this point is ſo full of <hi>mercy;</hi> and if Religion <hi>only</hi> did ſo <hi>Animate</hi> Queen <hi>Mary</hi> to Blood, She muſt in his very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance have ſhed abundance, ſince that <hi>moſt dangerous Rebellion</hi> (as he calls it) was <hi>moſt</hi> upon <hi>that</hi> ſcore, tho' the Spaniſh Match was ſo <hi>much</hi> pretended, tho' I think there was as much <hi>danger</hi> too in that which <hi>this</hi> KING <hi>went through,</hi> and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity no <hi>more</hi> than the neceſſity of the State ſo generally diſtemper'd, did inevitably require.</p>
               <p>In the next place, in another page of this applauded piece, <note n="*" place="margin">Reflection, P. 54. 55,</note> 
                  <hi>To condemn a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſon in Abſence upon Attainder,</hi> is there Juſtify'd in oppoſition to <hi>Varilla</hi>'s, to be <hi>alway practiſ'd by our Law, when the Abſence was wilful:</hi> but in other of his works, and even <hi>there</hi> in the next page the <hi>Caſes</hi> of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and <hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong,</hi> are made ſo many Murders, and the higheſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions of Equity and Juſtice: Was the thing <hi>alway</hi> practiſ'd by <hi>Law,</hi> and ſhall it be, when the Doctor pleaſes <hi>unlawful?</hi> But by his leave, the two Caſes that he confounds ſo Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, were never the ſame: The firſt was an attainder in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and never queſtion'd for <hi>illegal:</hi> the latter was attainted too, but upon <hi>Outlary;</hi> and tho' the Dr. would inſinuate the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs upon his ſeiſure to be ſo <hi>unjuſt,</hi> only to have another touch
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:95944:30"/>
at the <hi>Judge,</hi> 'tis as certain that he ſuffer'd <hi>Juſtly,</hi> for to be ſure the Clemency for <hi>Revoking</hi> the <hi>Judgment,</hi> was by the Law only intended to a <hi>Voluntary ſurrender;</hi> otherwiſe the Proſecution of the Law muſt be in a ſort of <hi>Abeyance,</hi> and at a ſtand; and the KING's Officers hearing of his abode, could not Seiſe an <hi>Outlaw'd</hi> Malefactor, till he has abſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Out</hi> his Year and a Day: <note n="*" place="margin">Theſe Caſes prove, that the prejudice of the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian has tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported him to give falſe Colours to his Characters; even to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, only for the defaming of his <hi>KING.</hi>
                  </note> but it would be well if the <hi>Dr.</hi> would make better uſe of his Caſe, and take warning by it, to forbear his Libells, leſt his <hi>High and Mighty States of Holland and Weſt-Friezland</hi> ſhould be rob'd of ſuch a Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell. If this Caſe does not concern him, I know he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers all the Reformation, and how they dealt with a <hi>Dr.</hi> in Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> time; that among his <hi>Mildneſſes too of that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes Reign Story</hi> was taken even out of <hi>Flanders;</hi> and if we <note place="margin">Acts and Mon. page 2152. <hi>Lond. Edit.</hi> 1583.</note> believe his Famous <hi>Fox,</hi> cut up <hi>alive</hi> in <hi>England:</hi> His Caſe was ſo Compleatly <hi>Parallel,</hi> that I compaſſionately wiſh this <hi>Dr.</hi> may never <hi>draw</hi> the <hi>lines</hi> ſo far, as to perfect it in his Fate. His Caſe was alſo put too to the Conſultation of all the Lawyers; he was Try'd for <hi>High Treaſon;</hi> he <hi>Pleaded</hi> hard for himſelf, that he was a <hi>ſworn Subject to the King of</hi> Spain, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Fox,</hi> Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>and none to the Queen of</hi> England; <hi>that the Judges had no Power to meddle with him;</hi> however, his Plea was Overul'd with this Reſolution, <hi>That no man can renounce the Country where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was Born, nor abjure his Prince at his own Pleaſure:</hi> If this be <note n="*" place="margin">6 Papers page 21</note> 
                  <hi>Mahometan Government, Murder,</hi> and <hi>Court of Inquiſition,</hi> Proteſtants will have little cauſe to thank him for his complements too on that <hi>mild</hi> Reign, and the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy's of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> in carrying on the Reformation. <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Varill,</hi> page 55.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But beſides; theſe expedients of bringing over Perſons obnoxious to the Government from Forreign Parts; which we ſee ſo confirm'd by Preſident, even where the Proteſtant Party Prevail'd: the Protection of the <hi>States</hi> he ſo ſtands upon, may fail him too; and the ſuccour of that Country which he ſo relyes on, <hi>by leaning on too much, may like the Reed of another</hi> Egypt, <hi>run into his Side:</hi> as little as he may value Mr. <hi>D' Albevills</hi> motions to remove him, his Maſters there are too cunning to Procure a Breach with a Crown, for the Protection of a Subject that is indeed none of theirs. Thoſe that never yet dealt ſo <hi>fairly</hi> with <hi>Princes,</hi> may be
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:95944:31"/>
ſuſpected for ſuch a ſuperfluous Faith, to one that puts himſelf upon them for a <hi>Vaſſal;</hi> but eſpecially the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the Dr. may be more than he Imagines, when the Juſtice and Law of <hi>Nations</hi> will oblige them to a ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of him up; or at leaſt a ſending him away, unleſs he fancies for that reaſon, the <hi>Dutch</hi> will refuſe it. Men of a greater Figure have been ſerv'd ſo: the Earl of <hi>Suffolk</hi> attainted in <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. time, was after a long Debate, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd up by the King of <hi>Spain;</hi> and ſo was the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil. de</hi> Commines. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 12.</note> Conſtable of <hi>France,</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> to <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi> and what this Celebrated Hiſtorian muſt remember more, even in the times of <hi>Reformation:</hi> Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> demanded <hi>Morgan</hi> from <hi>France,</hi> and told the <hi>Scots</hi> when <hi>they</hi> did <hi>Both well,</hi> that ſhe would either yield him up to <hi>Them,</hi> or ſend him away from <hi>Her;</hi> and ſure He will not now <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Camb.</hi> 1593.</note> Blaſt and Blemiſh <hi>that</hi> Reign too, as well as <hi>all</hi> the reſt that have been ſince.</p>
               <p>This Hiſtorian muſt have met with too in his reading; that where the delivering up ſuch Fugitives has been refus'd, it has only been becauſe they would put them to as fair a Tryal <hi>There;</hi> and ſo it was told the <hi>ſame</hi> Queen by the King of <note place="margin">Ibid. 1585.</note> 
                  <hi>Scots,</hi> when ſhe writ for <hi>Fernihurſt.</hi> Inferiour Criminals for <hi>defrauding</hi> the <hi>Revenue,</hi> have been return'd us here, and <hi>High-Treaſon</hi> I hope is of a <hi>higher</hi> Nature: the <hi>Crimen laeſae Majeſtatis</hi> Mutually concerns all <hi>Crown'd Heads</hi> not to <hi>Protect</hi> in the Fugitives of a <hi>Forreign</hi> State, no more than they can <hi>Encourage</hi> the committing it in their <hi>own</hi> at <hi>home:</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> cannot deny it us, unleſs it be only becauſe they have nothing of a <hi>Crown.</hi> It would be an hardſhip to a Government, not to be endur'd; that an individual Subject ſhould ſeize for Contract and Debt in another Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, or by Repriſals at Sea right himſelf; and yet Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitives <note n="*" place="margin">So were the Regicides to be return'd us by the <hi>Fifth</hi> Article of the Crown of <hi>Denmark.</hi> 1660. and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh the <hi>Dutch</hi> did the ſame.</note> to find refuge for betraying even the <hi>Commonweal;</hi> this would ſubject the <hi>States General</hi> to ſuch an <hi>Incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of righting themſelves, which every <hi>Particular Skipper</hi> is capable of, that ſells but an <hi>Herring.</hi> And at laſt, <hi>all</hi> doubt is out of doors, where ſuch <hi>Protection</hi> is provided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All Impartial People, I hope, will Pardon me for deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:95944:31"/>
a <hi>Little</hi> freely with the Dr. that has been certainly <hi>more</hi> bold with His MAJESTY, and taken the liberty to Libel no <hi>leſs</hi> than the <hi>whole Line:</hi> and for the Perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of ſuch Animadverſion I appeal to all his Papers, put out on purpoſe to Oppoſe any <hi>Happy Union,</hi> and all good agreement between <hi>King</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> and for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections I've return'd, I can ſafely ſay, I have but <hi>Mildly</hi> toucht upon, and that <hi>Promiſcuouſly,</hi> the moſt Provoking Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; from one that with the ſevereſt Satyr has pointed at his KING.</p>
               <p>Such rude Recriminations on the Crown, he knew would Interrupt the <hi>Peace</hi> that is expected from an <hi>Approaching Parliament;</hi> and ſo to clear it from ſuch Scandals, and refute ſuch Seditious Argument, muſt fall under our <hi>Duty,</hi> as well as <hi>Deſign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whatever are his hopes from it's <hi>Approach,</hi> and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences he expects in its Debates, (who it ſeems is now ſo much a Naturaliz'd <hi>Dutchman,</hi> as to promiſe himſelf good Fiſhing from troubl'd Waters and the Mudd). I am Morally perſwaded they will hardly eſpouſe his Quarrel, much leſs return him ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Thanks of the Houſe:</hi> and what ever are the fond expectan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of ſome vain People, will be ſo far from <hi>Invading</hi> the Rights of the Crown, as to <hi>Confirm</hi> this ſo <hi>queſtion'd Prerogative</hi> of their King; againſt which, the follies of ſome inconſiderate Perſons do ſo promiſe an <hi>Appeal,</hi> and will more likely draw up a <hi>Reſolve</hi> to ſuppreſs ſuch Libels, than any <hi>Remonſtrance for Grievances to be Redreſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The late Ld. <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was once againſt <hi>All Teſts,</hi> eſpecially for <hi>Religion;</hi> &amp; made a Notable Speech in the Houſe of Lords a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>April</hi> 65.</note> 
                  <hi>Oxford Act</hi> being more <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd: but ſome Years after, when he had a mind to put tricks upon the Papiſts; then, <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, Praying to Saints, Sacrifice of the Maſs,</hi> muſt be all confuted, and confounded with a <hi>Teſt,</hi> when they might as well have <hi>Enacted</hi> the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> to be <hi>Nonſenſe; as poſitively,</hi> to define, what <hi>poſſibly</hi> may be <hi>None, Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry:</hi> The Notions of Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I think, were never before without a General Council, ſo Dogmatically declar'd with an <hi>Order'd</hi> and <hi>Reſolv'd,</hi> and moſt part of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World <hi>Tranſubſtantiated</hi> into <hi>Pagan</hi> with an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:95944:32"/>
If the belief of Catholicks is ſo Captivated, as to conſent to the <hi>Corporeal,</hi> and Elemental change into the Subſtance of a <hi>God;</hi> for Godſake! Would they not be worſe then <hi>Idolators,</hi> if they did not Adore? And muſt they now be <hi>Voted ſuch,</hi> only becauſe they do not think as others do? I muſt confeſs, I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thought it would have been a wiſer definition of this <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſht Church;</hi> to have made <hi>Her</hi> Sacrament <hi>more Figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> or the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of the <hi>Maſs leſs Idolatrous;</hi> for <hi>Really Preſent,</hi> and <hi>the body</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> to be <hi>verily,</hi> and <hi>indeed Taken;</hi> are Terms that muſt put us to our Metaphyſicks; and which I have not yet ſeen ſo well Explicated, as not to touch upon an <hi>Elemental</hi> tranſmutation: <hi>Luther</hi> lik't it ſo little, that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than like <hi>Mahomet's</hi> Tomb, to hang between two <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> the <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>Earth;</hi> he made up his <hi>more</hi> abſurd compoſition of <hi>both.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then for that other <hi>Idolatry</hi> of <hi>Images,</hi> and <hi>Invocation;</hi> from their <hi>plain</hi> words, and in <hi>Charity to them,</hi> I am apt to think, has <hi>really</hi> no other Exiſtence, than in the Letter of our Laws, and the reſolution of our Act of Parliament; for my ſelf have put it as a <hi>Queſtion</hi> to ſeveral Papiſts <hi>abroad,</hi> as well as to ſome of our <hi>own</hi> at <hi>home,</hi> even to the <hi>moſt ignorant</hi> Votary's: and if any can be <hi>blind</hi> Adorers, the pooreſt <hi>Plebeians, to what</hi> they <hi>Exalted,</hi> and <hi>in what</hi> they <hi>Terminated</hi> their <hi>extreams</hi> of Worſhip, when addreſt to an <hi>Image</hi> or a <hi>Saint?</hi> Why! the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> was <hi>ſtill</hi> to this Purpoſe, <hi>To the True GOD alone,</hi> look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon thoſe Material Objects, but as ſo many Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to move, and elevate their Devotions to their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and excite them to have recourſe to <hi>Him</hi> by <hi>ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſors:</hi> ſo that if we believe their <hi>own</hi> words, and men may be allow'd to know their <hi>own</hi> minds, <hi>their</hi> Church cannot be guilty of the <hi>only Idolatry</hi> that can with any <hi>Charity</hi> be charg'd upon it; <hi>A Conſequential,</hi> and even <hi>that</hi> is but a forc't, <hi>unkind, unintelligible</hi> extenſion of it; a Term that has as much of <hi>malice</hi> in it, as of <hi>Metaphyſicks;</hi> and certainly can no more make <hi>their</hi> Doctrine <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> than <hi>that</hi> would the <hi>Church of England,</hi> if her <hi>nine</hi> and <hi>thirty Articles</hi> by a mad-man or a fool, ſhould be taken for the <hi>Alcoran: Ignorance</hi> may be the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Superſtition,</hi> or even a <hi>Criminal Devotion</hi> in the <hi>Members</hi> of a Communion; when it would be madneſs to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:95944:32"/>
make the <hi>whole body</hi> of Chriſtians ſuffer for it too, as ſo many <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Mahometans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I'le tell you now the ſubſtance of ſome of the Arguments of that <hi>Noble Peer,</hi> againſt the <hi>firſt Teſt;</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">An. 1665. <hi>Oxf.</hi> Act.</note> and you ſhall ſee, whether they will not ſerve againſt <hi>all</hi> the <hi>reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ay, ſays he, <hi>It will be a great ſtep to the overthrowing of the Act of Oblivion, and reviving diſtinctions among Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That all ſuch former Oaths were ſteps to to the ſame end, that we ſhould rather think of repealing, than enjoyning them to be taken by all the Officers of the Nation, and Members of both Houſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Oaths ought to be ſimple and plain, whereas that about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was intricate and dark, and only a ſnare to the Conſciences of well-meaning men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That ſuch Oaths were againſt the Property of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it is directly againſt the Kings Crown and Dignity, that Subjects ſhould be ſworn to matters of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it was the higheſt invaſion of the Supremacy, and the greateſt attempt that has been made againſt it, ſince the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>His</hi> Arguments cannot but take with <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> ſince it was a <hi>Speech</hi> he made in their <hi>own</hi> favor, and defence, and ſure <hi>Conformiſts</hi> cannot condemn the reaſonings of ſuch a <hi>Noble Peer,</hi> who introduc'd <hi>both</hi> the <hi>Teſts</hi> againſt the <hi>Roman Catholicks:</hi> And ſo Efficacious was his <hi>Oratory then,</hi> that the Lords Iaid aſide all further conſiderations of any <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Impoſition of ſuch unreaſonable <hi>Oaths;</hi> and ſo <hi>concern'd</hi> were they for offering the <hi>Impoſing</hi> it, that they drew up <note n="*" place="margin">So alſo in 73.</note> 
                  <hi>Proteſtations</hi> againſt it, as the <hi>Invaſion</hi> of <hi>their Peerage, and the Freedom of Parliaments.</hi> And ſure, if any of theſe <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting</hi> Peers are yet <hi>Living,</hi> (as I am ſure <hi>ſome</hi> are,) their <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> their <hi>Intereſt,</hi> their <hi>Birth-Right,</hi> their <hi>Peerage,</hi> the very Judgment of their Souls, their Hands &amp; Hearts, are all pawn'd, for the <hi>repealing</hi> of ſuch Laws, when againſt the <hi>Paſſing</hi> them they enter'd ſuch a notable <hi>Proteſt:</hi> a <hi>Repeal</hi> which <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> himſelf would be aſham'd were he now alive to oppoſe: This is no flouriſh, but Argument upon the Caſe, that is kept
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:95944:33"/>
upon Record, and that in the higheſt Court; and 'tis but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting the <hi>Journal</hi> of the <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> and by that let the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of ſuch Laws to <hi>ſtand,</hi> or <hi>fall,</hi> that <hi>Honourable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</hi> when ever it Sits, will find ſufficient Reaſonings, and as much Matter of Fact, for the removing <hi>all</hi> ſuch <hi>Teſts,</hi> preſerv'd for them within their <hi>own</hi> Walls; and their <hi>own</hi> Books ſhew them the <hi>beſt</hi> of <hi>Preſidents,</hi> and a <hi>Preſident,</hi> where the Caſe has been <hi>conteſted,</hi> is worth an <hi>hundred</hi> when there has been no <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And being here come home to that, which touches the <hi>only</hi> tender Part of the Government, The <hi>two</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter of <hi>Penſ. F.</hi> to Mr. <hi>St.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Teſts</hi> of <hi>Car.</hi> 2. againſt the <hi>Catholiques:</hi> I cannot but take notice of the <hi>New Paper</hi> of the <hi>Dutch Penſioner;</hi> that is ſo <hi>diligently</hi> ſpread for the diffuſion of an <hi>induſtrious</hi> miſchief, and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the moſt <hi>dangerous Difference,</hi> that can ariſe from the <hi>debates</hi> of a <hi>Divided Houſe;</hi> I cannot do better than cloſe our laſt Animadverſions on their <hi>lateſt</hi> effort, that is ſo freſhly ſet afoot for our diſturbance: The Reaſons that it brings up in the <hi>Reer,</hi> are leſs to be regarded than the <hi>Royal Characters,</hi> that it carries in the <hi>Front;</hi> and we could <hi>forgive mijn Heer F.</hi> his Arguments (if we did not refute them) when we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo ſoon <hi>Pardon</hi> the Preſumption for prefixing to a Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, <hi>Surreptitious,</hi> and <hi>unauthoriz'd,</hi> the rever'd name of the <hi>Princeſs</hi> of <hi>O.</hi> the <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> of whoſe temper, and <hi>gentle</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, as it cannot be ſuppos'd to delight in <hi>ſeverity,</hi> and <hi>Perſecution;</hi> ſo certainly is as little pleas'd to promote any thing to the diſturbance of a <hi>State,</hi> to which She <hi>ſtill</hi> ſeems ſo neerly related; as her obliging nature does <hi>ſufficiently</hi> ſecure us, ſhe'l <hi>favour</hi> an <hi>Indulgence;</hi> ſo does that <hi>dutiful affection</hi> as morally perſwade, ſhe cannot <hi>Patronize</hi> the oppoſers of her <hi>Parent.</hi> But the names of ſuch <hi>Princes</hi> to their <hi>pretended</hi> piece, they were well aſſur'd would make it <hi>Popular;</hi> the <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> ſide is the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> too, when it makes the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> party: it was their <hi>laſt</hi> expedient that made them treſpaſs upon good manners, and preſume to make <hi>Theirs,</hi> Her <hi>Highneſſes</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>It is offer'd it ſeems, in the firſt place, that the <hi>Papiſts through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all our three Kingdoms, ſhould be ſuffer'd to continue in their</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter of <hi>Penſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Religion:</hi> I confeſs the kindneſs is ſomewhat extraordinary,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:95944:33"/>
conſidering the <hi>Preſent</hi> ſeaſon; when the greateſt Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the <hi>Paſt,</hi> could not prevail with them to <hi>renounce</hi> it: but if it ſhall be as the Paper promiſes, <hi>with as much Liberty, as is allow'd by the States in thoſe Provinces;</hi> Then I humbly conceive, that from their <hi>own</hi> Conceſſions, both theſe <hi>Two Teſts</hi> muſt be taken away; for by them <hi>both,</hi> both <hi>Peers</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> of that perſwaſion are Incapacitated for <hi>Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Employment;</hi> which the <hi>Letter</hi> it ſelf, ſays by the Laws of that Country even <hi>there</hi> they cannot; do not exclude them from: and ſure then it will ly <hi>harder</hi> upon them <hi>here,</hi> to be hinder'd from ſerving their KING in his <hi>Camp,</hi> when a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Liegeance <hi>requires</hi> it, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Coke.</hi> 7. Rept. page 4.</note> expreſs Statutes <hi>command</hi> it, and a <hi>Prince</hi> of their <hi>own</hi> Religion <hi>receives</hi> it: Shall the <hi>Dutch</hi> truſt them for their defence, that are of a <hi>different</hi> faith? <note n="*" place="margin">1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>H.</hi> 7.</note> And cannot the KING of <hi>England</hi> confide in them, becauſe they <hi>agree</hi> in the <hi>ſame?</hi> And yet by <hi>both</hi> theſe <hi>Teſts</hi> they ſo contend for, the Catholicks are <hi>excluded</hi> from ſerving His Majeſty, tho' they take up Arms only for his preſervation: So that this <hi>Letter-maker,</hi> muſt certainly fall into the <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> of this <hi>Dilemma;</hi> that the Papiſts muſt <hi>not</hi> be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted here the <hi>Liberty they are allow'd in</hi> Holland, or theſe <hi>Teſts</hi> muſt be taken away for their more <hi>free</hi> Admiſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Military affairs;</hi> and without any <hi>medium,</hi> he muſt renounce his <hi>own</hi> Poſition, or admit <hi>ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Author</hi> of this Paper that muſt paſs for the <hi>Penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner,</hi> is certainly the worſt in the world to <hi>write</hi> for the <hi>Teſts;</hi> when he gives it under his hand, that he has never <hi>read</hi> them; and for that reaſon may be a <hi>Forreigner</hi> to our <hi>Laws,</hi> as well as <hi>Land;</hi> when he ſays, that thereby Roman Catholicks receive <hi>no other</hi> Prejudice, than their being <hi>exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> from <hi>Parliaments,</hi> or <hi>publick Employments;</hi> when by the latter of thoſe, <hi>Recuſants Convict</hi> are <hi>baniſh't</hi> the <hi>Court,</hi> ſo much as <hi>ſeeing,</hi> or <hi>coming</hi> into the <hi>preſence</hi> of their <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Queen;</hi> or <hi>places</hi> where they <hi>reſide,</hi> upon pains of incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all the fearful Penalties, and forfeitures, that follow the <note n="†" place="margin">30 <hi>Car. 2d.</hi>
                  </note> violation of that Act: I hope the bare <note n="‖" place="margin">Even the Ld. <hi>Digby</hi> a <hi>Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lited</hi> Papiſt, that conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>1ſt. Teſt,</hi> us'd this as an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe <hi>it did Not Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them the Court,</hi> which the <hi>2d.</hi> does moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</note> ſeeing of their <hi>Royal Soveraigns,</hi> can't be call'd a <hi>Sitting</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> an <hi>Office,</hi> or <hi>publick Employment,</hi> and the coming into their <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> or <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>abode,</hi> be preſently interpreted a promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:95944:34"/>
to a <hi>Place</hi> too of high Preferment, ſince 'tis ſeldom de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd the pooreſt <hi>Plebeian,</hi> that never expects (perhaps) the turning of the ſpit in the Kings Kitchin. I confeſs this clauſe is ſo far <hi>for</hi> keeping them out of <hi>Publick Employment,</hi> that it almoſt excludes them <hi>human ſociety:</hi> Herds them among <hi>Beaſts,</hi> debaſes them <hi>below Brutes</hi> too; for if we believe our old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proverbs, even A <hi>Cat may look upon a King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I muſt tell theſe Politicians too, who ſo finely <hi>extenuate</hi> the ſeverities of theſe <hi>Teſts</hi> into a meer <hi>Metaphyſical Entity;</hi> A <hi>Negative</hi> ſort of Puniſhment, that only <hi>denies Papiſts</hi> to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd; that to any impartial perſon, theſe diſabling Laws, will appear a <hi>poſitive Perſecution;</hi> and that <hi>only,</hi> for the ſake of <hi>Pure Religion:</hi> The <hi>Abjurations</hi> that they force upon the people in <hi>France,</hi> are only more <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal;</hi> and with this <hi>diſparity,</hi> they that <hi>there</hi> will not renounce their Religion, muſt reſolve to ſuffer as Patiently as they can, the <hi>inſolency, ſpoil, rapine,</hi> and <hi>outrages</hi> of all the Souldiers they ſend them, which reduces ſeveral Families to miſery and want; and for refuſing the <hi>ſame</hi> renuntiation <hi>here,</hi> many perſons that have had their <hi>ſole</hi> dependance upon ſome <hi>office,</hi> or <hi>place,</hi> have meerly for that been diſpoſſeſt and remov'd to their utter Ruin and deſtruction; all the difference lying in this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween being <hi>devour'd</hi> by <hi>dragoons,</hi> or <hi>beggar'd</hi> by being turn'd out &amp; <hi>diſcarded:</hi> or putting the caſe <hi>more</hi> favourably, we'l look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter of <hi>Penſ. F.</hi>
                  </note> theſe <hi>Oaths only</hi> as they reſpect (in the ſenſe of this Letter) the keeping Papiſts <hi>out</hi> of <hi>Employment:</hi> what comfort can this be to the poor <hi>Catholiques,</hi> or what mitigation of a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Perſecution;</hi> when they are deny'd the common Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages that may make them <hi>rich?</hi> It muſt be certainly the ſame misfortune, as to be turn'd out of their poſſeſſions, that they may be <hi>ſure</hi> to become <hi>poor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot ſee with what <hi>Conſcience</hi> this late Celebrated <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter of <hi>F.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Letter</hi> can aſſert, that, <hi>neither from theſe Teſts, nor the Other Laws, Roman Catholicks are made to ſuffer upon account of their Conſciences.</hi> This is too <hi>groſs</hi> to be put upon the <hi>Dutch</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for certainly were theſe <hi>Penal Laws</hi> ſo favourable as <hi>only</hi> to incapacitate them for <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Truſt;</hi> yet even <hi>that</hi> is a ſeverity, which they are neceſſitated to ſuffer, and <hi>that</hi> for <hi>Conſcience ſake:</hi> it is but a poor extenuation of an unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:95944:34"/>
temper, when he tells us that for ſome <hi>Political</hi> ends, theſe Laws for Religion muſt remain <hi>unrepeal'd;</hi> as if the <hi>Sacraments</hi> themſelves, were only made to be ſubſervient to ſome <hi>Civil</hi> Inſtitutions, and the <hi>God</hi> of Heaven, but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to work out the inventions of <hi>man:</hi> if meerly for <hi>ſecular</hi> ends, ſo <hi>ſacred</hi> a being, as the <hi>Drity</hi> it ſelf muſt be ſo ſolemnly <hi>invok't,</hi> (which the beſt Advocates for the cauſe do ſeem to confeſs) I am afraid ſuch an <hi>Invocation</hi> may be worſe than that to <hi>Saints,</hi> and be at leaſt very <hi>profane,</hi> if not <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous;</hi> neither can it be anſwer'd us, that then <hi>all Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, all Oaths</hi> muſt be laid aſide; for the Conſequence fails them too, for the Common reaſon of Impoſing <hi>them</hi> is <hi>only,</hi> or <hi>only</hi> ſhould be, for the detecting of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> the diſcovering of <hi>truth</hi> from <hi>falſehood,</hi> whereas theſe Proteſtations call'd <hi>Teſts,</hi> are by their <hi>own</hi> Confeſſion kept a foot, <hi>only</hi> to be <hi>Injurious</hi> to their fellow-Subjects that are <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitably</hi> born to the Common Priviledges of their Country, and are ſo far from a <hi>diſcovery</hi> of what is <hi>true</hi> or <hi>falſe,</hi> that they are made about matters ſo profoundly <hi>divine</hi> and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, that it is morally impoſſible for <hi>human</hi> underſtanding to <hi>diſcover</hi> or find it out, unleſs the <hi>ſwearing</hi> to an <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> be found a ſufficient <hi>proof</hi> of the <hi>ſoundneſs</hi> of the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and the <hi>books</hi> of <hi>Scripture, Antient Fathers, modern Criticks,</hi> can be all <hi>Confuted,</hi> or be better <hi>Expounded</hi> by the <hi>Votes</hi> of an houſe of <hi>Commons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This States-man makes it ſo <hi>Incomprehenſible</hi> for <hi>any that</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter</note> themſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to go to <hi>diſturb</hi> the <hi>quiet</hi> of a <hi>ſtate,</hi> and <hi>over-turn Conſtitutions, only that they may be admitted to employments:</hi> And pray, muſt not others then think it as <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian,</hi> to have the profeſſors of the <hi>ſame</hi> faith, and their fellow-Subjects excluded from ſuch <hi>employs,</hi> which as their Religion cannot really <hi>debar</hi> them from, ſo their very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Birth-right <hi>demands</hi> it: it is <hi>falſe</hi> in <hi>fact,</hi> tho they take it for <hi>granted,</hi> that it is the Roman-Catholicks <hi>alone</hi> that do ſo <hi>diſturb,</hi> and <hi>diſquiet</hi> the <hi>State</hi> of the Kingdom; it is <hi>only</hi> theſe <hi>Laws</hi> that create all this <hi>diſturbance</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> and the <hi>ſtate,</hi> theſe <hi>eſtabliſht-men</hi> would have been loath under the <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion</hi> of <hi>Oliver,</hi> to have merited the Name of <hi>diſturbers</hi> of the Nation; and 'tis ſhewn before, that ſuffering from a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Legal</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpt,</hi> is ſtill the <hi>ſame</hi> where the Laws are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:95944:35"/>
and if the <hi>Overturning</hi> of old <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> be a thing of that conſideration, (tho hardly a Parliament paſſes in which there are not <hi>new</hi> ones made) if <hi>that</hi> I ſay be ſuch a conſiderable argument, as to make it abſolutely neceſſary for our <hi>Engliſh Catholiques</hi> to acquieſce; to continue <hi>Out-Laws,</hi> more incapacitated them ſome <hi>Proteſtant Aliens:</hi> how deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive muſt this be to the Proteſtant Intereſt ſhould the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> take an opportunity to return upon us an old <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that of <hi>Talionis;</hi> and exclude all the <hi>Reform'd</hi> from <hi>Truſt,</hi> with a <hi>Teſt</hi> of <hi>Retaliation?</hi> why we <hi>muſt</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, we <hi>muſt</hi> not endeavour for our Reſtitution, we <hi>muſt</hi> not <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb</hi> the <hi>ſtate, overturn</hi> eſtabliſhment, or repeal <hi>Laws.</hi> And <hi>must</hi> not we look very ſilly too, when by our own Arguments we have ſilenc'd our ſelves? What a formidable blow will this give to the <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> which was carried on (as ſome ſay) by the <hi>overturning</hi> of all that was <hi>Antient,</hi> and <hi>Eſtabliſht, Sacred</hi> and <hi>Civil, both in Church and State;</hi> and afford them a Scurvy Argument, That they may <hi>overturn</hi> with a <hi>better</hi> warrant than they were <hi>turn'd</hi> out; that <hi>their</hi> alterations will be <hi>only</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of an <hi>old eſtabliſhment,</hi> whereas we <hi>overturn'd that,</hi> to ſet up <hi>new Conſtitutiens?</hi> In ſhort, if they bring no <hi>better Reaſons</hi> for our Religion, than its being ſo <hi>much Eſtabliſht,</hi> it will <hi>certainly</hi> reſolve it ſelf into the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure</hi> of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>really</hi> be, what they ſo <hi>ſcornfully</hi> reject, truly <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Oxford</hi> Reaſons.</note> 
                  <hi>Precarious;</hi> for ſurely they muſt ſee, that <hi>aſſoon</hi> as they had a <hi>Proteſtant King,</hi> they <hi>preſently</hi> had their <hi>Proteſtant Religion:</hi> And that in ſpite of far more <hi>Antient Conſtitutions,</hi> and <hi>Eſtabliſhments</hi> to the contrary.</p>
               <p>I'le grant him, that every <hi>conſtituted</hi> body, or <hi>Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> whatſoever, <hi>will be willing to make Laws for its own ſafety and Preſervation:</hi> But whatever be the <hi>Policy</hi> of the State, it muſt be ſtill agreeable to the Rules of Reaſon and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;</hi> otherwiſe it proves no more than that <hi>all things are Lawful that are Expedient;</hi> and that a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> (to uſe his <hi>own</hi> terms, as well as their <hi>own</hi> Conſtitution) tho the reſult of an abſolute rebellion, revolt, and defection from their <hi>Prince,</hi> may make what <hi>Laws</hi> they pleaſe, to prevent any <hi>Caſual</hi> return to there <hi>natural Allegiance;</hi> or that an <hi>Aſſembl'd</hi> or tumultuous People, may pull in pieces even a <hi>Penſioner,</hi> to <hi>provide againſt attempts thaet may diſturb their peace:</hi> and grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too that in <hi>Political</hi> bodies, like to thoſe that are truly
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:95944:35"/>
                  <hi>natural,</hi> there will be alway ſomwhat of <hi>innate</hi> tenderneſs to their own <hi>Preſervation;</hi> that <hi>genuin</hi> Principle, <hi>only</hi> reſpects all oppoſing of a <hi>forreign force,</hi> and no way determines it to <hi>domeſtick oppreſſion,</hi> no more than if the lazy man that is ſaid alway to ſee the <hi>Lyon in the way,</hi> ſhould <hi>cut</hi> off one of his <hi>legs,</hi> that he might the better run away with the <hi>reſt</hi> of his <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſs:</hi> I am ſorry I can <hi>ſay,</hi> that this <hi>diſmembring</hi> of our ſelves for the difference of Communion at <hi>home,</hi> does no leſs expoſe us to Invaſions from <hi>abroad;</hi> but I am ſure the <hi>ſaying</hi> is as certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>True,</hi> prov'd by <hi>Experience</hi> &amp; <hi>Fact;</hi> &amp; unavoidable from theſe <hi>Statutes,</hi> and the <hi>Laws;</hi> for ſhould the beſt <hi>Seaman,</hi> the beſt <hi>Souldier,</hi> by his birth, or Converſion, be a <hi>Papiſt Convict;</hi> he is <hi>totally</hi> incapacitated, <hi>utterly</hi> impoſſible to do the leaſt ſervice to the Kingdom or the Crown: and why ſhould theſe <hi>Dutch</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple put that upon <hi>us,</hi> the inconvenience of which they ſee in <hi>themſelves;</hi> and take all the care to avoid: unleſs they would <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter</note> have the more of the Kings Subjects unqualify'd to fight for him, only that they might the ſooner invade him. Before the making of our firſt <hi>Teſt;</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1673.</note> when Papiſts Participated of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, had their Places in <hi>Parliament;</hi> I cannot remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that they did <hi>Impeach</hi> our <hi>Peace;</hi> I am ſure ſome of them did us ſignal ſervice in the <hi>Dutch Wars,</hi> his <hi>foes</hi> felt too much of the force of the <hi>Admiral,</hi> and ſo may well fear the Preferment of his <hi>friends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What the <hi>Reform'd Religion</hi> ſuffers from the <hi>Roman-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> is no reaſon at all againſt the repealing of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter</note> theſe Laws in <hi>England,</hi> unleſs they can prove the <hi>diſpoſition</hi> of the <hi>Princes,</hi> and the <hi>Politicks</hi> of the Two <hi>States,</hi> to be <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely</hi> the <hi>ſame;</hi> which as precariouſly, as it is beg'd for an unqueſtionable <hi>Truth,</hi> if but duly conſider'd, is as poſitively <hi>falſe:</hi> for the Principle of <hi>our King</hi> will not permit him to <hi>Perſecute,</hi> &amp; by the Conſtitution of our ſtate againſt Proteſtants in <hi>general,</hi> it cannot be done: for ſure ſuch a mighty Majority muſt ſecure them from being <hi>ſuppreſt,</hi> tho perhaps it <hi>cannot</hi> from <hi>oppreſſing</hi> all others; and they may as well tell us, that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> are able to <hi>Frighten</hi> the Papiſts, and ſubdue them; ſince the <hi>Reform'd there,</hi> have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways much more <hi>formidable,</hi> both by number and force, than ever the Papiſts can be ſuppos'd <hi>here;</hi> and yet even
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:95944:36"/>
                  <hi>there,</hi> notwithſtanding theſe inſinuations, till theſe late revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions in the Policy of that State, the Proteſtants were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Offices</hi> and <hi>Truſt,</hi> in <hi>Court,</hi> and in <hi>Camp,</hi> by <hi>Sea,</hi> and by <hi>Land;</hi> the truth of which is ſo plain, that to name the Perſons, would be needleſs and impertinent.</p>
               <p>It is more <hi>Dogmatically</hi> laid down, than <hi>Judiciouſly</hi> aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when he ſays, that it is <hi>Impoſſible for Roman-Catholiques</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants to live Peaceably together, when both are put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to places of Truſt:</hi> as if <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Divine Illumination,</hi> muſt only diveſt us of <hi>Humanity, enlighten</hi> us only ſo far, as to <hi>ſee</hi> the better how to fall out among our ſelves. <hi>Firſt,</hi> 'tis plain, that it is very <hi>Unchriſtian</hi> that it <hi>ſhould</hi> be ſo. <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> The <hi>contrary</hi> appears by practiſe in ſeveral of the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring ſtates to <hi>Holland,</hi> and in ſome Towns that even <hi>they ſtill</hi> call their <hi>own;</hi> where both <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Military</hi> matters, are manag'd by both; as before we have prov'd, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe ſuggeſted conſequences of <hi>Suſpicions and Animoſities. Thirdly,</hi> We <hi>our ſelves</hi> perceive none of this <hi>bad</hi> Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, from theſe <hi>mixt preferments</hi> that His Majeſty beſtows; but on the contrary a <hi>better</hi> underſtanding; &amp; it would be <hi>hard</hi> indeed, if the Examination of his <hi>Faith,</hi> muſt only qualify the man as to his <hi>merit</hi> and <hi>deſert;</hi> ſhall it be therefore <hi>hard</hi> for Papiſts in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be ſhut out of <hi>Military Employment, becauſe in the firſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their ſtate, they joyned in the defence of their publick</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter</note> 
                  <hi>Liberty;</hi> (that is, as I conceive in <hi>Engliſh)</hi> in maintaining that revolt they had made from their <hi>Lawful Prince?</hi> And ſhall it not be as <hi>Injurious</hi> a piece of <hi>Hardſhip,</hi> or the greateſt <hi>injuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice</hi> to exclude them <hi>here</hi> from the <hi>ſame</hi> Employments, when they joyn'd with all their Loyal Fellow-Subjects in the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> of their <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and in ſome caſes were more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, and ſolely concern'd in his preſervation? And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he inſinuates their being <hi>mixt</hi> ſo together in <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Truſt,</hi> muſt ſo neceſſarily cauſe this contention and <hi>Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity?</hi> nothing is more true than the <hi>Contrary;</hi> when <hi>all</hi> our Jealouſies, and Envy, Emulation, and Diviſion, have been oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd by this ingroſſing of <hi>Office</hi> and Preferment, from the partiality of the Laws; and men muſt needs be more apt to malign thoſe, that only will allow themſelves to <hi>govern,</hi> than ſuch as will more modeſtly admit any other to ſhare
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:95944:36"/>
in the <hi>Government.</hi> Whatever has been the ſenſe of ſome Church-men, they need not be aſham'd to retract their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, when the Recantation too will only make them better Chriſtians, and add the more Credit to their reſtor'd Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; as many among them never approv'd of the making men ſuffer for the Religion of their <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Church; ſo ſeveral of them unprejudic'd, thought it as hard they ſhould utterly be diſabl'd for all Adminiſtrations in the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Proteſt of the Lords a-againſt the <hi>Tests.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>State.</hi> To tell us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we were <hi>once</hi> of an opinion, we muſt <hi>never</hi> change it; is a better <hi>Rule</hi> in <hi>Religion;</hi> and if obſerv'd, would have prevented all Schiſm, if not hinderd a Reformation, but is ſtill a bad <hi>Maxim</hi> in the <hi>Politicks</hi> of a <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> for the changes and wonderful revolutions that happen in thoſe <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregated</hi> bodies, as well as in our Perſonal and <hi>individuals;</hi> which many times in <hi>leſs</hi> than <hi>ſeven</hi> years, are mouldred <hi>all</hi> into new matter, make ſome <hi>Constitutions</hi> and <hi>Eſtabliſhments,</hi> Rules and Reaſons, not only ridiculous but Impracticable; and we cannot find in <hi>Scripture</hi> too, (unleſs <hi>interpreted</hi> by the whimſeys of ſuch as ſet up for <hi>Chriſts Kingdom,)</hi> that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, has aſſur'd us he'll be with the <hi>Government,</hi> as well as the <hi>Church to the end of the world.</hi> To this Point I can only tell the <hi>Penſioner</hi> further, that <hi>Catholiques here</hi> are not made uneaſy under their <hi>perferments,</hi> unleſs it be by theſe <hi>Laws</hi> that make them ſuch Criminals <hi>only</hi> for being <hi>prefer'd;</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> may maintain with them a <hi>good Correſpondence,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſuch, whoſe Ambition would <hi>alone</hi> ſhare the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the State, or the favour of the Crown, and make of the very Government it ſelf <hi>A Monopoly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That learned <hi>Dilemma,</hi> does not pinch, and preſs the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument ſo cloſe, as the Paper Pretends, <hi>viz. That, if the Papiſts are ſo Few, the Laws have the Leſs reaſon to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd for them; and if their Numbers are much Greater, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants have more reaſon to be affraid.</hi> This ſort of ſyllogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, as ſound as it is, is as ſoon anſwer'd with another to the ſame, and that, out of his <hi>Own</hi> Conceſſions. <hi>If their Numbers are ſo Few (as he ſayes they are in Polland) 'tis hard, to hinder them from Publick Employments, when the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Safety can no ways be endanger'd by them: and if they are ſo Numerous, as he would make them in Ireland, then</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:95944:37"/>
                  <hi>we have no reaſon to be affraid;</hi> ſince where ſo <hi>many</hi> of them (and we'll imagin them, if he will, the <hi>Major</hi> Part) <hi>People</hi> the Country, <hi>Inhabit</hi> the Towns, are <hi>Intruſted</hi> with Offices, <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> and <hi>Military,</hi> the Proteſtant Religion remains as <hi>firm</hi> and unviolated, and the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the Government, as much <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſhaken:</hi> and to bring it <hi>Homer</hi> to our ſelves in <hi>England,</hi> in a farther Anſwer to theſe fearful apprehenſions that are ſent us from <hi>Holland;</hi> That, <hi>when the Reſtraints of the Laws are Repeal'd, then we ſhall ſee them brought into the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and Proteſtants find no more the ſupport of the Laws from ſuch Magiſtrates.</hi> I hope he does not think too, we ſhall have no Proteſtant Lords left, and that the Peerage it ſelf ſhall be <hi>diſplac'd:</hi> but this Gentleman, is too much an <hi>Alien</hi> to our <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> to be admitted either as a <hi>Iudg</hi> or <hi>Iuror;</hi> being utterly unacquainted, both with <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Fact.</hi> For <hi>firſt,</hi> the Eſtabliſhment of the Proteſtant Religion does not <hi>ſolely</hi> depend upon thoſe Statutes that are <hi>Penal,</hi> and thoſe are <hi>only</hi> deſired to be <hi>Repeal'd.</hi> In the <hi>next</hi> place he has forgot, or is not yet inform'd, that our KINGS from the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of our Laws, have a power to <hi>Diſpenſe</hi> with them too; which a <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Six</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, page. 25.</note> Dr. of Ours, and a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite of theſe <hi>Dutch,</hi> has made as dangerous as a <hi>Repeal,</hi> &amp; indeed, the very <hi>ſame:</hi> He knows not that his Majeſty has <hi>Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> exerciſed this <hi>Power,</hi> &amp; <hi>Offices</hi> of all <hi>ſorts</hi> of <hi>Truſts,</hi> are <hi>already</hi> in their hands, <hi>Civil, Military,</hi> as <hi>Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates;</hi> and none can be more Powerful to make Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations, than ſuch as have the Command in an <hi>Army;</hi> and yet his fearful forebodings of future Invaſions are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>no</hi> matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> &amp; makes <hi>that</hi> fail him too; the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants promiſcuouſly enjoy, &amp; that quietly with them too all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Publick Imployment;</hi> and their Religion remains as much <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndiſturb'd</hi> and <hi>Eſtabliſht.</hi> But to infer from theſe Priveleges that the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> already Enjoy from the Clemency and Prerogative of the <hi>King,</hi> that therefore they muſt have fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>deſigns</hi> than their <hi>Own</hi> ſecurity; and that they need no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a <hi>Repeal</hi> for to compleat their Happineſs, or to aſcertain their ſafety, is certainly an inference <hi>uncharitable, groundleſs, Falſe:</hi> for as they have not ſhewn themſelves ſo forward to ſubvert this Proteſtant Religion; for this <hi>four</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:95944:37"/>
                  <hi>Years,</hi> wherein they may be imagin'd to have had <hi>all</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of doing it; (and if we believe Dr. <hi>B.</hi> and the mighty influence he ſayes they had in all the laſt Reign, we may add <hi>Twenty four Years</hi> more) we muſt conclude, that it is the want of ſome Peoples <hi>Charity,</hi> that makes them ſo <hi>deſigning;</hi> and that they are <hi>only</hi> ſo <hi>Formidable,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome Perſons are reſolv'd to be <hi>afraid:</hi> but nothing is a greater Miſtake and <hi>falſer</hi> Inference, than from the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity they Enjoy from the <hi>Meer</hi> Prerogative of the <hi>Prince,</hi> to ſay their neceſſity for abrogating theſe Laws is Superſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; when their <hi>ſole</hi> Safety they muſt needs ſee (and ſo do their Enemies too with more ſatisfaction) depends upon the Life of a <hi>Merciful</hi> Monarch (that muſt be <hi>mortal</hi> too) as long as theſe Laws are left in Force for their future <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction;</hi> and how compleatly they are fram'd for it, in the loſs of <hi>All Property, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> (if theſe little things can <hi>deſtroy</hi> a man) by only being lookt upon, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. Ple appeal to any Impartial Proteſtant, whether his <hi>endeavours</hi> would not be the <hi>ſame,</hi> if his <hi>Circumſtances</hi> were ſo too; one would think that ſuch <hi>Counſellors</hi> as would Lull them aſleep with their ſeeming ſecurity, propos'd only their more eaſy ruin by ſome ſudden ſurpriſe, ſuch as are content for a time that their helpful <hi>Hands</hi> bear with them the <hi>Sword</hi> of <hi>Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice,</hi> as long as <hi>another</hi> hangs over their <hi>Heads;</hi> that will allow them a <hi>good Dinner,</hi> if they'le but take it under <hi>Damocles</hi> his <hi>Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:</hi> But Gentlemen, this is none of the greateſt <hi>Kindneſs</hi> to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement them to ſuch a <hi>Meal;</hi> 'tis but <hi>civilly</hi> telling them in the literal ſenſe, <hi>Eat and Drink, for to Morrow ye Dy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſaid ſo much <hi>before,</hi> on this ſo controverted Subject; we ſhould hardly have purſu'd it ſo much <hi>farther,</hi> had not this freſh Provocation, upon the cloſing of this Piece, fell into our hands, which any one may ſee, is ſet a foot, on purpoſe to <hi>divide</hi> the Parliament, that themſelves are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid might otherwiſe <hi>Agree</hi> in an <hi>Vniverſal Repeal:</hi> And I muſt tell theſe Contenders, as long as a <hi>Legal Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> will certainly be as great a ſecurity to all Proteſtants, in the <hi>Liberty</hi> of their own Worſhip, as any <hi>Legal Teſts</hi> whatſoever: Theſe Retainers of them, poſitively declare, 'Tis not the Proteſtant Religion <hi>alone,</hi> they are ſo tender
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:95944:38"/>
to Preſerve; For if the <hi>Bill</hi> of <hi>Ercluſion</hi> had by the <hi>more</hi> Corruption of the Houſe, been Paſt into an <hi>Act,</hi> they might as well have labour'd too for the continuance of <hi>That:</hi> Since, if I have any conception of the Politicks of thoſe times, thoſe very <hi>two Teſts</hi> they are ſo Zealous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, were directly intended againſt the very <hi>Perſon</hi> of His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty:</hi> The <hi>Firſt,</hi> moſt effectually made him loſe the <hi>Place</hi> of an <hi>Admiral;</hi> and 'twas with much ado, the <hi>Proviſo</hi> of the <hi>Latter,</hi> left him a <hi>Place</hi> among the <hi>Peers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Veneration</hi> all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects ſhould have, for the <hi>Preſumptive,</hi> or <hi>Apparent Succeſſor</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> (for in ſpite of the Sophiſtry of the late Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> the ſenſe of the Terms is the <hi>Jame,</hi> when there is none <hi>Appears before</hi> to Intercept him;) <hi>That</hi> as it was ſufficient to recommend the Contents of ſuch a Piece to a <hi>Serious Peruſal;</hi> ſo it muſt needs make it Merit as <hi>Modeſt</hi> a <hi>Reflection,</hi> did it <hi>really</hi> bear that <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Superſcription,</hi> which I've reaſon to imagin was but a <hi>Counterfeited Coin.</hi> The Preſſes at <hi>London,</hi> did more probably produce, what was their Prudence and Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to Paum upon the <hi>Hague;</hi> and if <hi>Holland</hi> had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of bringing it into light, this <hi>Penſioner</hi> of the <hi>States,</hi> was only <hi>our Dr.</hi> at <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> however, it is handled with <hi>All</hi> the reſpect imaginable, even for the ſake of thoſe <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Characters</hi> ſo Politickly <hi>Feign'd:</hi> The <hi>Name</hi> of ſuch a Princeſs, by <hi>Nature</hi> the <hi>Beſt,</hi> and by <hi>Birth</hi> Inferiour to <hi>None;</hi> we would <hi>truly</hi> revere, tho' we were ſure it was there as <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſly</hi> prefixt, as we are ſtill bound to <hi>Pray</hi> for the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> ſo muſt <hi>Her</hi> Proſperity be as much remembred in our <hi>Prayers;</hi> neither will thoſe we uſe <hi>now</hi> for the <hi>Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of <hi>It,</hi> diſpleaſe ſuch a Generous <hi>Princeſs;</hi> much leſs, Should make ſome Proteſtants ſo ſullen, as in a Zeal, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline their Church, and <hi>Libel</hi> their very <hi>Prayers;</hi> ſince <hi>only</hi> they are offer'd for <hi>Perpetuating</hi> that <hi>Royal Line,</hi> of which there are but <hi>few</hi> in remainder, and not ſo <hi>many</hi> left: and if only the <hi>Touching</hi> upon ſuch a Subject, ſhall by ſome be made ſo Criminal, for the ſake <hi>only</hi> of ſo Sacred a Title, tho' <hi>without Their Authority,</hi> they muſt pardon me that <hi>undecency,</hi> ſince <hi>Royal Papers</hi> have been ſufficiently reflected on, that have been <hi>more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriz'd,</hi> and that by <hi>thoſe</hi> too, who with greater <hi>decency</hi> might have <hi>ſpar'd</hi> their Animadverſion.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:95944:38"/>
               <p>There remains no more to be ſaid, if men will Conſider their <hi>Intereſt,</hi> Examine their <hi>Reaſon,</hi> have a regard to <hi>Equity,</hi> they will ſoon ſee that what is deſir'd, is only, <hi>To do</hi> to <hi>others, as they would be done unto:</hi> But this <hi>Golden Rule,</hi> cannot I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, guide or direct thoſe that can <hi>Outface</hi> it with a <hi>forehead</hi> of <hi>braſs;</hi> that can treat <hi>Princes</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His <hi>Enquiry</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Prelates</hi> with more opprobrious terms than <hi>themſelves</hi> would <hi>bear,</hi> or ſo many <hi>Porters;</hi> but this <hi>incomparable Impudence</hi> is only due to that <hi>unimitable Dr.</hi> which in his affected Phraſe, muſt be <hi>needs</hi> an <hi>Original,</hi> becauſe <hi>never</hi> to be <hi>Copy'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such tranſcendent inſolency ſoars a pitch beyond <hi>Imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and, is indeed ſuch a <hi>ſublime,</hi> ſuch a <hi>flight</hi> to which nothing but a <hi>brow</hi> of a <hi>peculiar compoſition</hi> could attain; To <hi>Threaten</hi> KINGS with their Characters and <hi>Life</hi> as it is that <hi>Altitude</hi> and <hi>Acme</hi> of the moſt <hi>exalted Arrogance;</hi> So it muſt be the ſureſt indication of the <hi>Profoundeſt folly;</hi> it does but bid a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyance to <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>truth;</hi> and aſſures us he can reconcile to his Rage and Calumny, thoſe vaſt extreams of <hi>Falſehood</hi> and <hi>Contradiction;</hi> it only <hi>beſpeaks</hi> the Reader to that villany, which the Author is <hi>intended</hi> to commit, ſecures him his infamy <hi>beforehand;</hi> and blaſts his Credit with an Anticipation of his Crime; the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare but <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets Memoirs</hi> with <hi>Weldens Court.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Memoirs</hi> of <hi>King</hi> Charles the <hi>Second,</hi> when ſent us from ſuch hands, muſt needs have as much Malice and Reputation, as the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>King</hi> James <hi>the firſt;</hi> and the Confutation of <hi>both,</hi> has been <hi>beſt</hi> adjudg'd to be the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of the Common Executioner; and if <hi>threatned men live long</hi> (as the Dr. himſelf obſerves) 'tis in that ſenſe alone he makes his <hi>Monarch Immortal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis time now to <hi>Apply</hi> our ſelves to an approaching <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſince the Party that oppoſes its Agreement has form'd it's Faction; and been ſo <hi>forward,</hi> as to be <hi>before</hi> us in their <hi>Application:</hi> for men that have but a <hi>bad</hi> cauſe to carry on, commonly make diligence to ſupply the defect of the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of their Caſe; and therefore the late <hi>Letter</hi> to a <hi>Diſſenter</hi> (only in a new dreſs) is now <hi>directed</hi> to a <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid</hi> Letter to a Perſon of Quality, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Perſon</hi> of <hi>Quality;</hi> whom the Author (forgetting his former reflections) has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready <hi>Return'd</hi> a Member of the Houſe, before his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty (not to mention the <hi>leave</hi> to <hi>Debate)</hi> has granted them ſo much as <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Election.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:95944:39"/>
I need not <hi>revy</hi> upon the <hi>Reflecter</hi> on the late <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Penſioner,</hi> who has only put out a <hi>Panegyrick,</hi> in the name of an <hi>Animadverſion;</hi> he'le find himſelf refuted <hi>beforehand</hi> in our Obſervations upon <hi>that Original,</hi> and there is nothing more in <hi>his</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on F</hi>'s. <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Copy</hi> beſides the <hi>Malice;</hi> &amp; that is extended even to the making of their Primitive <hi>Hero,</hi> a Puſillanimous deſerter that would keep himſelf <hi>at a diſtance</hi> from their deeper deſigns; and ſure 'tis but a bad cauſe that ſhall make a Subjects defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his Prince the very Occaſion of his Crime; His in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference from <hi>mijn heer F</hi>'s. Wit and Parts, is no more an Argument that he <hi>made</hi> the <hi>Letter,</hi> than it is a ſtronger one <hi>a Majori,</hi> that the ſame Perſon made <hi>both</hi> that and the <hi>Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and we know what Author it is, ſo much fam'd for his miſchief, that is as notoriouſly vain for the commendation of himſelf.</p>
               <p>I Shall therefore cloſe with <hi>two Exhortations</hi> to thoſe that are to <hi>chuſe</hi> our Repreſentatives, and offer <hi>one conſideration</hi> to thoſe that are <hi>Choſen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When ever the KING ſends you his Summons, let your <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections</hi> be carried with Moderation, and your <hi>Choice</hi> of ſuch men, as are either concern'd to <hi>Repeal</hi> theſe Laws for their <hi>own</hi> ſakes, or inclin'd to do it for the <hi>Reaſons</hi> that require it.</p>
               <p>Let your <hi>Returns</hi> be made as <hi>fairly</hi> as poſſible; for that which is a <hi>ſound Parliament,</hi> will the ſooner be an <hi>Healing One.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And may that <hi>Peaceful Aſſembly,</hi> when it Sits, <hi>conſider</hi> how to <hi>Pacify</hi> the <hi>Nation,</hi> and grant too, His <hi>Majeſtys</hi> Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for <hi>Peace.</hi> Let them <hi>conſider,</hi> that their <hi>preſent Prince</hi> (tho as powerful as any of his <hi>Predeceſſors,</hi> or more <hi>abſolute</hi> neighbours) does only deſire a <hi>Repeal</hi> by <hi>Law,</hi> does allow them <hi>all</hi> that <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Debate,</hi> which even our <hi>Hen.</hi> the <hi>Eighth</hi> did indeed make but a <hi>Merit of Obedience;</hi> and the Kings of <hi>France</hi> in the <hi>True</hi> Senſe, their <hi>Le Roy Vult.</hi> I never ſaw a <hi>Parliament end</hi> well, when it <hi>began</hi> at <hi>Croſs Purpoſes</hi> with their <hi>King.</hi> I remember the time, when it was thought a <hi>Pretty play,</hi> to <hi>Triffle</hi> with the <hi>Crown,</hi> when <hi>It was Ask't —</hi>A <hi>Supply. It was Anſwer'd, Popery. — It was Ask't —</hi> to <hi>Conſider</hi> the <hi>Navy. It was Anſwer'd, Arbitrary Power.</hi> Such Seſſions we ſaw <hi>end</hi> in <hi>Remonſtrances,</hi> but never in any real <hi>good</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> or the <hi>Crown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:95944:39"/>
And <hi>may</hi> we <hi>all</hi> ſay to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> as it was <hi>unanimouſly</hi> ſaid to General <hi>Monk</hi> againſt the ſitting of that <hi>Healing Aſſembly, [We will all ſubmit to the Determinations of the next Parliament:]</hi> And may that Seſſion, prove as Auſpicious, for the ſettling of an <hi>Vnion</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Peace: may</hi> it anſwer the intention of Our <hi>Preſent</hi> Soveraign, and merit the glorious Character of the <hi>Paſt,</hi> that its <hi>fame may</hi> be as <hi>laſting,</hi> as the <hi>Liberty</hi> that it gives; and that <hi>both may</hi> be tranſmitted, and continued to <hi>Poſterity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
